<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ciência médica</title>
    <description>Blog sobre ciência médica, pesquisa científica, oncologia pediátrica, farmacologia e outras ciências da saúde afins. Continuação do blog publicado em https://pharmakon.blogspot.com
</description>
    <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 12:06:36 -0300</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 12:06:36 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Marcelo Gleiser: O Físico Brasileiro Premiado com o Templeton</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;O físico brasileiro &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Gleiser&quot;&gt;Marcelo Gleiser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; é reconhecido internacionalmente por suas contribuições à ciência e à divulgação científica. Em 2019, tornou-se o primeiro latino-americano e o único brasileiro a receber o prestigioso &lt;strong&gt;Prêmio Templeton&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;premio-templeton&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;premio-templeton&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prêmio Templeton:&lt;/strong&gt; Prêmio internacional criado em 1972 para reconhecer pessoas que contribuem de forma excepcional para afirmar a dimensão espiritual da vida, seja por meio de descobertas científicas, filosóficas ou ações práticas.&lt;/span&gt;
, um dos maiores prêmios internacionais concedidos a cientistas e pensadores que ampliam a compreensão da humanidade sobre a existência. O próprio Gleiser se define como agnóstico, defendendo o diálogo entre ciência e espiritualidade. &lt;label for=&quot;agnosticismo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;agnosticismo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agnosticismo:&lt;/strong&gt; Posição filosófica segundo a qual não é possível afirmar nem negar a existência de Deus, do divino ou de realidades metafísicas, por falta de evidências suficientes. O agnosticismo é comum em debates sobre ciência e espiritualidade.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;biografia-e-formação&quot;&gt;Biografia e Formação&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcelo Gleiser nasceu em 19 de março de 1959, no Rio de Janeiro. De família judaica, ele conta que, no seu Bar Mitzvah&lt;label for=&quot;bar-mitzvah&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;bar-mitzvah&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bar Mitzvah:&lt;/strong&gt; Cerimônia judaica que marca a maioridade religiosa de meninos aos 13 anos. Após o Bar Mitzvah, o jovem passa a ser responsável por seus atos perante a lei judaica e pode participar plenamente dos rituais religiosos.&lt;/span&gt;
, ganhou de sua tia uma foto autografada de Einstein.  Na foto estão Einstein e Isidoro Kohn, tio da madrasta de Gleiser. O avô paterno de Gleiser também acompanhou Einstein nessa visita ao Rio, em 1925. Segundo o relato familiar, Isidoro emprestou a gravata que Einstein usa na foto. Esta foto inspirou Marcelo Gleiser, então um adolescente fascinado pela natureza, a buscar uma carreira na física. Em seu livro “&lt;a href=&quot;#escritor-e-divulgador-científico&quot;&gt;Criação Imperfeita&lt;/a&gt;”, ele relata que, após a morte da mãe, passou por um período difícil de incertezas, e a busca de conhecimento científico foi uma das coisas que o ajudou a superar. Outra foi o esporte, tendo jogado vôlei e participado inclusive da vitória do time brasileiro no campeaonato junior em 1974, junto com &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernardinho&quot;&gt;Bernardinho&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ciencia-medica/assets/img/einstein-gleiser.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Einstein no Brasil em 1925&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Albert Einstein e Isidoro Kohn, amigo do avô paterno e tio da madrasta de Marcelo Gleiser, no Brasil em 1925. Kohn havia emprestado a gravata que Einstein está usando na foto.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estudou física na Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), onde se graduou em 1981. Em seguida, fez mestrado no Instituto de Física Teórica da Universidade Estadual Paulista (IFT-Unesp), com a dissertação intitulada “Soluções de Vórtice em Teorias de Gauge Abelianas e Não-Abelianas” (1982), sob orientação do Prof. Dr. Mario Novello. Nesse trabalho, Gleiser estudou estruturas chamadas “vórtices” — regiões onde campos físicos se organizam de modo semelhante a redemoinhos — em teorias fundamentais da física, buscando entender como padrões e estruturas podem surgir espontaneamente na natureza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posteriormente, fez doutorado (PhD) em física teórica na King’s College London, Reino Unido, concluído em 1986, sob orientação do Prof. Dr. Michael E. Fisher. Sua tese, intitulada “Phase Transitions in the Early Universe” (Transições de Fase no Universo Primordial), investigou como mudanças bruscas e fundamentais — semelhantes à transformação da água em gelo — podem ter ocorrido nos primeiros instantes do universo, influenciando a formação de estruturas cósmicas e a evolução do cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Após o doutorado, trabalhou como pesquisador de pós-doutorado no Fermilab (Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory), nos Estados Unidos, sob supervisão do físico Edward W. Kolb (Rocky Kolb), referência mundial em cosmologia física. Lá, Gleiser desenvolveu pesquisas independentes e colaborativas em cosmologia teórica, especialmente sobre transições de fase no universo primordial e a formação de estruturas cósmicas. Seu trabalho resultou em publicações científicas importantes, aprofundando a conexão entre física de partículas e a evolução do universo logo após o Big Bang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Em seguida, trabalhou também no Instituto de Física Teórica da Unesp, onde colaborou com grupos de pesquisa em física teórica e cosmologia, orientou jovens pesquisadores e participou de projetos sobre simetrias fundamentais, formação de estruturas no universo e modelos de matéria exótica. Sua atuação contribuiu para fortalecer a pesquisa em cosmologia no Brasil e ampliar o intercâmbio científico internacional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ao longo de sua carreira, Gleiser também orientou e influenciou diversos jovens cientistas, tanto no Brasil quanto no exterior, como &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sara_Imari_Walker&quot;&gt;Sara Imari Walker&lt;/a&gt;. Sua atuação como mentor contribuiu para formar uma nova geração de pesquisadores em física teórica e cosmologia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Em 1991, ingressou como professor no Dartmouth College, nos Estados Unidos, onde atua até hoje como professor titular de física e astronomia, ocupando a cátedra Appleton Professor of Natural Philosophy, um dos títulos mais prestigiosos da instituição.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trabalhos-destacados&quot;&gt;Trabalhos Destacados&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gleiser é especialista em cosmologia&lt;label for=&quot;cosmologia&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;cosmologia&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cosmologia:&lt;/strong&gt; Ramo da ciência que estuda a origem, estrutura, evolução e eventual destino do universo como um todo, integrando conhecimentos da física, astronomia e filosofia.&lt;/span&gt;
, física de partículas e astrobiologia&lt;label for=&quot;astrobiologia&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;astrobiologia&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astrobiologia:&lt;/strong&gt; Área interdisciplinar que investiga a origem, evolução, distribuição e futuro da vida no universo, incluindo a busca por vida em outros planetas.&lt;/span&gt;
.   Destacou-se por pesquisas sobre a origem e evolução do universo, simetrias fundamentais, transições de fase cósmicas e a busca por vida fora da Terra. Publicou mais de 100 artigos científicos e é referência internacional em temas como quebra de simetria e formação de estruturas cósmicas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entre seus trabalhos de maior destaque está a proposta do “Princípio da Vida Rara” (Rare Life Principle), em que Gleiser argumenta que a vida complexa no universo pode ser muito mais rara do que se imagina, devido à combinação de fatores físicos, químicos e biológicos necessários para sua emergência. Ele também contribuiu para o debate sobre a definição de vida e os limites da habitabilidade planetária, sendo referência internacional em astrobiologia. Gleiser participou de colaborações com a NASA e outros centros de pesquisa, discutindo as condições para a existência de vida fora da Terra e os desafios da busca por biossinais em exoplanetas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;o-prêmio-templeton&quot;&gt;O Prêmio Templeton&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O Prêmio Templeton foi criado em 1972 pelo filantropo britânico John Templeton para reconhecer pessoas que “contribuem de maneira excepcional para afirmar a dimensão espiritual da vida, seja por meio de insights, descobertas ou trabalhos práticos”. O valor do prêmio supera o do Nobel, e já foi concedido a nomes como Madre Teresa de Calcutá (a primeira laureada), Dalai Lama, Desmond Tutu, Charles Taylor, Freeman Dyson e Martin Rees. O Templeton é considerado um dos maiores reconhecimentos mundiais para cientistas, filósofos e líderes espirituais, e frequentemente é comparado ao Nobel em prestígio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcelo Gleiser foi o primeiro latino-americano e o único brasileiro a receber o Templeton, em 2019. A cerimônia ocorreu em Nova York, nos Estados Unidos. Gleiser foi agraciado por seu trabalho pioneiro ao explorar as grandes questões da existência humana, a relação entre ciência e espiritualidade, e por sua defesa do diálogo entre diferentes formas de conhecimento.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/06/Marcelo_Gleiser_no_Fronteiras_do_Pensamento_Florian%C3%B3polis_2013_%2810277998645%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Marcelo Gleiser&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Marcelo Gleiser no Fronteiras do Pensamento (Florianópolis, 2013).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;escritor-e-divulgador-científico&quot;&gt;Escritor e Divulgador Científico&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Além da carreira acadêmica, Gleiser é um dos mais influentes divulgadores científicos do Brasil e do mundo. &lt;label for=&quot;divulgacao-cientifica&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;divulgacao-cientifica&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Divulgação científica:&lt;/strong&gt; Atividade de comunicar conhecimentos científicos para o público leigo, tornando a ciência acessível e compreensível, e promovendo o pensamento crítico na sociedade.&lt;/span&gt;
 Sua trajetória como escritor começou com um impacto notável, e ele se consolidou como uma voz que une a complexidade da ciência à busca humana por significado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seu primeiro livro, &lt;strong&gt;‘A Dança do Universo’&lt;/strong&gt;, foi publicado em 1997 pela editora &lt;strong&gt;Companhia das Letras&lt;/strong&gt;. A obra rapidamente se tornou um best-seller no Brasil e foi agraciada com o &lt;strong&gt;Prêmio Jabuti&lt;/strong&gt; em 1998, consolidando Gleiser como um dos principais nomes da divulgação científica no país.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suas principais obras, traduzidas para mais de 15 idiomas, incluem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘A Dança do Universo’ (1997):&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Título em Inglês:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;‘The Dancing Universe’&lt;/em&gt;
Neste livro, Gleiser traça um panorama da história do pensamento cosmológico, desde os mitos de criação antigos até as teorias científicas modernas, como o Big Bang e a física de partículas. O livro foi um marco na divulgação científica no Brasil por sua linguagem acessível e por conectar a ciência com a filosofia e a busca humana por suas origens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘O Fim da Terra e do Céu’ (2001):&lt;/strong&gt;
Gleiser explora a fascinação humana com o fim do mundo, analisando mitos apocalípticos, profecias religiosas e previsões científicas sobre o destino final do universo. A obra discute como a ciência moderna oferece novas narrativas sobre o fim, substituindo o medo pela compreensão racional dos processos cósmicos. Ganhou o Prêmio Jabuti em 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘Criação Imperfeita’ (2010):&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Título em Inglês:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;‘A Tear at the Edge of Creation’&lt;/em&gt; 
Publicado no Brasil com o título ‘Criação Imperfeita’, este livro argumenta que as assimetrias e “imperfeições” encontradas na natureza — desde o nível subatômico até as estruturas cósmicas — são a chave para a existência do universo como o conhecemos. A obra desafia a noção de um “design perfeito” e celebra a criatividade inerente aos processos naturais. Ao privilegiar uma visão onde a busca pela ordem perfeita como fundamento da realidade é substituída pela “imperfeição”, pela assimetria como origem dos principais fenômenos que observamos, Gleiser recupera, de certa forma, uma visão epicurista (vazio e partículas movendo-se aleatoriamente) dos fundamentos do conhecimento, em contraste com o platonismo que parece ter sido predominante no pensamento ocidental e está, na verdade, cada vez mais forte.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘A Ilha do Conhecimento’ (2014):&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Título em Inglês:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;‘The Island of Knowledge’&lt;/em&gt;
Usando a metáfora de uma “ilha de conhecimento” em um “oceano de desconhecido”, Gleiser defende que, quanto mais aprendemos sobre o universo, mais vasta se torna a fronteira com o que não sabemos. O livro é uma reflexão sobre os limites da ciência e a importância de reconhecer o mistério como motor da busca humana por conhecimento.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘A Simples Beleza do Inesperado’ (2016):&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Título em Inglês:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;‘The Simple Beauty of the Unexpected’&lt;/em&gt; (publicado em 2016)
Nesta coletânea de ensaios, Gleiser conecta conceitos científicos a experiências cotidianas, explorando temas como o tempo, a vida, a morte e a busca pela felicidade. A obra convida o leitor a encontrar o maravilhamento e a beleza na ciência e no mundo ao seu redor, reforçando uma visão humanista do conhecimento científico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘O Despertar do Universo Consciente’ (2024):&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Título em Inglês:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;‘The Dawn of a Mindful Universe’&lt;/em&gt; (publicado em 2023)
Copérnico inaugurou uma linha de pensamento (epitomizada pelo princípio que leva seu nome) que tem retirado progressivamente o protagonismo do ser humano da sua própria noção de compreensão do mundo. “Um partícula insignificante em um universo vasto e frio” tornou-se a visão de uma humanidade com uma perspectiva cada vez mais sombria, e Gleiser atribui isso à perda da fagulha da curiosidade, da missão moral e do foco compassivo da ciência. Ele nos convida a recuperar esse sentimento, reconstruir um novo Iluminismo visando salvar a civilização e dar uma nova direção à humanidade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Além dos livros, Gleiser é colunista, apresentador de programas de TV e rádio, e fundador do Institute for Cross-Disciplinary Engagement (ICE). Nos últimos anos, tem se dedicado a campanhas pela valorização da ciência, do pensamento crítico e pela conservação do planeta, alertando para a urgência de ações em defesa do meio ambiente e da vida na Terra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nos últimos anos, Gleiser tem se dedicado a campanhas pela valorização da ciência, do pensamento crítico e pela conservação do planeta, alertando para a urgência de ações em defesa do meio ambiente e da vida na Terra. Uma de suas iniciativas mais recentes é o Podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;opi=89978449&amp;amp;url=https://www.youtube.com/watch%3Fv%3DGXXOl35LA1U&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjS3aiwnZiOAxU0rZUCHXUqOWMQwqsBegQIDRAG&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2hH0FDW6gDQlqdmN4mez51&quot;&gt;The Blind Spot&lt;/a&gt;, protagonizado por Gleiser, o físico e divulgador científico Adam Frank, da Universidade de Rochester e o filósofo Evan Thompson, da Universidade da Colúmbia Britânica. No primeiro episódio eles discutiram a natureza do conhecimento, da objetividade e da ciência, e as relações do projeto filosófico e científico ocidental com as religiões monoteístas, um tema recorrente na obra de Gleiser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;referências&quot;&gt;Referências&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.templetonprize.org/laureate/marcelo-gleiser/&quot;&gt;Templeton Prize - Official Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Gleiser&quot;&gt;Wikipedia: Marcelo Gleiser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Templeton_Prize&quot;&gt;Wikipedia: Templeton Prize&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/24/marcelo-gleiser-templeton.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/24/marcelo-gleiser-templeton.html</guid>
        
        <category>Física</category>
        
        <category>Marcelo Gleiser</category>
        
        <category>Templeton</category>
        
        <category>Divulgação científica</category>
        
        <category>Prêmios internacionais</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Marcelo Gleiser: El físico brasileño premiado con el Templeton</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;El físico brasileño &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Gleiser&quot;&gt;Marcelo Gleiser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; es reconocido internacionalmente por sus contribuciones a la ciencia y a la divulgación científica. En 2019, se convirtió en el primer latinoamericano y el único brasileño en recibir el prestigioso &lt;strong&gt;Premio Templeton&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;premio-templeton-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;premio-templeton-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Premio Templeton:&lt;/strong&gt; Premio internacional creado en 1972 para reconocer a personas que contribuyen de manera excepcional a afirmar la dimensión espiritual de la vida, ya sea mediante descubrimientos científicos, reflexiones filosóficas o acciones prácticas.&lt;/span&gt;
, uno de los premios más importantes del mundo para científicos y pensadores que amplían la comprensión de la existencia humana. El propio Gleiser se define como agnóstico, defendiendo el diálogo entre ciencia y espiritualidad. &lt;label for=&quot;agnosticismo-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;agnosticismo-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agnosticismo:&lt;/strong&gt; Posición filosófica según la cual no es posible afirmar ni negar la existencia de Dios, de lo divino o de realidades metafísicas, por falta de pruebas suficientes. El agnosticismo es común en debates sobre ciencia y espiritualidad.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;biografía-y-formación&quot;&gt;Biografía y Formación&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcelo Gleiser nació el 19 de marzo de 1959 en Río de Janeiro. De familia judía, cuenta que en su Bar Mitzvah&lt;label for=&quot;bar-mitzvah-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;bar-mitzvah-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bar Mitzvah:&lt;/strong&gt; Ceremonia judía que marca la mayoría de edad religiosa de los niños a los 13 años. Después del Bar Mitzvah, el joven es responsable de sus actos según la ley judía y puede participar plenamente en los rituales religiosos.&lt;/span&gt;
 recibió de su tía una foto autografiada de Einstein. En la foto están Einstein e Isidoro Kohn, tío de su madrastra. El abuelo paterno de Gleiser también acompañó a Einstein en esa visita a Río en 1925. Según el relato familiar, Isidoro prestó la corbata que Einstein usa en la foto. Esta foto inspiró a Marcelo Gleiser, entonces un adolescente fascinado por la naturaleza, a buscar una carrera en la física. En su libro “&lt;a href=&quot;#escritor-y-divulgador-cientifico&quot;&gt;Criação Imperfeita&lt;/a&gt;”, relata que, tras la muerte de su madre, pasó por un período difícil de incertidumbre, y la búsqueda de conocimiento científico fue una de las cosas que le ayudó a superarlo. Otra fue el deporte, habiendo jugado voleibol y participado incluso en la victoria del equipo juvenil brasileño en 1974, junto a &lt;a href=&quot;https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernardo_Resende&quot;&gt;Bernardinho&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ciencia-medica/assets/img/einstein-gleiser.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Einstein en Brasil, 1925&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Albert Einstein e Isidoro Kohn, amigo del abuelo paterno y tío de la madrastra de Marcelo Gleiser, en Brasil en 1925. Kohn había prestado la corbata que Einstein usa en la foto.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estudió física en la Universidad Federal de Río de Janeiro (UFRJ), donde se graduó en 1981. Luego obtuvo una maestría en el Instituto de Física Teórica de la Universidad Estatal Paulista (IFT-Unesp), con la disertación titulada “Soluciones de vórtice en teorías de gauge abelianas y no abelianas” (1982), bajo la supervisión del Prof. Dr. Mario Novello. En ese trabajo, Gleiser estudió estructuras llamadas “vórtices”—regiones donde los campos físicos se organizan de manera similar a los remolinos—en teorías fundamentales de la física, buscando entender cómo los patrones y estructuras pueden surgir espontáneamente en la naturaleza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posteriormente, realizó su doctorado (PhD) en física teórica en el King’s College London, Reino Unido, finalizado en 1986 bajo la orientación del Prof. Dr. Michael E. Fisher. Su tesis, titulada “Transiciones de fase en el universo primitivo”, investigó cómo cambios bruscos y fundamentales—similares a la transformación del agua en hielo—pudieron haber ocurrido en los primeros instantes del universo, influyendo en la formación de estructuras cósmicas y la evolución del cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tras el doctorado, trabajó como investigador posdoctoral en Fermilab (Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory), en Estados Unidos, bajo la supervisión del físico Edward W. Kolb (Rocky Kolb), referencia mundial en cosmología física. Allí, Gleiser desarrolló investigaciones independientes y colaborativas en cosmología teórica, especialmente sobre transiciones de fase en el universo primitivo y la formación de estructuras cósmicas. Su trabajo resultó en importantes publicaciones científicas, profundizando la conexión entre la física de partículas y la evolución del universo tras el Big Bang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luego trabajó también en el Instituto de Física Teórica de la Unesp, donde colaboró con grupos de investigación en física teórica y cosmología, orientó a jóvenes investigadores y participó en proyectos sobre simetrías fundamentales, formación de estructuras en el universo y modelos de materia exótica. Su actuación contribuyó a fortalecer la investigación en cosmología en Brasil y ampliar el intercambio científico internacional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lo largo de su carrera, Gleiser también orientó e influyó en numerosos jóvenes científicos, tanto en Brasil como en el extranjero, como &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sara_Imari_Walker&quot;&gt;Sara Imari Walker&lt;/a&gt;. Su papel como mentor ayudó a formar una nueva generación de investigadores en física teórica y cosmología.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En 1991, ingresó como profesor en Dartmouth College, en Estados Unidos, donde actúa hasta hoy como profesor titular de física y astronomía, ocupando la cátedra Appleton Professor of Natural Philosophy, uno de los títulos más prestigiosos de la institución.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trabajos-destacados&quot;&gt;Trabajos Destacados&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gleiser es especialista en cosmología&lt;label for=&quot;cosmologia-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;cosmologia-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cosmología:&lt;/strong&gt; Rama de la ciencia que estudia el origen, la estructura, la evolución y el destino final del universo en su conjunto, integrando conocimientos de física, astronomía y filosofía.&lt;/span&gt;
, física de partículas y astrobiología&lt;label for=&quot;astrobiologia-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;astrobiologia-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astrobiología:&lt;/strong&gt; Campo interdisciplinario que investiga el origen, la evolución, la distribución y el futuro de la vida en el universo, incluyendo la búsqueda de vida en otros planetas.&lt;/span&gt;
. Se destacó por investigaciones sobre el origen y la evolución del universo, simetrías fundamentales, transiciones de fase cósmicas y la búsqueda de vida fuera de la Tierra. Publicó más de 100 artículos científicos y es referencia internacional en temas como ruptura de simetría y formación de estructuras cósmicas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entre sus trabajos más destacados está la propuesta del “Principio de la Vida Rara”, en la que Gleiser argumenta que la vida compleja en el universo puede ser mucho más rara de lo que se imagina, debido a la combinación de factores físicos, químicos y biológicos necesarios para su surgimiento. También contribuyó al debate sobre la definición de vida y los límites de la habitabilidad planetaria, siendo referencia internacional en astrobiología. Gleiser participó en colaboraciones con la NASA y otros centros de investigación, discutiendo las condiciones para la existencia de vida fuera de la Tierra y los desafíos de la búsqueda de bioseñales en exoplanetas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;el-premio-templeton&quot;&gt;El Premio Templeton&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El Premio Templeton fue creado en 1972 por el filántropo británico John Templeton para reconocer a personas que “contribuyen de manera excepcional a afirmar la dimensión espiritual de la vida, ya sea mediante reflexiones, descubrimientos o trabajos prácticos”. &lt;label for=&quot;premio-templeton-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;premio-templeton-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Premio Templeton:&lt;/strong&gt; Premio internacional creado en 1972 para reconocer a personas que contribuyen de manera excepcional a afirmar la dimensión espiritual de la vida, ya sea mediante descubrimientos científicos, reflexiones filosóficas o acciones prácticas.&lt;/span&gt;
 El valor del premio supera al del Nobel, y ya ha sido concedido a nombres como la Madre Teresa de Calcuta (la primera galardonada), el Dalai Lama, Desmond Tutu, Charles Taylor, Freeman Dyson y Martin Rees. El Templeton es considerado uno de los mayores reconocimientos mundiales para científicos, filósofos y líderes espirituales, y a menudo se lo compara con el Nobel en prestigio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcelo Gleiser fue el primer latinoamericano y el único brasileño en recibir el Templeton, en 2019. La ceremonia tuvo lugar en Nueva York, Estados Unidos. Gleiser fue galardonado por su trabajo pionero al explorar las grandes cuestiones de la existencia humana, la relación entre ciencia y espiritualidad, y por su defensa del diálogo entre diferentes formas de conocimiento.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/06/Marcelo_Gleiser_no_Fronteiras_do_Pensamento_Florian%C3%B3polis_2013_%2810277998645%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Marcelo Gleiser&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Marcelo Gleiser en Fronteiras do Pensamento (Florianópolis, 2013).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;escritor-y-divulgador-científico&quot;&gt;Escritor y Divulgador Científico&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Además de su carrera académica, Gleiser es uno de los divulgadores científicos más influyentes de Brasil y del mundo. &lt;label for=&quot;divulgacao-cientifica-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;divulgacao-cientifica-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Divulgación científica:&lt;/strong&gt; Actividad de comunicar conocimientos científicos al público general, haciendo la ciencia accesible y comprensible, y promoviendo el pensamiento crítico en la sociedad.&lt;/span&gt;
 Su trayectoria como escritor comenzó con un impacto notable, y se consolidó como una voz que une la complejidad de la ciencia con la búsqueda humana de significado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Su primer libro, &lt;strong&gt;‘La Danza del Universo’&lt;/strong&gt;, fue publicado en 1997 por la editorial &lt;strong&gt;Companhia das Letras&lt;/strong&gt;. La obra rápidamente se convirtió en un best-seller en Brasil y fue galardonada con el &lt;strong&gt;Premio Jabuti&lt;/strong&gt; en 1998, consolidando a Gleiser como uno de los principales nombres de la divulgación científica en el país.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sus principales obras, traducidas a más de 15 idiomas, incluyen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘A Dança do Universo’ (1997) (“La Danza del Universo”):&lt;/strong&gt;
En este libro, Gleiser traza un panorama de la historia del pensamiento cosmológico, desde los mitos de creación antiguos hasta las teorías científicas modernas, como el Big Bang y la física de partículas. El libro fue un hito en la divulgación científica en Brasil por su lenguaje accesible y por conectar la ciencia con la filosofía y la búsqueda humana de sus orígenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘O Fim da Terra e do Céu’ (2001) (“El Fin de la Tierra y del Cielo”):&lt;/strong&gt;
Gleiser explora la fascinación humana con el fin del mundo, analizando mitos apocalípticos, profecías religiosas y predicciones científicas sobre el destino final del universo. La obra discute cómo la ciencia moderna ofrece nuevas narrativas sobre el fin, sustituyendo el miedo por la comprensión racional de los procesos cósmicos. Ganó el Premio Jabuti en 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘Criação Imperfeita’ (2010) (“Creación Imperfecta”):&lt;/strong&gt;
Publicado en Brasil como ‘Criação Imperfeita’, este libro argumenta que las asimetrías e “imperfecciones” encontradas en la naturaleza—desde el nivel subatómico hasta las estructuras cósmicas—son la clave para la existencia del universo tal como lo conocemos. La obra desafía la noción de un “diseño perfecto” y celebra la creatividad inherente a los procesos naturales. Al privilegiar una visión donde la búsqueda del orden perfecto como fundamento de la realidad es sustituida por la “imperfección”, por la asimetría como origen de los principales fenómenos que observamos, Gleiser recupera, de cierta forma, una visión epicúrea (vacío y partículas moviéndose aleatoriamente) de los fundamentos del conocimiento, en contraste con el platonismo que parece haber predominado en el pensamiento occidental y que, de hecho, es cada vez más fuerte.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘A Ilha do Conhecimento’ (2014) (“La Isla del Conocimiento”):&lt;/strong&gt;
Usando la metáfora de una “isla de conocimiento” en un “océano de lo desconocido”, Gleiser defiende que, cuanto más aprendemos sobre el universo, más vasta se vuelve la frontera con lo que no sabemos. El libro es una reflexión sobre los límites de la ciencia y la importancia de reconocer el misterio como motor de la búsqueda humana de conocimiento.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘A Simples Beleza do Inesperado’ (2016) (“La Simple Belleza de lo Inesperado”):&lt;/strong&gt;
En esta colección de ensayos, Gleiser conecta conceptos científicos con experiencias cotidianas, explorando temas como el tiempo, la vida, la muerte y la búsqueda de la felicidad. La obra invita al lector a encontrar el asombro y la belleza en la ciencia y en el mundo que lo rodea, reforzando una visión humanista del conocimiento científico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘El Universo Consciente’ (2024):&lt;/strong&gt;
Copérnico inauguró una línea de pensamiento (epitomizada por el principio que lleva su nombre) que ha ido retirando progresivamente el protagonismo del ser humano de su propia noción de comprensión del mundo. “Una partícula insignificante en un universo vasto y frío” se convirtió en la visión de una humanidad con una perspectiva cada vez más sombría, y Gleiser atribuye esto a la pérdida de la chispa de la curiosidad, la misión moral y el enfoque compasivo de la ciencia. Nos invita a recuperar ese sentimiento, reconstruir una nueva Ilustración para salvar la civilización y dar una nueva dirección a la humanidad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Además de sus libros, Gleiser es columnista, presentador de programas de TV y radio, y fundador del Institute for Cross-Disciplinary Engagement (ICE). En los últimos años, se ha dedicado a campañas por la valorización de la ciencia, el pensamiento crítico y la conservación del planeta, alertando sobre la urgencia de acciones en defensa del medio ambiente y la vida en la Tierra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En los últimos años, Gleiser se ha dedicado a campañas por la valorización de la ciencia, el pensamiento crítico y la conservación del planeta, alertando sobre la urgencia de acciones en defensa del medio ambiente y la vida en la Tierra. Una de sus iniciativas más recientes es el Podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GXXOl35LA1U&quot;&gt;The Blind Spot&lt;/a&gt;, protagonizado por Gleiser, el físico y divulgador científico Adam Frank (Universidad de Rochester) y el filósofo Evan Thompson (Universidad de Columbia Británica). En el primer episodio discutieron la naturaleza del conocimiento, la objetividad y la ciencia, y las relaciones del proyecto filosófico y científico occidental con las religiones monoteístas, un tema recurrente en la obra de Gleiser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;referencias&quot;&gt;Referencias&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.templetonprize.org/laureate/marcelo-gleiser/&quot;&gt;Premio Templeton - Sitio Oficial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Gleiser&quot;&gt;Wikipedia: Marcelo Gleiser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Premio_Templeton&quot;&gt;Wikipedia: Premio Templeton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/24/marcelo-gleiser-templeton-es.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/24/marcelo-gleiser-templeton-es.html</guid>
        
        <category>Física</category>
        
        <category>Marcelo Gleiser</category>
        
        <category>Templeton</category>
        
        <category>Divulgación científica</category>
        
        <category>Premios internacionales</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Marcelo Gleiser: The Brazilian Physicist Awarded the Templeton Prize</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Brazilian physicist &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Gleiser&quot;&gt;Marcelo Gleiser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is internationally recognized for his contributions to science and science communication. In 2019, he became the first Latin American and the only Brazilian to receive the prestigious &lt;strong&gt;Templeton Prize&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;premio-templeton-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;premio-templeton-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Templeton Prize:&lt;/strong&gt; An international award created in 1972 to honor individuals who make exceptional contributions to affirming life’s spiritual dimension, whether through scientific discoveries, philosophical insights, or practical actions.&lt;/span&gt;
, one of the world’s most important awards for scientists and thinkers who broaden humanity’s understanding of existence. Gleiser himself defines as agnostic, advocating dialogue between science and spirituality. &lt;label for=&quot;agnosticismo-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;agnosticismo-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agnosticism:&lt;/strong&gt; A philosophical position that holds it is not possible to affirm or deny the existence of God, the divine, or metaphysical realities due to insufficient evidence. Agnosticism is common in debates about science and spirituality.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;biography-and-education&quot;&gt;Biography and Education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcelo Gleiser was born on March 19, 1959, in Rio de Janeiro. From a Jewish family, he recounts that at his Bar Mitzvah&lt;label for=&quot;bar-mitzvah-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;bar-mitzvah-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bar Mitzvah:&lt;/strong&gt; Jewish coming-of-age ceremony for boys at age 13. After the Bar Mitzvah, the boy is considered responsible for his actions under Jewish law and can fully participate in religious rituals.&lt;/span&gt;
, he received from his aunt an autographed photo of Einstein. In the photo are Einstein and Isidoro Kohn, his stepmother’s uncle. Gleiser’s paternal grandfather also accompanied Einstein on this visit to Rio in 1925. According to family accounts, Isidoro lent the tie that Einstein is wearing in the photo. This photo inspired Marcelo Gleiser, then a teenager fascinated by nature, to pursue a career in physics. In his book “&lt;a href=&quot;#writer-and-science-communicator&quot;&gt;A Tear at the Edge of Creation&lt;/a&gt;”, he reports that after his mother’s death, he went through a difficult period of uncertainty, and the pursuit of scientific knowledge was one of the things that helped him overcome it. Another was sports, having played volleyball and even participated in the victory of the Brazilian junior team in 1974, alongside &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernardo_Resende&quot;&gt;Bernardinho&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ciencia-medica/assets/img/einstein-gleiser.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Einstein in Brazil, 1925&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Albert Einstein and Isidoro Kohn, friend of Gleiser’s paternal grandfather and stepmother’s uncle, in Brazil in 1925. Kohn had lent the tie Einstein is wearing in the photo.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He studied physics at the Federal University of Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), graduating in 1981. He then earned a master’s degree at the Institute of Theoretical Physics of São Paulo State University (IFT-Unesp), with a dissertation entitled “Vortex Solutions in Abelian and Non-Abelian Gauge Theories” (1982), supervised by Prof. Dr. Mario Novello. In this work, Gleiser studied structures called “vortices”—regions where physical fields organize similarly to whirlpools—in fundamental theories of physics, seeking to understand how patterns and structures can spontaneously arise in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He later completed his PhD in theoretical physics at King’s College London, UK, in 1986, under Prof. Dr. Michael E. Fisher. His thesis, entitled “Phase Transitions in the Early Universe,” investigated how abrupt and fundamental changes—similar to the transformation of water into ice—may have occurred in the universe’s earliest moments, influencing the formation of cosmic structures and the evolution of the cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After his PhD, he worked as a postdoctoral researcher at Fermilab (Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory) in the United States, under the supervision of physicist Edward W. Kolb (Rocky Kolb), a world reference in physical cosmology. There, Gleiser developed independent and collaborative research in theoretical cosmology, especially on phase transitions in the early universe and the formation of cosmic structures. His work resulted in important scientific publications, deepening the connection between particle physics and the evolution of the universe after the Big Bang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also worked at the Institute of Theoretical Physics at Unesp, collaborating with research groups in theoretical physics and cosmology, mentoring young researchers, and participating in projects on fundamental symmetries, structure formation in the universe, and models of exotic matter. His work helped strengthen cosmology research in Brazil and expand international scientific exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout his career, Gleiser has also mentored and influenced many young scientists, both in Brazil and abroad, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sara_Imari_Walker&quot;&gt;Sara Imari Walker&lt;/a&gt;. His role as a mentor has helped form a new generation of researchers in theoretical physics and cosmology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1991, he became a professor at Dartmouth College in the United States, where he still works as a full professor of physics and astronomy, holding the Appleton Professor of Natural Philosophy chair, one of the institution’s most prestigious titles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;main-works&quot;&gt;Main Works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gleiser is a specialist in cosmology&lt;label for=&quot;cosmologia-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;cosmologia-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cosmology:&lt;/strong&gt; The branch of science that studies the origin, structure, evolution, and ultimate fate of the universe as a whole, integrating knowledge from physics, astronomy, and philosophy.&lt;/span&gt;
, particle physics, and astrobiology&lt;label for=&quot;astrobiologia-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;astrobiologia-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astrobiology:&lt;/strong&gt; An interdisciplinary field that investigates the origin, evolution, distribution, and future of life in the universe, including the search for life on other planets.&lt;/span&gt;
. He has stood out for research on the origin and evolution of the universe, fundamental symmetries, cosmic phase transitions, and the search for life beyond Earth. He has published over 100 scientific articles and is an international reference in topics such as symmetry breaking and the formation of cosmic structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among his most prominent works is the proposal of the “Rare Life Principle,” in which Gleiser argues that complex life in the universe may be much rarer than imagined, due to the combination of physical, chemical, and biological factors required for its emergence. He has also contributed to the debate on the definition of life and the limits of planetary habitability, being an international reference in astrobiology. Gleiser has participated in collaborations with NASA and other research centers, discussing the conditions for the existence of life beyond Earth and the challenges of searching for biosignatures on exoplanets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-templeton-prize&quot;&gt;The Templeton Prize&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Templeton Prize was created in 1972 by British philanthropist John Templeton to recognize people who “make exceptional contributions to affirming life’s spiritual dimension, whether through insights, discoveries, or practical work.” &lt;label for=&quot;premio-templeton-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;premio-templeton-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Templeton Prize:&lt;/strong&gt; An international award created in 1972 to honor individuals who make exceptional contributions to affirming life’s spiritual dimension, whether through scientific discoveries, philosophical insights, or practical actions.&lt;/span&gt;
 The prize amount exceeds that of the Nobel, and it has been awarded to names such as Mother Teresa of Calcutta (the first laureate), the Dalai Lama, Desmond Tutu, Charles Taylor, Freeman Dyson, and Martin Rees. The Templeton is considered one of the world’s greatest recognitions for scientists, philosophers, and spiritual leaders, and is often compared to the Nobel in prestige.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcelo Gleiser was the first Latin American and the only Brazilian to receive the Templeton, in 2019. The ceremony took place in New York, USA. Gleiser was honored for his pioneering work exploring the great questions of human existence, the relationship between science and spirituality, and for his advocacy of dialogue between different forms of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/06/Marcelo_Gleiser_no_Fronteiras_do_Pensamento_Florian%C3%B3polis_2013_%2810277998645%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Marcelo Gleiser&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Marcelo Gleiser at Fronteiras do Pensamento (Florianópolis, 2013).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;writer-and-science-communicator&quot;&gt;Writer and Science Communicator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to his academic career, Gleiser is one of the most influential science communicators in Brazil and the world. &lt;label for=&quot;divulgacao-cientifica-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;divulgacao-cientifica-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science communication:&lt;/strong&gt; The activity of communicating scientific knowledge to the general public, making science accessible and understandable, and promoting critical thinking in society.&lt;/span&gt;
 His journey as a writer began with notable impact, and he established himself as a voice that unites the complexity of science with the human search for meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His first book, &lt;strong&gt;‘The Dancing Universe’&lt;/strong&gt;, was published in 1997 by &lt;strong&gt;Companhia das Letras&lt;/strong&gt;. The work quickly became a bestseller in Brazil and won the &lt;strong&gt;Jabuti Prize&lt;/strong&gt; in 1998, establishing Gleiser as one of the leading names in science communication in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His main works, translated into more than 15 languages, include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘The Dancing Universe’ (1997):&lt;/strong&gt;
In this book, Gleiser traces an overview of the history of cosmological thought, from ancient creation myths to modern scientific theories such as the Big Bang and particle physics. The book was a milestone in science communication in Brazil for its accessible language and for connecting science with philosophy and the human search for origins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘The End of Earth and Sky’ (2001):&lt;/strong&gt;
Gleiser explores humanity’s fascination with the end of the world, analyzing apocalyptic myths, religious prophecies, and scientific predictions about the universe’s ultimate fate. The work discusses how modern science offers new narratives about the end, replacing fear with rational understanding of cosmic processes. It won the Jabuti Prize in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘A Tear at the Edge of Creation’ (2010):&lt;/strong&gt;
Published in Brazil as ‘Criação Imperfeita’, this book argues that the asymmetries and “imperfections” found in nature—from the subatomic level to cosmic structures—are the key to the existence of the universe as we know it. The work challenges the notion of a “perfect design” and celebrates the creativity inherent in natural processes. By privileging a view where the search for perfect order as the foundation of reality is replaced by “imperfection,” by asymmetry as the origin of the main phenomena we observe, Gleiser, in a way, recovers an Epicurean view (void and particles moving randomly) of the foundations of knowledge, in contrast to the Platonism that seems to have predominated in Western thought and is, in fact, increasingly strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘The Island of Knowledge’ (2014):&lt;/strong&gt;
Using the metaphor of an “island of knowledge” in an “ocean of the unknown,” Gleiser argues that the more we learn about the universe, the vaster the frontier with what we do not know becomes. The book is a reflection on the limits of science and the importance of recognizing mystery as the engine of the human quest for knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘The Simple Beauty of the Unexpected’ (2016):&lt;/strong&gt;
In this collection of essays, Gleiser connects scientific concepts to everyday experiences, exploring themes such as time, life, death, and the pursuit of happiness. The work invites the reader to find wonder and beauty in science and the world around them, reinforcing a humanistic view of scientific knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘The Dawn of a Mindful Universe’ (2024):&lt;/strong&gt;
Copernicus inaugurated a line of thought (epitomized by the principle that bears his name) that has progressively removed the protagonism of human beings from their own notion of understanding the world. “An insignificant particle in a vast and cold universe” became the vision of a humanity with an increasingly somber perspective, and Gleiser attributes this to the loss of the spark of curiosity, the moral mission, and the compassionate focus of science. He invites us to recover this feeling, rebuild a new Enlightenment to save civilization, and give a new direction to humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to his books, Gleiser is a columnist, host of TV and radio programs, and founder of the Institute for Cross-Disciplinary Engagement (ICE). In recent years, he has dedicated himself to campaigns for the appreciation of science, critical thinking, and the conservation of the planet, warning of the urgency of actions to defend the environment and life on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, Gleiser has dedicated himself to campaigns for the appreciation of science, critical thinking, and the conservation of the planet, warning of the urgency of actions to defend the environment and life on Earth. One of his most recent initiatives is the Podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GXXOl35LA1U&quot;&gt;The Blind Spot&lt;/a&gt;, featuring Gleiser, physicist and science communicator Adam Frank (University of Rochester), and philosopher Evan Thompson (University of British Columbia). In the first episode, they discussed the nature of knowledge, objectivity and science, and the relationship of the Western philosophical and scientific project with monotheistic religions, a recurring theme in Gleiser’s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.templetonprize.org/laureate/marcelo-gleiser/&quot;&gt;Templeton Prize - Official Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Gleiser&quot;&gt;Wikipedia: Marcelo Gleiser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Templeton_Prize&quot;&gt;Wikipedia: Templeton Prize&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/24/marcelo-gleiser-templeton-en.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/24/marcelo-gleiser-templeton-en.html</guid>
        
        <category>Physics</category>
        
        <category>Marcelo Gleiser</category>
        
        <category>Templeton</category>
        
        <category>Science communication</category>
        
        <category>International awards</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Merchant, the Portal, and Time Loops: Science and Fiction in Ted Chiang</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In his award-winning short story “The Merchant and the Alchemist’s Gate,” Ted Chiang weaves a fascinating narrative around a real scientific concept: closed timelike curves.&lt;label for=&quot;closed-timelike-curve&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;closed-timelike-curve&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Closed timelike curve:&lt;/strong&gt; A trajectory in spacetime that returns to the same point, theoretically allowing time travel without violating general relativity.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Inspired by a lecture from physicist Kip Thorne, Chiang explores the idea of trajectories in spacetime that return to the same point—meaning, mathematically possible time travel.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/e/e3/The_Merchant_and_the_Alchemist%27s_Gate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cover of the original edition of &amp;quot;The Merchant and the Alchemist&apos;s Gate&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cover of the original edition of “The Merchant and the Alchemist’s Gate”. Image by Subterranean Press, published on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:The_Merchant_and_the_Alchemist%27s_Gate.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; under Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported license.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we get lost in paradoxes and portals, it’s worth asking: what is time, after all? Long before time became a theme in Western philosophy, Hindus wrote in the Vedas about cycles of creation and destruction lasting more than 4 million years each. The Egyptian Ptahotep said that wasting time was an abomination (perhaps already anticipating Novikov? - see below). The Incas saw space and time as one: &lt;em&gt;pacha&lt;/em&gt;. And probably the ancient speakers of Proto-Semitic already had the concept of remote time and an origin of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Aristotle, time was not an independent entity, but the measure of change—time exists only because things change. Newton, on the other hand, saw time (and space) as absolutes, a fixed stage where everything happens, regardless of what exists or changes. Then Einstein brought the big surprise: time can “stretch” or “shrink” depending on speed and gravity, becoming relative to the observer.&lt;label for=&quot;relativity&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;relativity&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Relativity:&lt;/strong&gt; The physical theory developed by Einstein that revolutionized our understanding of space, time, and gravity, showing they are relative to the observer.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Other philosophers also gave their interpretations, but none changed our understanding as much as modern physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what are these curves, after all? Technically, they are “closed worldlines of a Lorentzian manifold in spacetime.” In simpler terms: they are trajectories that allow an object to return to the same point in space and time. The first mathematical solution for this concept was found by Willem Jacob van Stockum in 1937, and later confirmed by Kurt Gödel in 1949, both using Einstein’s field equations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before time travel was seriously considered, Karl Schwarzschild—adventurer, mountaineer, and physicist—found the first exact solution to Einstein’s equations during World War I.&lt;label for=&quot;wormhole-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;wormhole-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Wormhole:&lt;/strong&gt; A theoretical solution to Einstein’s equations connecting two distinct points in spacetime, acting as a cosmic shortcut.
&lt;/span&gt;
 His work paved the way for the concept of wormholes, which would later be considered possible mechanisms for closed timelike curves. If anyone had to be a time traveler, it would be him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the concepts that most fascinated Chiang was Novikov’s self-consistency principle. But who was Novikov? Igor Dmitriyevich Novikov is a Russian astrophysicist and cosmologist, known for his contributions to black hole physics, cosmology, and especially to the study of time travel.&lt;label for=&quot;novikov-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;novikov-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Novikov self-consistency principle:&lt;/strong&gt; States that events causing time paradoxes have zero probability of occurring, making the universe “self-consistent”.
&lt;/span&gt;
 He formulated the self-consistency principle, which states that the probability of worldlines causing time paradoxes is zero. In other words, the universe “adjusts itself” to prevent paradoxes, making them impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1990s, Thorne and other physicists found mathematical solutions suggesting the existence of infinite closed timelike curves that avoid paradoxes.&lt;label for=&quot;time-paradox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;time-paradox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time paradox:&lt;/strong&gt; A hypothetical situation in which an action in the past changes the future in a contradictory way, such as preventing one’s own birth.
&lt;/span&gt;
 This could be used in traversable wormholes—true “windows” to the past or future, but always in worldlines where paradoxes cannot occur. The result would be similar to Chiang’s description in his story, something quite different from the wormhole in Carl Sagan’s book Contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chiang is a master at building stories around singular scientific concepts, always in a romanticized fantasy setting. “The Merchant and the Alchemist’s Gate” won the Nebula and Hugo awards in 2008, showing how great science fiction can arise from mathematically possible ideas that remain mysterious to most of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ted Chiang is an American science fiction writer, known for his stories that explore deep scientific and philosophical concepts. His most popular work is the short story “Story of Your Life,” which was adapted into the acclaimed film “Arrival” (2016), directed by Denis Villeneuve. Chiang has received several major awards in speculative fiction, including the Nebula, Hugo, and Locus awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.: The concepts discussed in this post also apply to other works of fiction in different media, such as the Netflix series “Dark” and the anime “Steins;Gate”—each of which deserves its own dedicated post in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/20/chiang-merchant-portal-en.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/20/chiang-merchant-portal-en.html</guid>
        
        <category>Science fiction</category>
        
        <category>Time travel</category>
        
        <category>Relativity</category>
        
        <category>Wormhole</category>
        
        <category>Ted Chiang</category>
        
        <category>Kip Thorne</category>
        
        <category>Gödel</category>
        
        <category>Novikov</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>O mercador, o portal e as curvas do tempo: ciência e ficção em Ted Chiang</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ted Chiang, em seu premiado conto “O Mercador e o Portal do Alquimista”, constrói uma narrativa fascinante ao redor de um conceito científico real: as curvas fechadas do tipo tempo.&lt;label for=&quot;curva-fechada-tempo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;curva-fechada-tempo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Curva fechada do tipo tempo:&lt;/strong&gt; Trajetória no espaço-tempo que retorna ao mesmo ponto, permitindo, em teoria, viagens no tempo sem violar as equações da relatividade geral.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Inspirado por uma palestra do físico Kip Thorne, Chiang explora a ideia de trajetórias no espaço-tempo que retornam ao mesmo ponto — ou seja, viagens no tempo matematicamente possíveis.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/e/e3/The_Merchant_and_the_Alchemist%27s_Gate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Capa da edição original de &amp;quot;The Merchant and the Alchemist&apos;s Gate&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Capa da edição original de “The Merchant and the Alchemist’s Gate”. Imagem de Subterranean Press, publicada na &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:The_Merchant_and_the_Alchemist%27s_Gate.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; sob licença Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antes de nos perdermos nos paradoxos e portais, vale perguntar: afinal, o que é o tempo? Muito antes de o tempo ser tema da filosofia ocidental, os hindus já escreviam nos Vedas sobre ciclos de criação e destruição que duravam mais de 4 milhões de anos cada. O egípcio Ptahotep dizia que a perda de tempo era uma abominação (talvez já antecipando Novikov? - veja adiante). Os Incas viam espaço e tempo como uma coisa só: &lt;em&gt;pacha&lt;/em&gt;. E, provavelmente, os antigos falantes do proto-semítico já tinham o conceito de tempo remoto e de uma origem do tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para Aristóteles, o tempo não era uma entidade independente, mas a medida da mudança — só existe tempo porque as coisas mudam. Newton, por outro lado, via o tempo (e o espaço) como absolutos, um palco fixo onde tudo acontece, independentemente do que existe ou muda. Já Einstein trouxe a grande surpresa: o tempo pode “esticar” ou “encolher” dependendo da velocidade e da gravidade, tornando-se relativo ao observador.&lt;label for=&quot;relatividade&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;relatividade&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Relatividade:&lt;/strong&gt; Teoria física desenvolvida por Einstein que revolucionou a compreensão do espaço, tempo e gravidade, mostrando que são relativos ao observador.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Outros filósofos também deram suas interpretações, mas nenhuma delas mudou tanto nossa compreensão quanto a física moderna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mas afinal o que são as tais curvas? Em termos técnicos, são “linhas do universo fechadas de um distribuidor Lorentziano no espaço-tempo”. Traduzindo: são trajetórias que permitem a um objeto voltar ao mesmo ponto no espaço e no tempo. A primeira solução matemática para esse conceito foi encontrada por Willem Jacob van Stockum em 1937, e depois confirmada por Kurt Gödel em 1949, ambos usando as equações de campo de Einstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antes mesmo de se falar em viagens no tempo, Karl Schwarzschild — aventureiro, alpinista e físico — encontrou a primeira solução exata das equações de Einstein durante a Primeira Guerra Mundial.&lt;label for=&quot;wormhole&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;wormhole&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Buraco de minhoca:&lt;/strong&gt; Solução teórica das equações de Einstein que conecta dois pontos distintos do espaço-tempo, funcionando como um atalho cósmico.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Sua solução abriu caminho para o conceito de buracos de minhoca, que mais tarde seriam considerados possíveis mecanismos para curvas fechadas do tempo. Se alguém tivesse que ser um viajante do tempo, seria ele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Um dos conceitos que mais fascinaram Chiang foi o princípio de autoconsistência de Novikov (um astrofísico e cosmólogo russo, conhecido por suas contribuições à física dos buracos negros, à cosmologia e, especialmente, ao estudo das viagens no tempo).&lt;label for=&quot;novikov&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;novikov&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Princípio de autoconsistência de Novikov:&lt;/strong&gt; Postula que eventos que causariam paradoxos temporais têm probabilidade zero de ocorrer, tornando o universo “autoconsistente”.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Esse princípio postula que a probabilidade de linhas do universo que causam paradoxos temporais é zero. Ou seja, o universo “se ajusta” para impedir paradoxos, tornando-os impossíveis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nos anos 90, Thorne e outros físicos encontraram soluções matemáticas que sugerem a existência de infinitas curvas fechadas do tempo que evitam paradoxos.&lt;label for=&quot;paradoxo-temporal&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;paradoxo-temporal&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Paradoxo temporal:&lt;/strong&gt; Situação hipotética em que uma ação no passado altera o futuro de forma contraditória, como impedir o próprio nascimento.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Isso poderia ser usado em buracos de minhoca atravessáveis — verdadeiras “janelas” para o passado ou futuro, mas sempre em linhas do universo onde paradoxos não podem ocorrer. O resultado seria semelhante à descrição de Chiang em seu conto, algo bem diferente do buraco de minhoca do livro Contato, de Carl Sagan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chiang é mestre em criar contos ao redor de conceitos científicos singulares, sempre em cenários de fantasia romanceada. “O Mercador e o Portal do Alquimista” ganhou os prêmios Nebula e Hugo em 2008, mostrando como a boa ficção científica pode nascer de ideias matematicamente possíveis, mas ainda misteriosas para a maioria de nós.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ted Chiang é um escritor norte-americano de ficção científica, conhecido por suas histórias que exploram conceitos científicos e filosóficos profundos. Sua obra mais popular é o conto “Story of Your Life” (“A História da Sua Vida”), que foi adaptado para o cinema no premiado filme “A Chegada” (“Arrival”, 2016), dirigido por Denis Villeneuve. Chiang já recebeu diversos prêmios importantes da literatura fantástica, incluindo o Nebula, o Hugo e o Locus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.: Os conceitos discutidos nesta postagem também se aplicam a outras obras de ficção em diferentes mídias, como a série da Netflix “Dark” e o anime “Steins;Gate” — cada uma delas merece, no futuro, uma postagem própria.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/20/chiang-mercador-portal-pt.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/20/chiang-mercador-portal-pt.html</guid>
        
        <category>Ficção científica</category>
        
        <category>Viagem no tempo</category>
        
        <category>Relatividade</category>
        
        <category>Buraco de minhoca</category>
        
        <category>Ted Chiang</category>
        
        <category>Kip Thorne</category>
        
        <category>Gödel</category>
        
        <category>Novikov</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>El mercader, el portal y las curvas del tiempo: ciencia y ficción en Ted Chiang</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ted Chiang, en su premiado relato “El Mercader y el Portal del Alquimista”, construye una narrativa fascinante en torno a un concepto científico real: las curvas cerradas tipo tiempo.&lt;label for=&quot;curva-cerrada-tiempo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;curva-cerrada-tiempo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Curva cerrada tipo tiempo:&lt;/strong&gt; Trayectoria en el espacio-tiempo que regresa al mismo punto, permitiendo en teoría viajes en el tiempo sin violar las ecuaciones de la relatividad general.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Inspirado por una conferencia del físico Kip Thorne, Chiang explora la idea de trayectorias en el espacio-tiempo que regresan al mismo punto — es decir, viajes en el tiempo matemáticamente posibles.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/e/e3/The_Merchant_and_the_Alchemist%27s_Gate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Portada de la edición original de &amp;quot;The Merchant and the Alchemist&apos;s Gate&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Portada de la edición original de “The Merchant and the Alchemist’s Gate”. Imagen de Subterranean Press, publicada en &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:The_Merchant_and_the_Alchemist%27s_Gate.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; bajo licencia Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antes de perdernos en paradojas y portales, vale la pena preguntar: ¿qué es el tiempo? Mucho antes de que el tiempo fuera tema de la filosofía occidental, los hindúes ya escribían en los Vedas sobre ciclos de creación y destrucción que duraban más de 4 millones de años cada uno. El egipcio Ptahotep decía que la pérdida de tiempo era una abominación (¿quizás anticipando a Novikov? - véase más adelante). Los incas veían el espacio y el tiempo como una sola cosa: &lt;em&gt;pacha&lt;/em&gt;. Y, probablemente, los antiguos hablantes del proto-semítico ya tenían el concepto de tiempo remoto y de un origen del tiempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para Aristóteles, el tiempo no era una entidad independiente, sino la medida del cambio — solo existe tiempo porque las cosas cambian. Newton, en cambio, veía el tiempo (y el espacio) como absolutos, un escenario fijo donde todo sucede, independientemente de lo que exista o cambie. Einstein trajo la gran sorpresa: el tiempo puede “estirarse” o “encogerse” dependiendo de la velocidad y la gravedad, volviéndose relativo al observador.&lt;label for=&quot;relatividad&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;relatividad&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Relatividad:&lt;/strong&gt; Teoría física desarrollada por Einstein que revolucionó la comprensión del espacio, el tiempo y la gravedad, mostrando que son relativos al observador.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Otros filósofos también dieron sus interpretaciones, pero ninguna cambió tanto nuestra comprensión como la física moderna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;¿Pero qué son esas curvas? En términos técnicos, son “líneas del universo cerradas de un distribuidor Lorentziano en el espacio-tiempo”. Traducido: son trayectorias que permiten a un objeto volver al mismo punto en el espacio y en el tiempo. La primera solución matemática para este concepto fue encontrada por Willem Jacob van Stockum en 1937, y luego confirmada por Kurt Gödel en 1949, ambos usando las ecuaciones de campo de Einstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antes incluso de hablar de viajes en el tiempo, Karl Schwarzschild — aventurero, alpinista y físico — encontró la primera solución exacta de las ecuaciones de Einstein durante la Primera Guerra Mundial.&lt;label for=&quot;agujero-gusano&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;agujero-gusano&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Agujero de gusano:&lt;/strong&gt; Solución teórica de las ecuaciones de Einstein que conecta dos puntos distintos del espacio-tiempo, funcionando como un atajo cósmico.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Su solución abrió el camino para el concepto de agujeros de gusano, que más tarde serían considerados posibles mecanismos para curvas cerradas del tiempo. Si alguien debía ser un viajero en el tiempo, sería él.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uno de los conceptos que más fascinó a Chiang fue el principio de autoconsistencia de Novikov (un astrofísico y cosmólogo ruso, conocido por sus contribuciones a la física de los agujeros negros, la cosmología y, especialmente, al estudio de los viajes en el tiempo).&lt;label for=&quot;novikov-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;novikov-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Principio de autoconsistencia de Novikov:&lt;/strong&gt; Postula que los eventos que causarían paradojas temporales tienen probabilidad cero de ocurrir, haciendo que el universo sea “autoconsistente”.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Este principio postula que la probabilidad de líneas del universo que causan paradojas temporales es cero. Es decir, el universo “se ajusta” para impedir paradojas, haciéndolas imposibles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En los años 90, Thorne y otros físicos encontraron soluciones matemáticas que sugieren la existencia de infinitas curvas cerradas del tiempo que evitan paradojas.&lt;label for=&quot;paradoja-temporal&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;paradoja-temporal&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Paradoja temporal:&lt;/strong&gt; Situación hipotética en la que una acción en el pasado altera el futuro de forma contradictoria, como impedir el propio nacimiento.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Esto podría usarse en agujeros de gusano atravesables — verdaderas “ventanas” al pasado o al futuro, pero siempre en líneas del universo donde los paradojas no pueden ocurrir. El resultado sería similar a la descripción de Chiang en su relato, algo muy diferente al agujero de gusano del libro Contacto, de Carl Sagan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chiang es un maestro en crear relatos alrededor de conceptos científicos singulares, siempre en escenarios de fantasía novelada. “El Mercader y el Portal del Alquimista” ganó los premios Nebula y Hugo en 2008, mostrando cómo la buena ciencia ficción puede nacer de ideas matemáticamente posibles, pero aún misteriosas para la mayoría de nosotros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ted Chiang es un escritor estadounidense de ciencia ficción, conocido por sus historias que exploran conceptos científicos y filosóficos profundos. Su obra más popular es el relato “Story of Your Life” (“La historia de tu vida”), que fue adaptado al cine en la premiada película “La Llegada” (“Arrival”, 2016), dirigida por Denis Villeneuve. Chiang ha recibido varios premios importantes de la literatura fantástica, incluyendo el Nebula, el Hugo y el Locus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.D.: Los conceptos discutidos en esta publicación también se aplican a otras obras de ficción en diferentes medios, como la serie de Netflix “Dark” y el anime “Steins;Gate” — cada una de ellas merece, en el futuro, una publicación propia.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/20/chiang-mercador-portal-es.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/20/chiang-mercador-portal-es.html</guid>
        
        <category>Ciencia ficción</category>
        
        <category>Viaje en el tiempo</category>
        
        <category>Relatividad</category>
        
        <category>Agujero de gusano</category>
        
        <category>Ted Chiang</category>
        
        <category>Kip Thorne</category>
        
        <category>Gödel</category>
        
        <category>Novikov</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>O lobo terrível não voltou: o que realmente significa o anúncio da &quot;desextinção&quot; e por que o futuro é mais importante que o passado</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Em abril de 2025, manchetes ao redor do mundo anunciaram a suposta “desextinção” do lobo terrível (dire wolf), espécie extinta há milhares de anos, após divulgação de um preprint e comunicado da empresa Colossal Biosciences.&lt;label for=&quot;desextincao&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;desextincao&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Desextinção:&lt;/strong&gt; Conceito que se refere à tentativa de recriar ou restaurar espécies extintas por meio de técnicas biotecnológicas, como clonagem, edição genética ou cruzamentos seletivos. Até hoje, nenhum caso de desextinção plena foi comprovado cientificamente.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Mas, afinal, o que realmente aconteceu? A resposta é mais complexa e interessante do que o sensacionalismo sugere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/92/Canis_dirus_Sergiodlarosa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reconstrução artística do lobo terrível (Canis dirus)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Reconstrução artística do lobo terrível (Canis dirus). Ilustração de Sergiodlarosa, publicada sob licença Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Canis_dirus_Sergiodlarosa.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;label for=&quot;lobo-terrivel&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;lobo-terrivel&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Lobo terrível (Canis dirus):&lt;/strong&gt; Espécie de lobo pré-histórico que viveu nas Américas durante o Pleistoceno e se extinguiu há cerca de 10 mil anos. Era maior e mais robusto que os lobos modernos.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;o-que-foi-feito-e-o-que-não-foi&quot;&gt;O que foi feito (e o que não foi)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Colossal Biosciences utilizou material genético de lobos cinzentos modernos, não de cães. Um dos  grandes avanços metodológicos nesse caso foi o uso de clonagem a partir de células progenitoras endoteliais, que normalmente existem em quantidade diminuta no revestimento interno dos vasos sanguíneos. Diferente das técnicas tradicionais de clonagem, que dependem de amostras de tecido obtidas por biópsia (e podem ser contaminadas por células diferenciadas), essa abordagem requer apenas uma amostra de sangue e a separação específica dessas células progenitoras — algo que até pouco tempo parecia ficção científica, como no filme ‘O Sexto Dia’. &lt;label for=&quot;clonagem&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;clonagem&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Clonagem:&lt;/strong&gt; Técnica de reprodução assexuada que gera um organismo geneticamente idêntico ao original. Pode ser feita por transferência nuclear, como no caso da ovelha Dolly, ou por outros métodos laboratoriais.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O DNA dos lobos cinzentos foi então editado geneticamente usando uma técnica com a enzima CRISPR-Cas9, permitindo a modificação de 20 posições de nucleotídeos do material genético original. Essas 20 alterações foram suficientes para dar aos animais gerados a aparência do lobo terrível. No entanto, os lobos terríveis originais tinham milhões de pares de bases diferentes dos lobos cinzentos modernos — ou seja, a modificação é superficial e limitada. &lt;label for=&quot;crispr&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;crispr&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;CRISPR:&lt;/strong&gt; Ferramenta de edição genética baseada em um sistema natural de defesa bacteriana, que permite modificar o DNA de organismos de forma precisa, rápida e relativamente barata. Revolucionou a biotecnologia e a medicina.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Após a edição genética, o núcleo dessas células modificadas foi transferido para óvulos de lobo cujo núcleo havia sido removido, etapa semelhante à técnica clássica de clonagem utilizada no caso da famosa ovelha Dolly. Assim, os embriões resultantes continham o material genético editado e puderam ser implantados para o desenvolvimento dos filhotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Os embriões de lobo cinzento geneticamente modificados foram implantados em cadelas, que gestaram e deram à luz três filhotes. Portanto, não são lobos terríveis, mas sim lobos cinzentos modificados para parecerem lobos terríveis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A polêmica aumentou em maio de 2025, quando a própria cientista-chefe da Colossal admitiu publicamente que os animais criados não são lobos terríveis e que nunca houve, de fato, uma desextinção. Essa admissão, amplamente repercutida na mídia, reforçou o caráter midiático do anúncio e evidenciou a importância de uma comunicação científica precisa e transparente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cientistas e veículos como a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/dire-wolf-back-dead-not-exactly&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; e a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/portuguese/articles/c62973qwx4do&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt; foram claros: não existe desextinção real, nem evidências de que lobos terríveis estejam de volta. O anúncio foi, em grande parte, um golpe de mídia, como apontou também a &lt;a href=&quot;https://jornal.usp.br/radio-usp/nao-existem-evidencias-cientificas-da-recuperacao-dos-lobos-terriveis-extintos-ha-milhares-de-anos/&quot;&gt;Universidade de São Paulo - USP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;o-verdadeiro-marco-crispr-e-o-futuro&quot;&gt;O verdadeiro marco: CRISPR e o futuro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apesar do exagero midiático, o trabalho representa um avanço notável na aplicação da edição genética em mamíferos, especialmente usando CRISPR para inserir modificações genéticas semelhantes aquelas de espécies extintas em genomas modernos. Isso abre portas para pesquisas em biotecnologia, saúde animal e humana, e até para a conservação de espécies ameaçadas — mas não para “ressuscitar” o passado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O impacto prático imediato para a ecologia ou proteção de espécies é nulo. Não há benefícios para o meio ambiente, nem para a biodiversidade, neste momento. O que há, de fato, é um salto tecnológico que pode, no futuro, revolucionar a medicina, tornando possível criar animais (e talvez humanos) resistentes a doenças, ou com características otimizadas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;o-debate-ético-e-o-futuro-disruptivo&quot;&gt;O debate ético e o futuro disruptivo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O aspecto mais relevante — e pouco discutido — é o potencial da edição genética para criar seres vivos com características inéditas. O “lobo terrível” é só um símbolo: o verdadeiro dilema está em como a sociedade lidará com a possibilidade de modificar profundamente seres humanos e animais. A tecnologia CRISPR pode, em médio e longo prazo, transformar a saúde, mas também traz desafios éticos enormes. &lt;label for=&quot;bioetica&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;bioetica&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Bioética:&lt;/strong&gt; Campo interdisciplinar que discute os limites éticos, sociais e legais das intervenções biomédicas, como clonagem, edição genética e desextinção. Fundamental para orientar decisões responsáveis na ciência.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusão&quot;&gt;Conclusão&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A notícia da “desextinção” do lobo terrível é, na verdade, um marco para o futuro, não para o passado. O mais importante não é o que foi recuperado, mas o que poderá ser criado. O debate sobre os limites e usos da edição genética está só começando.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fontes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.04.09.647074v1.full.pdf&quot;&gt;Preprint científico&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/dire-wolf-back-dead-not-exactly&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/portuguese/articles/c62973qwx4do&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jornal.usp.br/radio-usp/nao-existem-evidencias-cientificas-da-recuperacao-dos-lobos-terriveis-extintos-ha-milhares-de-anos/&quot;&gt;Universidade de São Paulo - USP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://colossal.com/direwolf/&quot;&gt;Colossal Biosciences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://colossal.com/direwolf/science/&quot;&gt;Colossal - Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/7274542/colossal-dire-wolf/&quot;&gt;Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/18/direwolf-2025.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/18/direwolf-2025.html</guid>
        
        <category>Desextinção</category>
        
        <category>CRISPR</category>
        
        <category>Edição genética</category>
        
        <category>Lobo terrível</category>
        
        <category>Bioética</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>El lobo terrible no ha vuelto: qué significa realmente el anuncio de la &quot;desextinción&quot; y por qué el futuro es más importante que el pasado</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;En abril de 2025, titulares de todo el mundo anunciaron la supuesta “desextinción” del lobo terrible (dire wolf), especie extinta hace miles de años, tras la divulgación de un preprint y un comunicado de la empresa Colossal Biosciences.&lt;label for=&quot;desextincion&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;desextincion&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Desextinción:&lt;/strong&gt; Concepto que se refiere al intento de recrear o restaurar especies extintas mediante técnicas biotecnológicas como la clonación, la edición genética o los cruces selectivos. Hasta hoy, ningún caso de desextinción plena ha sido comprobado científicamente.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Pero, ¿qué fue lo que realmente ocurrió? La respuesta es más compleja e interesante de lo que sugiere el sensacionalismo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/92/Canis_dirus_Sergiodlarosa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reconstrucción artística del lobo terrible (Canis dirus)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Reconstrucción artística del lobo terrible (Canis dirus). Ilustración de Sergiodlarosa, publicada bajo licencia Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported. Fuente: &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Canis_dirus_Sergiodlarosa.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;label for=&quot;lobo-terrible&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;lobo-terrible&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Lobo terrible (Canis dirus):&lt;/strong&gt; Especie de lobo prehistórico que vivió en América durante el Pleistoceno y se extinguió hace unos 10 mil años. Era más grande y robusto que los lobos modernos.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;qué-se-hizo-y-qué-no&quot;&gt;Qué se hizo (y qué no)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colossal Biosciences utilizó material genético de lobos grises modernos, no de perros. Uno de los grandes avances metodológicos en este caso fue el uso de clonación a partir de células progenitoras endoteliales, que normalmente existen en cantidad reducida en el revestimiento interno de los vasos sanguíneos. A diferencia de las técnicas tradicionales de clonación, que dependen de muestras de tejido obtenidas por biopsia (y pueden estar contaminadas por células diferenciadas), este enfoque requiere solo una muestra de sangre y la separación específica de estas células progenitoras — algo que hasta hace poco parecía ciencia ficción, como en la película ‘El sexto día’. &lt;label for=&quot;clonacion&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;clonacion&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Clonación:&lt;/strong&gt; Técnica de reproducción asexual que genera un organismo genéticamente idéntico al original. Puede realizarse por transferencia nuclear, como en el caso de la oveja Dolly, u otros métodos de laboratorio.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El ADN de los lobos grises fue editado genéticamente usando una técnica con la enzima CRISPR-Cas9, permitiendo la modificación de 20 posiciones de nucleótidos del material genético original. Estas 20 alteraciones fueron suficientes para dar a los animales generados la apariencia del lobo terrible. Sin embargo, los lobos terribles originales tenían millones de pares de bases diferentes de los lobos grises modernos — es decir, la modificación es superficial y limitada. &lt;label for=&quot;crispr-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;crispr-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;CRISPR:&lt;/strong&gt; Herramienta de edición genética basada en un sistema natural de defensa bacteriana, que permite modificar el ADN de organismos de forma precisa, rápida y relativamente barata. Revolucionó la biotecnología y la medicina.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tras la edición genética, el núcleo de estas células modificadas fue transferido a óvulos de lobo cuyo núcleo había sido removido, etapa similar a la técnica clásica de clonación utilizada en el caso de la famosa oveja Dolly. Así, los embriones resultantes contenían el material genético editado y pudieron ser implantados para el desarrollo de los cachorros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Los embriones de lobo gris genéticamente modificados fueron implantados en perras, que gestaron y dieron a luz tres cachorros. Por lo tanto, no son lobos terribles, sino lobos grises modificados para parecer lobos terribles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La polémica aumentó en mayo de 2025, cuando la propia científica jefe de Colossal admitió públicamente que los animales creados no son lobos terribles y que nunca hubo, de hecho, una desextinción. Esta admisión, ampliamente difundida en los medios, reforzó el carácter mediático del anuncio y evidenció la importancia de una comunicación científica precisa y transparente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Científicos y medios como &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/dire-wolf-back-dead-not-exactly&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; y la &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/portuguese/articles/c62973qwx4do&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt; fueron claros: no existe desextinción real, ni evidencias de que los lobos terribles estén de vuelta. El anuncio fue, en gran parte, un golpe mediático, como también señaló la &lt;a href=&quot;https://jornal.usp.br/radio-usp/nao-existem-evidencias-cientificas-da-recuperacao-dos-lobos-terriveis-extintos-ha-milhares-de-anos/&quot;&gt;Universidad de São Paulo - USP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;el-verdadero-hito-crispr-y-el-futuro&quot;&gt;El verdadero hito: CRISPR y el futuro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pesar del sensacionalismo, el trabajo representa un avance notable en la aplicación de la edición genética en mamíferos, especialmente usando CRISPR para insertar modificaciones genéticas similares a las de especies extintas en genomas modernos. Esto abre puertas para investigaciones en biotecnología, salud animal y humana, e incluso para la conservación de especies amenazadas — pero no para “resucitar” el pasado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El impacto práctico inmediato para la ecología o la protección de especies es nulo. No hay beneficios para el medio ambiente ni para la biodiversidad, en este momento. Lo que hay, en realidad, es un salto tecnológico que puede, en el futuro, revolucionar la medicina, haciendo posible crear animales (y tal vez humanos) resistentes a enfermedades, o con características optimizadas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;el-debate-ético-y-el-futuro-disruptivo&quot;&gt;El debate ético y el futuro disruptivo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El aspecto más relevante — y poco discutido — es el potencial de la edición genética para crear seres vivos con características inéditas. El “lobo terrible” es solo un símbolo: el verdadero dilema está en cómo la sociedad lidiará con la posibilidad de modificar profundamente a los seres humanos y animales. La tecnología CRISPR puede, a mediano y largo plazo, transformar la salud, pero también plantea enormes desafíos éticos. &lt;label for=&quot;bioetica-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;bioetica-es&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Bioética:&lt;/strong&gt; Campo interdisciplinario que discute los límites éticos, sociales y legales de las intervenciones biomédicas, como la clonación, la edición genética y la desextinción. Fundamental para orientar decisiones responsables en la ciencia.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusión&quot;&gt;Conclusión&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La noticia de la “desextinción” del lobo terrible es, en realidad, un hito para el futuro, no para el pasado. Lo más importante no es lo que se recuperó, sino lo que podrá ser creado. El debate sobre los límites y usos de la edición genética apenas comienza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fuentes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.04.09.647074v1.full.pdf&quot;&gt;Preprint científico&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/dire-wolf-back-dead-not-exactly&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/portuguese/articles/c62973qwx4do&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jornal.usp.br/radio-usp/nao-existem-evidencias-cientificas-da-recuperacao-dos-lobos-terriveis-extintos-ha-milhares-de-anos/&quot;&gt;Universidad de São Paulo - USP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://colossal.com/direwolf/&quot;&gt;Colossal Biosciences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://colossal.com/direwolf/science/&quot;&gt;Colossal - Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/7274542/colossal-dire-wolf/&quot;&gt;Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/18/direwolf-2025-es.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/18/direwolf-2025-es.html</guid>
        
        <category>Desextinción</category>
        
        <category>CRISPR</category>
        
        <category>Edición genética</category>
        
        <category>Lobo terrible</category>
        
        <category>Bioética</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The dire wolf is not back: what the &quot;de-extinction&quot; announcement really means and why the future matters more than the past</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In April 2025, headlines around the world announced the supposed “de-extinction” of the dire wolf, a species extinct for thousands of years, following the release of a preprint and a statement from Colossal Biosciences.&lt;label for=&quot;deextinction&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;deextinction&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;De-extinction:&lt;/strong&gt; The concept of attempting to recreate or restore extinct species using biotechnological techniques such as cloning, genetic editing, or selective breeding. To date, no full de-extinction has been scientifically achieved.
&lt;/span&gt;
 But what really happened? The answer is more complex and interesting than the hype suggests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/92/Canis_dirus_Sergiodlarosa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Artistic reconstruction of the dire wolf (Canis dirus)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Artistic reconstruction of the dire wolf (Canis dirus). Illustration by Sergiodlarosa, published under Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported license. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Canis_dirus_Sergiodlarosa.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;label for=&quot;dire-wolf&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;dire-wolf&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Dire wolf (Canis dirus):&lt;/strong&gt; A prehistoric wolf species that lived in the Americas during the Pleistocene and went extinct about 10,000 years ago. It was larger and more robust than modern wolves.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-was-and-wasnt-done&quot;&gt;What was (and wasn’t) done&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colossal Biosciences used genetic material from modern gray wolves, not dogs. One of the major methodological advances was the use of cloning from endothelial progenitor cells, which are normally found in very small quantities in the inner lining of blood vessels. Unlike traditional cloning techniques, which rely on tissue samples obtained by biopsy (and can be contaminated by differentiated cells), this approach requires only a blood sample and the specific separation of these progenitor cells—something that until recently seemed like science fiction, as in the movie ‘The 6th Day.’ &lt;label for=&quot;cloning&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;cloning&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cloning:&lt;/strong&gt; An asexual reproduction technique that generates a genetically identical organism to the original. It can be done by nuclear transfer, as in the case of Dolly the sheep, or by other laboratory methods.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DNA of the gray wolves was then genetically edited using a CRISPR-Cas9 based technique, allowing for the modification of 20 DNA nucleotide positions in the original genetic material. These 20 changes were enough to give the resulting animals the appearance of a dire wolf. However, the original dire wolves had millions of base pairs different from modern gray wolves—so the modification is superficial and limited. &lt;label for=&quot;crispr-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;crispr-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;CRISPR:&lt;/strong&gt; A genetic editing tool based on a natural bacterial defense system, allowing precise, fast, and relatively inexpensive modification of DNA in organisms. It has revolutionized biotechnology and medicine.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the genetic editing, the nuclei of these modified cells were transferred into gray wolf eggs whose nuclei had been removed, a step similar to the classic cloning technique used in the famous Dolly the sheep. The resulting embryos, containing the edited genetic material, could then be implanted for development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genetically modified gray wolf embryos were implanted into domestic dogs, which gestated and gave birth to three pups. Therefore, these are not dire wolves, but gray wolves modified to look like dire wolves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The controversy increased in May 2025, when Colossal’s chief scientist publicly admitted that the animals created are not dire wolves and that there was, in fact, no de-extinction. This admission, widely reported in the media, reinforced the media-driven nature of the announcement and highlighted the importance of precise and transparent scientific communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists and outlets such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/dire-wolf-back-dead-not-exactly&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/portuguese/articles/c62973qwx4do&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt; were clear: there is no real de-extinction, nor evidence that dire wolves are back. The announcement was, for the most part, a media stunt, as also pointed out by &lt;a href=&quot;https://jornal.usp.br/radio-usp/nao-existem-evidencias-cientificas-da-recuperacao-dos-lobos-terriveis-extintos-ha-milhares-de-anos/&quot;&gt;Universidade de São Paulo - USP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-real-milestone-crispr-and-the-future&quot;&gt;The real milestone: CRISPR and the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the media exaggeration, the work represents a remarkable advance in the application of genetic editing in mammals, especially using CRISPR to insert genetic modifications similar to extinct species into modern genomes. This opens doors for research in biotechnology, animal and human health, and even for the conservation of endangered species—but not for “resurrecting” the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The immediate practical impact for ecology or species protection is zero. There are no benefits for the environment or biodiversity at this time. What we do have is a technological leap that could, in the future, revolutionize medicine, making it possible to create animals (and perhaps humans) resistant to diseases or with optimized traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-ethical-debate-and-a-disruptive-future&quot;&gt;The ethical debate and a disruptive future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most relevant—and underdiscussed—aspect is the potential of genetic editing to create living beings with unprecedented characteristics. The “dire wolf” is just a symbol: the real dilemma is how society will deal with the possibility of profoundly modifying humans and animals. CRISPR technology could, in the medium and long term, transform health, but it also brings enormous ethical challenges. &lt;label for=&quot;bioethics&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;bioethics&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Bioethics:&lt;/strong&gt; An interdisciplinary field that discusses the ethical, social, and legal boundaries of biomedical interventions such as cloning, genetic editing, and de-extinction. Essential for guiding responsible decisions in science.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The news of the dire wolf’s “de-extinction” is, in fact, a milestone for the future, not the past. The most important thing is not what was recovered, but what could be created. The debate about the limits and uses of genetic editing is just beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.04.09.647074v1.full.pdf&quot;&gt;Scientific preprint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/dire-wolf-back-dead-not-exactly&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/portuguese/articles/c62973qwx4do&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jornal.usp.br/radio-usp/nao-existem-evidencias-cientificas-da-recuperacao-dos-lobos-terriveis-extintos-ha-milhares-de-anos/&quot;&gt;Universidade de São Paulo - USP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://colossal.com/direwolf/&quot;&gt;Colossal Biosciences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://colossal.com/direwolf/science/&quot;&gt;Colossal - Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/7274542/colossal-dire-wolf/&quot;&gt;Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/18/direwolf-2025-en.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/18/direwolf-2025-en.html</guid>
        
        <category>De-extinction</category>
        
        <category>CRISPR</category>
        
        <category>Genetic editing</category>
        
        <category>Dire wolf</category>
        
        <category>Bioethics</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Early-onset cancer: the size of the problem and what we know so far</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In recent years, the scientific community and the public have paid increasing attention to the global rise in early-onset cancer&lt;label for=&quot;cancer&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;cancer&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cancer&lt;/strong&gt; (from Latin cancer = crab): a large group of very different diseases, all characterized by incessant and disordered cell proliferation, the ability to locally invade healthy tissues, and the ability to spread to distant sites (metastasis). The various types of cancer theoretically originate from a single cell (clonal origin) that has undergone mutations in its genetic code. Learn more &lt;a href=&quot;../../../2017/03/01/what-is-cancer.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
—defined as cancer diagnosed before the age of 50. The article by Ugai &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2022), published in Nature Reviews Clinical Oncology (&lt;a href=&quot;https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9509459/#SM1&quot;&gt;DOI: 10.1038/s41571-022-00672-8&lt;/a&gt;), showed that although cancer was traditionally associated with people over 50, its incidence is becoming increasingly common in young adults.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-early-onset-cancer&quot;&gt;What is early-onset cancer?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early-onset cancer refers to tumors diagnosed in people under 50 years old. Within this group, there are important subcategories: adolescents (15-18/24 years), young adults (25-39 years), and early middle-aged adults (40-49 years). The internationally used term for adolescents and young adults is AYA (adolescents and young adults), generally covering ages 15 to 39. The impact of a cancer diagnosis at this stage of life is profound, affecting not only health but also social, emotional, and economic aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classification of early-onset cancer was introduced in recent decades after the observation that certain types of cancer, traditionally rare in young people, began to show increased incidence in adults under 50. This definition gained prominence from the 2000s onwards, especially in international epidemiological studies&lt;label for=&quot;epidemiology&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;epidemiology&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Epidemiology&lt;/strong&gt; (from Greek epi = upon; demos = people; logos = study): the quantitative study of the distribution of health/disease phenomena and their conditioning and determining factors in human populations. It is a field of science that deals with various genetic, social, or environmental factors and conditions derived from microbiological, toxic, traumatic, etc. exposures that determine the occurrence and distribution of health, disease, disability, and death among groups of individuals.&lt;/span&gt;
, to differentiate tumors that arise early from those that occur at older ages. The goal is to facilitate surveillance, research, and the development of prevention and early diagnosis strategies for this group, which has distinct clinical characteristics, risk factors, and needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A search for the term “early onset cancer” in Google Scholar (with quotation marks, to force the search for the complete term) shows the earliest mention in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/jnci/53.6.1577&quot;&gt;1974 article&lt;/a&gt; on breast cancer, which already compared the disease in women under or over 45 years old. The authors of this study were interested in the impact of known risk factors in patients with early-onset disease (supposedly more linked to genetic and hereditary factors&lt;label for=&quot;gene-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;gene-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gene&lt;/strong&gt;: a segment of DNA that encodes a molecule (usually a protein) with a specific function. Genes are the units of inheritance first hypothesized by Mendel and named by the Danish botanist Wilhelm Johannsen in 1909. Genes make up only a small fraction of a cell’s DNA; most DNA does not code for proteins and is not part of genes. The phrase “one gene, one protein” summarizes the central dogma of biology: genetic information is transferred from DNA to RNA and then to a protein.&lt;/span&gt;
) or later-onset (supposedly more related to habits and environmental exposure). They found that a family history of breast cancer seemed to be a risk factor for earlier cases, as well as age over 25 at first childbirth. Interestingly, later-onset breast cancer cases did not show a correlation with age at first childbirth. Thus, even in this 1970s publication, there was already a clue that non-hereditary factors were acting in the emergence of early-onset cancer cases. The corresponding term in Portuguese (câncer de início precoce) only appears in academic works (very few) after 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of scientific publications on this topic (“early onset cancer”), between the 1970s and 2000, focused only on hereditary cancer cases, related to known genetic alterations, and did not differentiate a specific age group, sometimes including children up to middle age. The greater emphasis on Ugai’s working definition (adults under 50) really came in the 21st century. But where does this definition come from? Why is 50 years the cutoff? There is no direct answer, but I found a very interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/instance/1685650/pdf/ajhg00351-0124.pdf&quot;&gt;1983 study&lt;/a&gt; on hereditary cancer epidemiology and age at diagnosis, which tried, for the first time, to show that the occurrence of cancer in people younger than expected signaled some hereditary predisposition factor. The authors divided the group of patients they studied (with a family history of cancer) into groups according to the age of highest frequency of diagnosis for each cancer. The “young” group was bellow the 10th percentile of the age distribution and the “intermediate” group was between the 10th and 45th percentiles&lt;label for=&quot;percentile&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;percentile&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Percentile&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;statistics&lt;/em&gt;) in this context is a statistical measure that indicates the relative position of a value within an ordered data set. The percentile is the value below which a certain percentage of the data falls. For example, the 50th percentile (or median) is the value below which 50% of the data are located. If a student is in the 90th percentile on a test, it means they scored better than 90% of the other students who took the same test. The 10th percentile, on the other hand, indicates that 10% of the data are below that value. Percentiles are often used to understand the distribution of data and to identify outliers or extreme values. They are useful in various fields, such as education, health, and finance, to compare performance or characteristics between different groups or populations.
&lt;/span&gt;
. The median&lt;label for=&quot;median&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;median&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Median&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;statistics&lt;/em&gt;) is the value that separates the higher half and the lower half of a sample, a population, or a probability distribution. In simpler terms, the median can be the middle value of a data set. In the data set {1, 3, 3, &lt;b&gt;6&lt;/b&gt;, 7, 8, 9}, for example, the median is 6.
&lt;/span&gt;
 age of the “intermediate” group was 53 years, and the mean was 49 years. Thus, it makes sense that the age of 50 has been used more frequently to differentiate early-onset cancer patients from the rest. Curiously, the 1983 study did not prove the correlation between family history (heredity) and early-onset cancer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of maintaining epidemiological surveillance in this age group is growing, as early diagnosis can significantly impact prognosis and quality of life. In addition, understanding the factors associated with the increase in these tumors can help guide public policies and preventive interventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-we-know-incidence-is-rising&quot;&gt;How do we know incidence is rising?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple population-based cancer registries worldwide have shown a consistent increase in the incidence of several types of early-onset cancer since the 1990s. The Ugai article refers only to adults aged 20 to under 50, not children and adolescents. It analyzed data from the Global Cancer Observatory (&lt;a href=&quot;https://gco.iarc.fr/&quot;&gt;GLOBOCAN&lt;/a&gt;) on 14 types of cancer in adults aged 20 to 49, in 44 countries, and found that between 2002 and 2012, there was a significant increase in tumors such as colorectal, breast, kidney, liver, pancreas, stomach, and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors calculated the average annual percentage increase in the incidence of each cancer during the study period. For example, the incidence of colorectal cancer in women under 50 increased, on average, by about 2% per year in Australia, Canada, Denmark, France, Japan, the Netherlands, the UK, Turkey, and the USA. In Ecuador and South Korea, this increase was nearly 5% per year, indicating that this phenomenon was not restricted to developed Western countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ugai et al. analyzed global trends and showed that the incidence of early-onset colorectal cancer increased consistently in several countries since the 1990s, both in developed and developing nations. The increase is observed even in countries without systematic screening programs for young adults, suggesting that it is not just a matter of greater detection, but a real phenomenon. This pattern is repeated for other tumors, such as breast, kidney, liver, pancreas, and stomach, as detailed in the review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review by di Martino &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2022) published in the British Journal of Cancer (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41416-022-01704-x&quot;&gt;DOI: 10.1038/s41416-022-01704-x&lt;/a&gt;) started from the observation of an increased incidence of colorectal cancer, especially in developed countries, and tried to confirm this for this and 11 other cancer types. They conducted a literature review published between 1995 and 2020, including 98 studies (68 from North America and 24 from Europe). Most studies reported only one type of cancer, 8 described several types. The meta-analysis showed that the incidence of colorectal cancer in adults under 50 increased by about 1-3% per year on average, in both sexes, in North America (in Canada, this increase reached 6-7% per year in those under 30). In Europe, the same trend was documented. This observation was more pronounced the younger the patient group (8% average annual increase in people aged 20-29 between 2004 and 2016). In Australia, the same pattern was repeated, but the data were less consistent in New Zealand. Another finding: cancer cases in people under 50 are more aggressive and diagnosed at a more advanced stage. This may be due to delayed diagnosis because of lower clinical suspicion in this age group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early-onset cancers of the breast, kidney, uterus, pancreas, bladder, and larynx are also increasing in several countries, as highlighted by both works. This growth is observed in both developed and developing countries, reflecting changes in risk factors and lifestyles, as well as possible environmental and behavioral influences. The di Martino review, however, showed a trend toward a reduction in the incidence of early-onset lung cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article by Sung &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2024) published in The Lancet Public Health (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/s2468-2667(24)00156-7&quot;&gt;DOI: 10.1016/s2468-2667(24)00156-7&lt;/a&gt;) analyzed a population-based cancer registry in the USA. The authors used incidence data on 34 cancer types and mortality data on 25 types, in patients aged 24 to 85, diagnosed between 2000 and 2019. They compared the incidence adjusted by decade of birth, from 1920 to 1990. The study evaluated more than 23 million patients and more than 7 million cancer deaths in the period. They found that the incidence of 17 cancer types (small intestine, kidney and renal pelvis, pancreas, liver, intrahepatic bile ducts, breast, uterus, colon and rectum, stomach, gallbladder and other biliary tracts, ovary, testis, anus, Kaposi’s sarcoma) increased in people born more recently. As for mortality, it stabilized or decreased for most cancer types (except liver and intrahepatic bile ducts in women).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the publication by Teng &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2024) in Science China Life Sciences (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11427-023-2445-1&quot;&gt;DOI: 10.1007/s11427-023-2445-1&lt;/a&gt;) evaluated the annual report of the China Cancer Registry, calculating incidence and mortality in patients with 25 cancer types between 20-49 years, from 2000 to 2017. The authors found an increase in the incidence of all combined cases of early-onset cancer, with an average annual increase of about 1.5%, especially in the youngest group. They also found a reduction in mortality in this group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These data show that the phenomenon of increasing early-onset cancer incidence is global and not restricted to a few cancer types, affecting different regions and socioeconomic contexts, and not just the developed world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;which-cancer-types-are-rising-fastest&quot;&gt;Which cancer types are rising fastest?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gastrointestinal tumors are the most notable for their increase, especially colorectal, pancreas, stomach, and, notably, biliary tract tumors (such as cholangiocarcinoma and gallbladder cancer). The Nature Reviews Clinical Oncology article and Global Cancer Statistics 2024 data show that, in countries such as Canada, Sweden, the UK, and Bulgaria, the incidence of biliary tract cancer in adults under 50 increased on average between 3% and 5% per year, reaching 10% annual increase in Belarus (which, in a decade, amounts to a 100% increase in incidence!). Early-onset stomach cancer also grew significantly in the USA and Canada, reaching a 4-5% average annual increase in Northern Ireland, England, and Poland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early-onset pancreatic cancer, although still rare, increased its incidence by 1-3% per year in countries such as Australia, Canada, France, Sweden, the UK, and the USA. Liver cancer also increased, especially in Australia, Canada, Spain, the UK, Scotland, and Norway (in Ireland and Uganda, the increase was more than 9% per year!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These regional differences seem to reflect both environmental and behavioral factors as well as screening patterns, diet, and infection prevalence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-this-happening-main-hypotheses&quot;&gt;Why is this happening? Main hypotheses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is still no single explanation for the increase in early-onset cancer, but the various articles highlight several hypotheses. Below, we list the main ideas discussed in the recent literature, according to the sources we consulted. This is a quick overview; a more complete discussion of possible causes and associations with environmental exposures will be left for a second post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lifestyle changes&lt;/strong&gt;: increased sedentary behavior, obesity, diets high in ultra-processed foods and low in fiber are pointed out as central factors in all articles analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Early exposure to environmental and behavioral risk factors&lt;/strong&gt;: exposure to pollutants, passive smoking, alcohol, endocrine disruptors, and other environmental agents since childhood/adolescence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alterations in the gut microbiome&lt;/strong&gt;: changes in the microbiome&lt;label for=&quot;microbiome-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;microbiome-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Gut microbiome:&lt;/strong&gt; The gut microbiome is the set of trillions of microorganisms that inhabit the human gastrointestinal tract. The microbiome influences digestion, immunity, metabolism, and even the functioning of the nervous system.
&lt;/span&gt;
, possibly related to diet, antibiotic use, and cesarean sections, may influence cancer risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use of antibiotics and other medications in childhood&lt;/strong&gt;: suggested as a risk factor in several studies, but still with indirect evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genetic and epigenetic factors&lt;/strong&gt;: although genetic syndromes explain few cases, epigenetic changes induced by environment and lifestyle are increasingly discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sleep, circadian rhythm, and exposure to artificial light&lt;/strong&gt;: changes in sleep patterns and exposure to light at night may play a role in cancer risk, especially in urban populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Viral and bacterial infections&lt;/strong&gt;: hepatitis, H. pylori, and other infectious agents are relevant for liver and gastric tumors in specific regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article by di Martino &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; reinforces that most cases are not explained by known genetic syndromes, suggesting an important role for environmental and behavioral factors acquired in the first decades of life. The 2022 Nature Reviews Clinical Oncology article and the 2024 Science China Life Sciences article emphasize the role of the microbiome, diet, and early exposures as central factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;public-health-impacts&quot;&gt;Public health impacts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise in early-onset cancer represents a growing challenge for health systems worldwide. These patients have specific needs, may be underdiagnosed due to low clinical suspicion, and often face barriers to timely diagnosis and appropriate treatment. Strategies for prevention, early diagnosis, and research into causes are urgently needed.&lt;label for=&quot;prevention-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;prevention-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prevention&lt;/strong&gt;: set of actions and habits aimed at preventing the onset of diseases. For cancer, it includes not smoking, avoiding excessive alcohol, maintaining a healthy diet, exercising, and protecting yourself from the sun.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;perspectives-what-to-expect-for-the-future&quot;&gt;Perspectives: what to expect for the future?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still many uncertainties about the future incidence of early-onset cancer. Current data suggest that the upward trend may continue, especially if environmental and behavioral factors are not modified at the population level. However, understanding of the causes is still limited, and there is a need for longitudinal studies, investigations into early-life exposures, and research that integrates genetic, environmental, and microbiome data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible that, with greater awareness, public health policies, and advances in screening and prevention, it will be possible to reverse or at least slow this trend. On the other hand, without structural changes and more knowledge about the mechanisms involved, the increase may persist in the coming decades. Therefore, the scenario requires continuous epidemiological surveillance, international collaboration, and investment in multidisciplinary research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ciencia-medica/assets/img/nihms-1825592-f0001.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 1 from Ugai et al. 2022, Nature Reviews Clinical Oncology&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 1 from Ugai et al. (2022), Nature Reviews Clinical Oncology: Global incidence trends of early-onset cancers (diagnosed in adults &amp;lt;50 years) for 14 cancer types, 2002–2012, in 44 countries. Reproduced from the original article under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY 4.0). For full details, see: Ugai T, et al. Nat Rev Clin Oncol. 2022;19(10):656-673. &lt;a href=&quot;https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9509459/#SM1&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41571-022-00672-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ugai T, et al. Nature Reviews Clinical Oncology, 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9509459/#SM1&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41571-022-00672-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sung H, et al. The Lancet Public Health, 2024. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/s2468-2667(24)00156-7&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/s2468-2667(24)00156-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;di Martino E, et al. British Journal of Cancer, 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41416-022-01704-x&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41416-022-01704-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teng Y, et al. Science China Life Sciences, 2024. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11427-023-2445-1&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11427-023-2445-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/16/cancer-young-adults-2025.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/16/cancer-young-adults-2025.html</guid>
        
        <category>Cancer</category>
        
        <category>Early-onset</category>
        
        <category>Epidemiology</category>
        
        <category>Clinical research</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
