<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ciência médica</title>
    <description>Blog sobre ciência médica, pesquisa científica, oncologia pediátrica, farmacologia e outras ciências da saúde afins. Continuação do blog publicado em https://pharmakon.blogspot.com
</description>
    <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 20:10:23 -0300</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 20:10:23 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title></title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-problem-with-p-values-how-significant-are-they-really&quot;&gt;The problem with p values: how significant are they, really?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/profiles/geoff-cumming-4100&quot;&gt;Geoff Cumming&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;La Trobe University&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For researchers there’s a lot that turns on the &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value, the number used to determine whether a result is statistically significant. The current consensus is that if &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is less than .05, a study has reached the holy grail of being statistically significant, and therefore likely to be published. Over .05 and it’s usually back to the drawing board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But today, Texas A&amp;amp;M University professor &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stat.tamu.edu/directory-details.php?directoryid=321&quot;&gt;Valen Johnson&lt;/a&gt;, writing in the prestigious journal Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.1313476110&quot;&gt;argues&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; less than .05 is far too weak a standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using .05 is, he contends, a key reason why false claims are published and many published results fail to replicate. He advocates requiring .005 or even .001 as the criterion for statistical significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-p-value-anyway&quot;&gt;What is a &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value anyway?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value is at the heart of the most common approach to data analysis – null hypothesis significance testing (NHST). Think of NHST as a waltz with three steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;State a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.null-hypothesis.co.uk/science/item/what_is_a_null_hypothesis/&quot;&gt;null hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;: that is, there is no effect.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Calculate the &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value, which is the probability of getting results like ours – &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; the null hypothesis is true.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is sufficiently small, reject the null hypothesis and sound the trumpets: our effect is not zero, it’s statistically significant!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British statistician and geneticist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronald_Fisher&quot;&gt;Sir Ronald Fisher&lt;/a&gt; introduced &lt;a href=&quot;https://psychclassics.yorku.ca/Fisher/Methods/index.htm&quot;&gt;the &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value&lt;/a&gt; in 1925. He adopted .05 as a reference point for rejecting a null hypothesis. For him it was not a sharp cutoff: a thoughtful researcher should consider the context, and other results as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHST has, however, become deeply entrenched in medicine and numerous other disciplines. The precise value .05 has become a bar to wriggle under to achieve publication in top journals. Generations of students have been inducted into the rituals of .05 meaning “significant”, and .01 “highly significant”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sounds-good-whats-the-problem&quot;&gt;Sounds good. What’s the problem?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble is there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apastyle.org/manual/related/kline-2004.pdf&quot;&gt;numerous deep flaws&lt;/a&gt; in NHST.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://tiny.cc/nhstohdear&quot;&gt;evidence&lt;/a&gt; that students, researchers and even many teachers of statistics don’t understand NHST properly. More worryingly, there’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/neuro/journal/v14/n9/full/nn.2886.html&quot;&gt;evidence&lt;/a&gt; it’s widely misused, even in top journals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most researchers don’t appreciate that &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is highly unreliable. Repeat your experiment and you’ll get a &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value that could be extremely different. Even more surprisingly, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is highly unreliable even for &lt;a href=&quot;https://tiny.cc/pintervals&quot;&gt;very large samples&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHST may be a waltz, but the dance of &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is highly frenetic. Here’s a demonstration of why we simply shouldn’t trust any &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5OL1RqHrZQ8&quot;&gt;YouTube: Why p-values are unreliable&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all those problems, NHST persists, perhaps because we yearn for certainty. Declaring a result “significant” suggests certainty, even though our results almost always contain considerable uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;should-we-require-stronger-evidence&quot;&gt;Should we require stronger evidence?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Johnson makes a cogent argument that .05 provides only weak evidence against the null hypothesis: perhaps only odds of 3 or 4 to 1 against reasonable alternative hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He suggests we should require more persuasive odds, say 50 to 1 or even 200 to 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, we need to adopt .005 or .001 as our &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value criterion for statistical significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He recognises there’s a price to pay for demanding stronger evidence. In typical cases, we’d need to roughly double our sample sizes to still have a reasonable chance of finding true effects. Using larger samples would indeed be highly desirable, but sometimes that’s simply not possible. And are research grants about to double?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Johnson is correct that .05 corresponds to weak evidence, and .005 or .001 to evidence that’s usefully stronger. Adopting his stricter criterion would, however, mean that the majority of all published research analysed using NHST would fail the new test, and suddenly be statistically non-significant!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c479107.ssl.cf2.rackcdn.com/files/34853/width237/kzzxq98g-1384132459.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;shutupyourface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More fundamentally, merely shifting the criterion does not overcome the unreliability of &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, or most of the other deep flaws of NHST. The core problem is that NHST panders to our yearning for certainty by presenting the world as black or white — an effect is statistically significant or not; it exists or it doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact our world is many shades of grey — I won’t pretend to know how many. We need something more nuanced than NHST, and fortunately there are good alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-better-way-estimation-and-meta-analysis&quot;&gt;A better way: estimation and meta-analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiana.edu/~kruschke/DoingBayesianDataAnalysis/&quot;&gt;Bayesian techniques&lt;/a&gt; are highly promising and becoming widely used. Most readily available and already widely used is estimation based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://tiny.cc/GeoffConversation&quot;&gt;confidence intervals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A confidence interval gives us the best estimate of the true effect, and also indicates the extent of uncertainty in our results. Confidence intervals are also what we need to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://tiny.cc/GeoffConversation&quot;&gt;meta-analysis&lt;/a&gt;, which allows us to integrate results from a number of experiments that investigate the same issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often need to make clear decisions — whether or not to licence the new drug, for example — but NHST provides a poor basis for such decisions. It’s far better to use the integration of all available evidence to guide decisions, and estimation and meta-analysis provides that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merely shifting the NHST goal posts simply won’t do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Further reading:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/give-p-a-chance-significance-testing-is-misunderstood-20207&quot;&gt;Give p a chance: significance testing is misunderstood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Geoff Cumming has received funding from the Australian Research Council.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article was originally published at &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com&quot;&gt;The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;. Read the &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/the-problem-with-p-values-how-significant-are-they-really-20029&quot;&gt;original article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postagem original em Pharmakon &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;aqui&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 20:10:23 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/15/2013-11-19-the-problem-with-p-values-how.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/15/2013-11-19-the-problem-with-p-values-how.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fibromyalgia, chronic pain and the role of the gut microbiome: new findings from 2025</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A study published in &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032&quot;&gt;Neuron&lt;/a&gt; in 2025 and discussed on the TWIM (This Week in Microbiology) podcast on May 27th brought new evidence about the relationship between the gut microbiome and chronic pain in fibromyalgia. The work shows that changes in gut bacteria may not only be associated with, but also directly contribute to, pain and other symptoms of the disease.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction-what-is-fibromyalgia-and-why-does-the-microbiome-matter&quot;&gt;Introduction: What is fibromyalgia and why does the microbiome matter?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fibromyalgia is a common syndrome, marked by widespread pain, fatigue, sleep disturbances, and cognitive difficulties, mainly affecting women. It is estimated that fibromyalgia affects about 2% to 4% of the world population, being more prevalent in women between 30 and 60 years old. In Brazil, this represents millions of people living with chronic pain and a significant impact on quality of life, productivity, and healthcare costs. &lt;label for=&quot;fibromyalgia-epid-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;fibromyalgia-epid-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Fibromyalgia epidemiology:&lt;/strong&gt; Fibromyalgia affects about 2% to 4% of the world population, being more common in women. In Brazil, millions of people are estimated to live with the syndrome, which is one of the main causes of chronic pain and disability.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Despite its high prevalence, the causes of fibromyalgia are still poorly understood and available treatments are often unsatisfactory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does the microbiome matter for health?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gut microbiome is the set of trillions of microorganisms (mainly bacteria) that live in our digestive tract. It acts as a true “biochemical factory,” helping digest food, produce vitamins, regulate the immune system, and protect against infectious agents. In addition, the microbiome communicates with the brain through chemical substances and the enteric nervous system, influencing mood, metabolism, and even pain perception. Changes in the balance of these bacteria (dysbiosis) have been associated with several diseases, including metabolic, autoimmune, psychiatric disorders, and chronic pain conditions such as fibromyalgia. &lt;label for=&quot;microbiome-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;microbiome-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Gut microbiome:&lt;/strong&gt; The gut microbiome is the set of trillions of microorganisms that inhabit the human gastrointestinal tract. The microbiome influences digestion, immunity, metabolism, and even the functioning of the nervous system.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent studies suggest that the gut microbiome can influence the functioning of the nervous and immune systems, even affecting pain perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;methods-how-was-the-study-conducted&quot;&gt;Methods: How was the study conducted?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The researchers transplanted the microbiome (gut bacteria) from women with fibromyalgia into germ-free mice, comparing with transplants from healthy individuals. They also conducted a small open clinical study, in which women with fibromyalgia received microbiota transplants from healthy donors after antibiotic and bowel preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;main-results&quot;&gt;Main results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In mice:&lt;/strong&gt; Transplanting microbiota from fibromyalgia patients induced persistent pain, immune system changes, metabolic alterations, and reduced skin innervation—all phenomena similar to those observed in human patients. The mice showed increased sensitivity to mechanical, thermal (heat and cold), and spontaneous pain, without motor or cognitive changes. The study also showed that the patients’ microbiota led to changes in immune cells, activation of microglia in the spinal cord (cells involved in chronic pain), and changes in metabolites such as bile acids and neuroactive amino acids. &lt;label for=&quot;microglia-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;microglia-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Microglia:&lt;/strong&gt; Microglia are cells of the central nervous system that act as “defenders” of the brain and spinal cord. When chronically activated, they can contribute to persistent pain and inflammation.
&lt;/span&gt;
 When the mice later received microbiota from healthy people, the pain was reversed and part of the metabolic and immune changes returned to normal, suggesting a causal role of the microbiome in chronic pain in fibromyalgia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reversal:&lt;/strong&gt; When the mice subsequently received healthy microbiota, the pain was relieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.cell.com/cms/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032/asset/c4101b78-70b3-4e9b-84f1-25c59bce8c12/main.assets/gr5_lrg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 5 from the article&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 5 from the article: Graphs show that mice receiving microbiota from fibromyalgia patients had greater sensitivity to pain (mechanical, thermal, and spontaneous), and that subsequent transplantation of healthy microbiota reversed this, normalizing pain thresholds. Source: Cai W et al., Neuron, 2025.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the clinical study:&lt;/strong&gt; Women with severe, treatment-resistant fibromyalgia showed significant pain reduction and improved quality of life after receiving healthy microbiota transplants. The open clinical study involved 14 women, who received capsules of microbiota from healthy donors after bowel preparation. There was an average drop of 2 points on the pain scale (NRS), improvement in global disease impact (FIQ), reduction in anxiety and depression, better sleep, and improved physical quality of life. Sensory tests showed increased cold pain threshold and a trend toward improvement in heat pain. The metabolic profile and microbiome composition also changed, becoming more similar to the donors’. Adverse effects were mild and transient, mainly fatigue and mild gastrointestinal symptoms. &lt;label for=&quot;fmt-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;fmt-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Fecal Microbiota Transplantation (FMT):&lt;/strong&gt; A procedure in which gut bacteria from a healthy donor are transferred to the intestine of a patient, aiming to restore the balance of the microbiome. It is already used to treat &lt;em&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/em&gt; infections and is under study for other conditions.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.cell.com/cms/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032/asset/86701a65-abed-49f6-9c26-9a92e9d705fc/main.assets/gr6_lrg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 6 from the article&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 6 from the article: Graphs show that after healthy microbiota transplantation, women with fibromyalgia had significant reduction in pain intensity, improvement in global disease impact, anxiety, depression, sleep quality, and physical quality of life. The graphs also show changes in cold and heat pain thresholds. Source: Cai W et al., Neuron, 2025.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;significance-for-the-field-and-for-patients&quot;&gt;Significance for the field and for patients&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study provides evidence that the gut microbiome is not just a “bystander” in fibromyalgia, but may be one of the factors causing or perpetuating chronic pain. This opens the way for new therapeutic approaches, such as microbiota transplantation or the use of specific probiotics, and reinforces the importance of research on the relationship between the gut, immune system, and brain. &lt;label for=&quot;probiotic-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;probiotic-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Probiotics:&lt;/strong&gt; These are live microorganisms that, when administered in adequate amounts, confer health benefits. They can modulate the gut microbiome and are being studied as a complementary therapy in chronic diseases.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the promising results, it is important to remember that the clinical study was small and open-label (without a control group), and more research is needed before microbiota transplantation can be routinely recommended. Still, the work represents an important advance in understanding fibromyalgia and may inspire new strategies to treat chronic pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is TWiM?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TWiM (This Week in Microbiology) is a podcast created by virologist Vincent Racaniello, from Columbia University (USA), in 2010. The program discusses weekly advances and curiosities in microbiology, focusing on recent scientific articles and topics relevant to health and science. The regular members include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vincent Racaniello (Columbia University, USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Petra Levin (Washington University in St. Louis, USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michele Swanson (University of Michigan, USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Schmidt (Medical University of South Carolina, USA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All are recognized scientists in their fields. TWiM is part of the MicrobeTV network and is available for free at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microbe.tv/twim/&quot;&gt;microbe.tv/twim&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032&quot;&gt;Original article in Neuron&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microbe.tv/twim/twim-332/&quot;&gt;TWIM 332: Fibromyalgia pain and the gut microbiome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/12/fibromyalgia-microbiome-2025.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/12/fibromyalgia-microbiome-2025.html</guid>
        
        <category>Fibromyalgia</category>
        
        <category>Microbiome</category>
        
        <category>Chronic pain</category>
        
        <category>Clinical research</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fibromialgia, dor crônica e o papel do microbioma intestinal: novos achados de 2025</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Um estudo publicado na revista &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032&quot;&gt;Neuron&lt;/a&gt; em 2025 e discutido no podcast TWIM (This Week in Microbiology) de 27 de maio trouxe novas evidências sobre a relação entre o microbioma intestinal e a dor crônica na fibromialgia. O trabalho mostra que alterações nas bactérias intestinais podem não só estar associadas, mas também contribuir diretamente para a dor e outros sintomas da doença.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introdução-o-que-é-fibromialgia-e-por-que-o-microbioma-importa&quot;&gt;Introdução: O que é fibromialgia e por que o microbioma importa?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fibromialgia é uma síndrome comum, marcada por dor generalizada, fadiga, distúrbios do sono e dificuldades cognitivas, afetando principalmente mulheres. Estima-se que a fibromialgia atinja cerca de 2% a 4% da população mundial, sendo mais prevalente em mulheres entre 30 e 60 anos. No Brasil, isso representa milhões de pessoas convivendo com dor crônica e impacto significativo na qualidade de vida, produtividade e custos de saúde. &lt;label for=&quot;fibromialgia-epid&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;fibromialgia-epid&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Epidemiologia da fibromialgia:&lt;/strong&gt; A fibromialgia afeta cerca de 2% a 4% da população mundial, sendo mais comum em mulheres. No Brasil, estima-se que milhões de pessoas convivam com a síndrome, que é uma das principais causas de dor crônica e incapacidade.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Apesar de sua alta prevalência, as causas da fibromialgia ainda são pouco compreendidas e os tratamentos disponíveis costumam ser insatisfatórios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Por que o microbioma importa para a saúde?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O microbioma intestinal é o conjunto de trilhões de microrganismos (principalmente bactérias) que vivem no nosso trato digestivo. Ele atua como uma verdadeira “fábrica bioquímica”, ajudando na digestão de alimentos, produção de vitaminas, regulação do sistema imunológico e proteção contra agentes infecciosos. Além disso, o microbioma se comunica com o cérebro por meio de substâncias químicas e do sistema nervoso entérico, influenciando o humor, o metabolismo e até a percepção da dor. Alterações no equilíbrio dessas bactérias (disbiose) têm sido associadas a diversas doenças, incluindo distúrbios metabólicos, autoimunes, psiquiátricos e condições de dor crônica como a fibromialgia. &lt;label for=&quot;microbioma&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;microbioma&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Microbioma intestinal:&lt;/strong&gt; É o conjunto de trilhões de microrganismos que habitam o trato gastrointestinal humano. O microbioma influencia digestão, imunidade, metabolismo e até o funcionamento do sistema nervoso.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estudos recentes sugerem que o microbioma intestinal pode influenciar o funcionamento do sistema nervoso e do sistema imunológico, afetando inclusive a percepção da dor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;metodologia-como-o-estudo-foi-feito&quot;&gt;Metodologia: Como o estudo foi feito?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Os pesquisadores transplantaram o microbioma (bactérias intestinais) de mulheres com fibromialgia para camundongos criados em ambiente estéril (germ-free), comparando com transplantes de pessoas saudáveis. Também realizaram um pequeno estudo clínico aberto, em que mulheres com fibromialgia receberam transplante de microbiota de doadoras saudáveis, após preparo com antibióticos e limpeza intestinal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resultados-principais&quot;&gt;Resultados principais&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Em camundongos:&lt;/strong&gt; O transplante de microbiota de pacientes com fibromialgia induziu dor persistente, alterações no sistema imunológico, mudanças no metabolismo e redução da inervação da pele — todos fenômenos semelhantes aos observados em pacientes humanos. Os camundongos apresentaram maior sensibilidade à dor mecânica, térmica (calor e frio) e espontânea, sem alterações motoras ou cognitivas. O estudo também mostrou que a microbiota de pacientes levou a alterações em células do sistema imune, ativação de microglia na medula espinhal (células envolvidas na dor crônica) e mudanças em metabólitos como ácidos biliares e aminoácidos neuroativos. &lt;label for=&quot;microglia&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;microglia&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Microglia:&lt;/strong&gt; São células do sistema nervoso central que atuam como “defensoras” do cérebro e da medula espinhal. Quando ativadas de forma crônica, podem contribuir para a dor persistente e inflamação.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Quando os camundongos receberam, posteriormente, microbiota de pessoas saudáveis, a dor foi revertida e parte das alterações metabólicas e imunes voltou ao normal, sugerindo um papel causal do microbioma na dor crônica da fibromialgia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reversão do quadro:&lt;/strong&gt; Quando os camundongos receberam, posteriormente, microbiota de pessoas saudáveis, a dor foi aliviada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.cell.com/cms/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032/asset/c4101b78-70b3-4e9b-84f1-25c59bce8c12/main.assets/gr5_lrg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figura 5 do artigo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figura 5 do artigo: Gráficos mostram que camundongos que receberam microbiota de pacientes com fibromialgia apresentaram maior sensibilidade à dor (mecânica, térmica e espontânea), e que o transplante subsequente de microbiota saudável reverteu esse quadro, normalizando os limiares de dor. Fonte: Cai W et al., Neuron, 2025.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No estudo clínico:&lt;/strong&gt; Mulheres com fibromialgia grave e resistente a tratamentos apresentaram redução significativa da dor e melhora da qualidade de vida após receberem transplante de microbiota saudável. O estudo clínico aberto envolveu 14 mulheres, que receberam cápsulas de microbiota de doadoras saudáveis após preparo intestinal. Houve queda média de 2 pontos na escala de dor (NRS), melhora do impacto global da doença (FIQ), redução de ansiedade e depressão, melhora do sono e da qualidade de vida física. Testes sensoriais mostraram aumento do limiar de dor ao frio e tendência de melhora ao calor. O perfil metabólico e a composição do microbioma também mudaram, aproximando-se do perfil das doadoras. Os efeitos adversos foram leves e transitórios, principalmente fadiga e sintomas gastrointestinais leves. &lt;label for=&quot;fmt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;fmt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Transplante de Microbiota Fecal (FMT):&lt;/strong&gt; Procedimento em que bactérias intestinais de um doador saudável são transferidas para o intestino de um paciente, visando restaurar o equilíbrio do microbioma. Já é usado para tratar infecções por &lt;em&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/em&gt; e está em estudo para outras condições.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.cell.com/cms/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032/asset/86701a65-abed-49f6-9c26-9a92e9d705fc/main.assets/gr6_lrg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figura 6 do artigo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figura 6 do artigo: Gráficos mostram que, após o transplante de microbiota saudável, mulheres com fibromialgia apresentaram redução significativa da intensidade da dor, melhora do impacto global da doença, ansiedade, depressão, qualidade do sono e qualidade de vida física. Os gráficos também mostram a mudança no limiar de dor ao frio e calor. Fonte: Cai W et al., Neuron, 2025.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;significado-para-o-campo-e-para-os-pacientes&quot;&gt;Significado para o campo e para os pacientes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O estudo fornece evidências de que o microbioma intestinal não é apenas um “espectador” na fibromialgia, mas pode ser um dos fatores que causam ou perpetuam a dor crônica. Isso abre caminho para novas abordagens terapêuticas, como o transplante de microbiota ou o uso de probióticos específicos, além de reforçar a importância de pesquisas sobre a relação entre intestino, sistema imunológico e cérebro. &lt;label for=&quot;probiotico&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;probiotico&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Probióticos:&lt;/strong&gt; São microrganismos vivos que, quando administrados em quantidades adequadas, conferem benefícios à saúde. Podem modular o microbioma intestinal e estão sendo estudados como terapia complementar em doenças crônicas.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apesar dos resultados promissores, é importante lembrar que o estudo clínico foi pequeno e aberto (sem grupo controle), e mais pesquisas são necessárias antes que o transplante de microbiota possa ser recomendado rotineiramente. Ainda assim, o trabalho representa um avanço importante na compreensão da fibromialgia e pode inspirar novas estratégias para tratar a dor crônica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;O que é o TWiM?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O TWiM (This Week in Microbiology) é um podcast criado pelo virologista Vincent Racaniello, da Universidade Columbia (EUA), em 2010. O programa discute semanalmente avanços e curiosidades em microbiologia, com foco em artigos científicos recentes e temas relevantes para a saúde e a ciência. Os integrantes regulares incluem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vincent Racaniello (Universidade Columbia, EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Petra Levin (Universidade Washington em St. Louis, EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michele Swanson (Universidade de Michigan, EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Schmidt (Universidade Médica da Carolina do Sul, EUA).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todos são cientistas reconhecidos em suas áreas. O TWiM faz parte da rede MicrobeTV e está disponível gratuitamente em &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microbe.tv/twim/&quot;&gt;microbe.tv/twim&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Referências:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032&quot;&gt;Artigo original na Neuron&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microbe.tv/twim/twim-332/&quot;&gt;TWIM 332: Fibromyalgia pain and the gut microbiome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/12/fibromialgia-microbioma-2025.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/12/fibromialgia-microbioma-2025.html</guid>
        
        <category>Fibromialgia</category>
        
        <category>Microbioma</category>
        
        <category>Dor crônica</category>
        
        <category>Pesquisa clínica</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine 2020–2024: Five Years of Breakthroughs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last five years, the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine has recognized discoveries that have revolutionized our understanding of genetics, molecular biology, and medicine. Below is a summary table of the laureates, their countries, and the main themes:
  &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Theme&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Laureates&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Country&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2020&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Discovery of Hepatitis C virus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Harvey J. Alter, Michael Houghton, Charles M. Rice&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA, UK, Canada&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2021&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Receptors for temperature and touch&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;David Julius, Ardem Patapoutian&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA, Lebanon/USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2022&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Genomes of extinct hominins and human evolution&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Svante Pääbo&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sweden, Germany&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2023&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;mRNA vaccine technology&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Katalin Karikó, Drew Weissman&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hungary/USA, USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2024&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Discovery of microRNA and gene regulation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Victor Ambros, Gary Ruvkun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;laureates-and-themes&quot;&gt;Laureates and Themes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2020-discovery-of-hepatitis-c-virus&quot;&gt;2020: Discovery of Hepatitis C Virus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureates:&lt;/strong&gt; Harvey J. Alter (USA), Michael Houghton (UK/Canada), Charles M. Rice (USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theme:&lt;/strong&gt; Identification of the hepatitis C virus, enabling blood tests and curative therapies for a major cause of chronic hepatitis and liver cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before these discoveries, millions were infected through contaminated blood transfusions, with no precise diagnosis. The laureates’ work enabled highly sensitive blood tests, eliminating transfusion-related transmission and leading to antivirals that now cure hepatitis C in over 95% of cases. &lt;label for=&quot;antiviral-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;antiviral-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Antiviral: a type of medication used to treat viral infections by inhibiting the development or replication of viruses. Antivirals are distinct from antibiotics, which target bacteria.&lt;/span&gt;
 The global impact is profound, with the World Health Organization targeting hepatitis C elimination as a public health threat.
&lt;label for=&quot;gene-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;gene-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Gene: a segment of DNA that encodes a molecule (usually a protein) with a specific function. Genes are the units of inheritance first hypothesized by Mendel and named by the Danish botanist Wilhelm Johannsen in 1909. Genes make up only a small fraction of a cell’s DNA; most DNA does not code for proteins and is not part of genes. The phrase “one gene, one protein” summarizes the central dogma of biology: genetic information is transferred from DNA to RNA and then to a protein.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;label for=&quot;who-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;who-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;World Health Organization (WHO): a specialized agency of the United Nations responsible for international public health. Founded in 1948, the WHO coordinates global health responses, sets standards, and provides guidance on health issues, disease prevention, and control.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/ba/Dr._Harvey_J._Alter_wins_2020_Nobel_Prize_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Dr._Harvey_J._Alter_wins_2020_Nobel_Prize_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Harvey J. Alter&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Harvey J. Alter. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvey_J._Alter&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e4/Prof_Michael_Houghton.jpg/250px-Prof_Michael_Houghton.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Michael Houghton&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Michael Houghton. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Houghton&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6d/Charles_M._Rice.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Charles M. Rice&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Charles M. Rice. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_M._Rice&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2021-receptors-for-temperature-and-touch&quot;&gt;2021: Receptors for Temperature and Touch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureates:&lt;/strong&gt; David Julius (USA), Ardem Patapoutian (Lebanon/USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theme:&lt;/strong&gt; Discovery of how our bodies sense temperature and mechanical stimuli, through TRP and Piezo receptors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julius used capsaicin (the spicy compound in chili peppers) to identify the TRPV1 receptor, responsible for heat sensation. Patapoutian discovered Piezo1 and Piezo2 receptors, essential for touch and pressure. These findings opened new fields in sensory neuroscience, directly impacting the development of painkillers and treatments for chronic pain, and explaining rare genetic diseases related to proprioception. &lt;label for=&quot;pain-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;pain-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Pain: an unpleasant sensory and emotional experience associated with actual or potential tissue damage. Pain can be acute (short-term) or chronic (long-lasting), and is a major focus of medical research and treatment.&lt;/span&gt;
 Julius and Patapoutian also collaborated and co-published, highlighting the interconnectedness of the scientific community.
&lt;label for=&quot;receptor-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;receptor-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Receptor: a protein molecule, usually found on the surface of a cell, that receives and responds to chemical signals from outside the cell. Receptors are essential for communication between cells and for the body’s response to hormones, neurotransmitters, and other signaling molecules.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/49/Dr_David_Julius_by_christopher_michel_in_2022_04_%28cropped2%29.jpg/250px-Dr_David_Julius_by_christopher_michel_in_2022_04_%28cropped2%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;David Julius&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;David Julius. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Julius&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e6/Ardem_Patapoutian_by_C_Michel_67_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Ardem_Patapoutian_by_C_Michel_67_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ardem Patapoutian&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ardem Patapoutian. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ardem_Patapoutian&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2022-genomes-of-extinct-hominins-and-human-evolution&quot;&gt;2022: Genomes of Extinct Hominins and Human Evolution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureate:&lt;/strong&gt; Svante Pääbo (Sweden/Germany)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theme:&lt;/strong&gt; Sequencing the Neanderthal genome and discovering Denisovans, revealing interbreeding with Homo sapiens and transforming our understanding of human evolution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pääbo founded paleogenomics, overcoming technical challenges to extract and sequence ancient DNA. His team showed that modern humans inherited genes from Neanderthals and Denisovans, influencing immunity, metabolism, and even responses to diseases like COVID-19. &lt;label for=&quot;immune-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;immune-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Immune system: the complex network of cells, tissues, and organs that defends the body against infections and diseases. It recognizes and neutralizes pathogens such as bacteria, viruses, and other foreign substances.&lt;/span&gt;
 For example, Neanderthal gene variants affect blood clotting (&lt;em&gt;F5&lt;/em&gt;), pain sensitivity (&lt;em&gt;SCN9A&lt;/em&gt;), and antiviral immunity (OAS gene cluster), while a Denisovan gene (&lt;em&gt;EPAS1&lt;/em&gt;) increases altitude tolerance in Himalayan populations. Pääbo’s work inspired multidisciplinary collaborations, and his son, Hugo Zeberg, also works in the field, showing family continuity in research.
&lt;label for=&quot;genome-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;genome-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Genome: the complete genetic material of an organism. It includes all genes, non-coding DNA sequences (which are not genes), and also the genetic material in organelles such as mitochondria. For example, the 22,000 human genes make up less than 2% of the human genome.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/26/Professor_Svante_Paabo_ForMemRS_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Professor_Svante_Paabo_ForMemRS_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Svante Pääbo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Svante Pääbo. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Svante_P%C3%A4%C3%A4bo&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2023-mrna-vaccine-technology&quot;&gt;2023: mRNA Vaccine Technology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureates:&lt;/strong&gt; Katalin Karikó (Hungary/USA), Drew Weissman (USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theme:&lt;/strong&gt; Discoveries enabling the development of mRNA vaccines, crucial in the fight against COVID-19 and opening new avenues for vaccines and therapies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karikó and Weissman faced years of skepticism and lack of funding, but their persistence led to the modification of mRNA to avoid inflammatory responses, making clinical use possible. The technology was rapidly applied to COVID-19 vaccines, setting a record for speed and saving millions of lives. Today, mRNA platforms are being tested for cancer, HIV, and autoimmune diseases. Karikó and Weissman collaborated directly, and their stories inspire scientists about the importance of resilience and international collaboration.
&lt;label for=&quot;mrna-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;mrna-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;mRNA (messenger RNA): a type of RNA that carries genetic information from DNA to the cell’s protein-making machinery (ribosomes). mRNA serves as the template for protein synthesis, playing a central role in the expression of genetic information.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/3e/Katalin_Karik%C3%B3_at_the_United_States_Embassy_Sweden%2C_2023_Nobel_Reception_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Katalin_Karik%C3%BÓ_at_the_United_States_Embassy_Sweden%2C_2023_Nobel_Reception_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Katalin Karikó&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Katalin Karikó. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katalin_Karik%C3%B3&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e2/Drew_Weissman%2C_2023_Nobel_Laureate_in_Medicine_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Drew_Weissman%2C_2023_Nobel_Laureate_in_Medicine_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drew Weissman&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Drew Weissman. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drew_Weissman&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2024-discovery-of-microrna-and-gene-regulation&quot;&gt;2024: Discovery of microRNA and Gene Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureates:&lt;/strong&gt; Victor Ambros (USA), Gary Ruvkun (USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theme:&lt;/strong&gt; Discovery of microRNAs, small RNA molecules that regulate gene expression, with profound implications for development, disease, and therapeutics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambros and Ruvkun, who worked in parallel and also collaborated, showed that small non-coding RNAs control gene expression in animals and humans. The microRNA field exploded, revealing roles in cancer, heart disease, neurodegeneration, and immunity. The first RNA interference therapy approved for clinical use (patisiran, for hereditary amyloidosis) is a direct result of these discoveries. RNA-based therapies are now in clinical trials, and the discovery changed our view of so-called “junk DNA.” Both laureates have collaborated with other Nobel winners, such as Robert Horvitz.
&lt;label for=&quot;dna-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;dna-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid): a complex organic molecule, DNA is a polymer—a chain made up of simpler molecules. It is composed of four types of molecules: adenine, cytosine, guanine, and thymine, which are nucleotides, the monomers (individual parts) that make up the DNA polymer. Each DNA molecule consists of two long strands of nucleotides that coil into a double helix. The order of nucleotides along the DNA strand is not random; it forms a code, called the genetic code, which stores the information needed to produce all the proteins in a cell. In fact, the DNA in each cell contains the information necessary to reproduce the entire organism.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/de/Victor_Ambros%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine.jpg/250px-Victor_Ambros%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Victor Ambros&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Victor Ambros. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victor_Ambros&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/24/Gary_Ruvkun%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine_3_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Gary_Ruvkun%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine_3_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gary Ruvkun&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Gary Ruvkun. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_Ruvkun&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-unites-the-themes-and-laureates&quot;&gt;What Unites the Themes and Laureates?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molecular and Genetic Focus:&lt;/strong&gt; All prizes highlight advances in molecular biology, genetics, and the mechanisms underlying health and disease.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Translational Impact:&lt;/strong&gt; Each discovery has led to new diagnostics, therapies, or fundamental shifts in biomedical science.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Collaboration:&lt;/strong&gt; Many laureates have worked across countries and institutions, reflecting the global nature of modern science.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diversity of Backgrounds:&lt;/strong&gt; Laureates include immigrants and those with multicultural backgrounds (e.g., Karikó from Hungary, Patapoutian from Lebanon).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Active Scientists:&lt;/strong&gt; As of June 2025, all laureates are alive and most remain active in research or academia, except Michael Houghton, who retired but is still alive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interrelations:&lt;/strong&gt; Several laureates have collaborated with each other or with other Nobel winners, showing the importance of scientific networks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;controversies-and-curiosities&quot;&gt;Controversies and Curiosities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020:&lt;/strong&gt; Debate over the exclusion of other contributors to hepatitis C research, but the main discoverers were recognized.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021:&lt;/strong&gt; No major controversies; the discoveries were widely accepted and celebrated.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2022:&lt;/strong&gt; Some discussion about the focus on ancient DNA, but Pääbo’s pioneering work was universally acknowledged.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2023:&lt;/strong&gt; The rapid development and deployment of mRNA vaccines during the COVID-19 pandemic sparked public debate, but the scientific achievement was clear. Karikó’s long struggle for recognition before the Nobel was widely discussed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2024:&lt;/strong&gt; The microRNA field is vast, and some researchers contributed to its development, but Ambros and Ruvkun’s foundational discoveries were decisive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications-for-the-present-and-future&quot;&gt;Implications for the Present and Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The awarded technologies and discoveries already have a profound impact today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hepatitis C:&lt;/strong&gt; The disease is close to eradication in several countries thanks to tests and treatments derived from the 2020 discoveries.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/hepatitis-c&quot;&gt;Learn more: WHO - Hepatitis C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mRNA Vaccines:&lt;/strong&gt; The mRNA platform is being adapted for vaccines against cancer, HIV, influenza, and autoimmune diseases, with clinical trials underway. The record speed of COVID-19 vaccine development demonstrated the potential of this technology.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02483-w&quot;&gt;Nature - mRNA vaccines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;microRNA and RNAi:&lt;/strong&gt; The first RNA interference therapy approved for clinical use was patisiran (Onpattro), for hereditary transthyretin amyloidosis, in 2018. Since then, six RNAi therapies have been FDA-approved, expanding treatment options for genetic and chronic diseases and potentially revolutionizing personalized medicine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/drugs/spotlight-cder-science/new-class-drugs-fulfills-promise-rna-based-medicine&quot;&gt;FDA - RNAi therapies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41573-024-00912-9&quot;&gt;Nature Reviews Drug Discovery - RNAi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evolutionary Genetics:&lt;/strong&gt; Genes inherited from Neanderthals, such as &lt;em&gt;F5&lt;/em&gt; (clotting), &lt;em&gt;SCN9A&lt;/em&gt; (pain sensitivity), and variants in the &lt;em&gt;OAS&lt;/em&gt; cluster (antiviral immunity), affect current human traits. A Denisovan gene, &lt;em&gt;EPAS1&lt;/em&gt;, increases altitude tolerance in Tibetans. These findings help explain disease susceptibility and human adaptations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-020-2818-3&quot;&gt;Nature - Neanderthal DNA and COVID-19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/tibetans-inherited-high-altitude-gene-ancient-human&quot;&gt;Science - Denisovan gene and altitude&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sensory Neuroscience:&lt;/strong&gt; New painkillers and treatments for chronic pain and neurological diseases are being developed based on the receptors discovered in 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/hot-and-cool-research-wins-nobel-prize-physiology-or-medicine&quot;&gt;Science - Pain research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, these discoveries are expected to continue transforming medicine, making diagnostics more precise, treatments more personalized, and deepening our understanding of life’s fundamental mechanisms. International exchange, multidisciplinary collaboration, and the value of basic science have proven essential for advances that benefit all humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last five years of Nobel Prizes in Medicine reflect a golden era for molecular biology and genetics, with discoveries that have immediate impact on human health and deepen our understanding of life itself. Scientific research is fundamental to human well-being and societal progress. However, the rise of scientific denialism and misinformation is concerning, as it threatens historic achievements and hinders access to treatments and vaccines. It is therefore essential to value and disseminate quality, evidence-based information, so that the benefits of science reach everyone and society can make informed decisions about health and public policy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/10/nobel-medicine-20-24.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/10/nobel-medicine-20-24.html</guid>
        
        <category>Physiology or Medicine</category>
        
        <category>Nobel Prize</category>
        
        <category>Science History</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Prêmio Nobel de Fisiologia ou Medicina 2020–2024: Cinco Anos de Revoluções</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nos últimos cinco anos, o Prêmio Nobel de Fisiologia ou Medicina reconheceu descobertas que revolucionaram a genética, a biologia molecular e a medicina. Veja abaixo uma tabela-resumo dos laureados, seus países e os principais temas:
  &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Ano&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Tema&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Laureados&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;País(es)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2020&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Descoberta do vírus da Hepatite C&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Harvey J. Alter, Michael Houghton, Charles M. Rice&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;EUA, Reino Unido, Canadá&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2021&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Receptores de temperatura e tato&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;David Julius, Ardem Patapoutian&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;EUA, Líbano/EUA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2022&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Genomas de hominídeos extintos e evolução&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Svante Pääbo&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Suécia, Alemanha&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2023&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tecnologia de vacinas de mRNA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Katalin Karikó, Drew Weissman&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hungria/EUA, EUA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2024&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Descoberta do microRNA e regulação gênica&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Victor Ambros, Gary Ruvkun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;EUA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;laureados-e-temas&quot;&gt;Laureados e Temas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2020-descoberta-do-vírus-da-hepatite-c&quot;&gt;2020: Descoberta do Vírus da Hepatite C&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureados:&lt;/strong&gt; Harvey J. Alter (EUA), Michael Houghton (Reino Unido/Canadá), Charles M. Rice (EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tema:&lt;/strong&gt; Identificação do vírus da hepatite C, permitindo testes sanguíneos e terapias curativas para uma das principais causas de hepatite crônica e câncer de fígado.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antes dessas descobertas, milhões de pessoas eram infectadas por transfusões de sangue contaminado, sem diagnóstico preciso. O trabalho dos laureados permitiu o desenvolvimento de testes altamente sensíveis, tornando possível eliminar a transmissão do vírus por transfusões e levando ao desenvolvimento de antivirais que hoje curam a hepatite C em mais de 95% dos casos. &lt;label for=&quot;antiviral-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;antiviral-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Antiviral: medicamento utilizado para tratar infecções virais, inibindo o desenvolvimento ou a replicação dos vírus. Antivirais são diferentes de antibióticos, que atuam contra bactérias.&lt;/span&gt;
 O impacto é global, com a Organização Mundial da Saúde estabelecendo a meta de erradicação da hepatite C como problema de saúde pública.
&lt;label for=&quot;gene&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;gene&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Gene (&lt;em&gt;gr gonos&lt;/em&gt; = geração, semente): trecho de DNA que
  codifica uma molécula (proteína) com uma função. Correspondem às unidades de herança
  hipotetizadas por Mendel e denominadas de genes pelo botânico dinamarquês
  Johannsen em 1905. Constitui uma minoria do DNA de uma célula. A maior parte do DNA
  não codifica proteínas e, portanto, não faz parte de genes. A expressão “um gene,
  uma proteína” resume o &lt;em&gt;dogma central da biologia&lt;/em&gt;, de que a informação genética
  é transferida (codificada) do DNA para o RNA e deste para uma proteína
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;label for=&quot;oms-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;oms-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Organização Mundial da Saúde (OMS): agência especializada das Nações Unidas responsável pela saúde pública internacional. Fundada em 1948, a OMS coordena respostas globais, define padrões e fornece orientações sobre saúde, prevenção e controle de doenças.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/ba/Dr._Harvey_J._Alter_wins_2020_Nobel_Prize_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Dr._Harvey_J._Alter_wins_2020_Nobel_Prize_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Harvey J. Alter&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Harvey J. Alter. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvey_J._Alter&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e4/Prof_Michael_Houghton.jpg/250px-Prof_Michael_Houghton.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Michael Houghton&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Michael Houghton. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Houghton&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6d/Charles_M._Rice.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Charles M. Rice&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Charles M. Rice. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_M._Rice&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2021-receptores-de-temperatura-e-tato&quot;&gt;2021: Receptores de Temperatura e Tato&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureados:&lt;/strong&gt; David Julius (EUA), Ardem Patapoutian (Líbano/EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tema:&lt;/strong&gt; Descoberta de como o corpo sente temperatura e estímulos mecânicos, através dos receptores TRP e Piezo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julius utilizou a capsaicina (composto da pimenta) para identificar o receptor TRPV1, responsável pela sensação de calor. Patapoutian identificou os receptores Piezo1 e Piezo2, essenciais para a sensação de toque e pressão. Essas descobertas abriram novas áreas na neurociência sensorial, com impacto direto no desenvolvimento de analgésicos e tratamentos para dor crônica, além de explicar doenças genéticas raras ligadas à propriocepção. &lt;label for=&quot;pain-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;pain-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Dor: experiência sensorial e emocional desagradável associada a dano real ou potencial aos tecidos. Pode ser aguda (curta duração) ou crônica (longa duração), sendo um dos principais focos de pesquisa e tratamento em medicina.&lt;/span&gt;
 Julius e Patapoutian também colaboraram e publicaram juntos em alguns momentos, mostrando a interconexão da comunidade científica.
&lt;label for=&quot;receptor-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;receptor-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Receptor: molécula (geralmente uma proteína) presente na superfície ou interior das células, responsável por receber e responder a sinais químicos do ambiente. Receptores são essenciais para a comunicação entre células e para a resposta do organismo a hormônios, neurotransmissores e outros sinais.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/49/Dr_David_Julius_by_christopher_michel_in_2022_04_%28cropped2%29.jpg/250px-Dr_David_Julius_by_christopher_michel_in_2022_04_%28cropped2%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;David Julius&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;David Julius. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Julius&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e6/Ardem_Patapoutian_by_C_Michel_67_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Ardem_Patapoutian_by_C_Michel_67_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ardem Patapoutian&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ardem Patapoutian. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ardem_Patapoutian&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2022-genomas-de-hominídeos-extintos-e-evolução-humana&quot;&gt;2022: Genomas de Hominídeos Extintos e Evolução Humana&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureado:&lt;/strong&gt; Svante Pääbo (Suécia/Alemanha)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tema:&lt;/strong&gt; Sequenciamento do genoma neandertal e descoberta dos denisovanos, revelando cruzamentos com Homo sapiens e transformando a compreensão da evolução humana.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pääbo fundou a paleogenômica, superando desafios técnicos para extrair e sequenciar DNA antigo. Sua equipe mostrou que humanos modernos herdaram genes de neandertais e denisovanos, influenciando imunidade, metabolismo e até resposta a doenças como COVID-19. &lt;label for=&quot;immune-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;immune-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Sistema imunológico: rede complexa de células, tecidos e órgãos que defende o organismo contra infecções e doenças. Reconhece e neutraliza patógenos como bactérias, vírus e outras substâncias estranhas.&lt;/span&gt;
 Por exemplo, variantes de genes neandertais afetam a coagulação do sangue e a sensibilidade à dor, enquanto um gene herdado dos denisovanos aumenta a resistência à altitude em populações do Himalaia. O trabalho de Pääbo inspirou colaborações multidisciplinares entre genética, arqueologia e antropologia, e seu filho, Hugo Zeberg, também atua na área, mostrando continuidade familiar na pesquisa.
&lt;label for=&quot;genoma&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;genoma&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Genoma: material genético de um organismo. Inclui todos os
  genes, as sequências de DNA &lt;em&gt;não codificante&lt;/em&gt; (que não são genes) e também o
  material genético em organelas como as mitocôndrias. Por exemplo, os 22 mil genes
  humanos constituem menos de 2% do genoma humano.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/26/Professor_Svante_Paabo_ForMemRS_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Professor_Svante_Paabo_ForMemRS_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Svante Pääbo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Svante Pääbo. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Svante_P%C3%A4%C3%A4bo&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2023-tecnologia-de-vacinas-de-mrna&quot;&gt;2023: Tecnologia de Vacinas de mRNA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureados:&lt;/strong&gt; Katalin Karikó (Hungria/EUA), Drew Weissman (EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tema:&lt;/strong&gt; Descobertas que permitiram o desenvolvimento das vacinas de mRNA, fundamentais no combate à COVID-19 e abrindo novas possibilidades para vacinas e terapias.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karikó e Weissman enfrentaram anos de descrédito e falta de financiamento, mas sua persistência levou à modificação do mRNA para evitar resposta inflamatória, tornando possível o uso clínico. A tecnologia foi rapidamente aplicada nas vacinas contra COVID-19, batendo recorde de velocidade no desenvolvimento de uma vacina eficaz e salvando milhões de vidas. Hoje, a plataforma de mRNA está sendo testada para vacinas contra câncer, HIV e doenças autoimunes. Karikó e Weissman colaboraram diretamente, e suas trajetórias inspiram cientistas sobre a importância da resiliência e da colaboração internacional.
&lt;label for=&quot;mrna-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;mrna-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;mRNA (RNA mensageiro): tipo de RNA que carrega a informação genética do DNA até a maquinaria celular responsável pela produção de proteínas (ribossomos). O mRNA serve como molde para a síntese de proteínas, desempenhando papel central na expressão gênica.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/3e/Katalin_Karik%C3%B3_at_the_United_States_Embassy_Sweden%2C_2023_Nobel_Reception_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Katalin_Karik%C3%BÓ_at_the_United_States_Embassy_Sweden%2C_2023_Nobel_Reception_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Katalin Karikó&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Katalin Karikó. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katalin_Karik%C3%B3&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e2/Drew_Weissman%2C_2023_Nobel_Laureate_in_Medicine_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Drew_Weissman%2C_2023_Nobel_Laureate_in_Medicine_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drew Weissman&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Drew Weissman. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drew_Weissman&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2024-descoberta-do-microrna-e-regulação-gênica&quot;&gt;2024: Descoberta do microRNA e Regulação Gênica&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureados:&lt;/strong&gt; Victor Ambros (EUA), Gary Ruvkun (EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tema:&lt;/strong&gt; Descoberta dos microRNAs, pequenas moléculas de RNA que regulam a expressão gênica, com impacto profundo no desenvolvimento, doenças e terapias.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambros e Ruvkun, que trabalharam em paralelo e também colaboraram, mostraram que pequenos RNAs não codificantes controlam a expressão de genes em animais e humanos. O campo do microRNA explodiu, revelando seu papel em câncer, doenças cardíacas, neurodegenerativas e imunidade. A primeira terapia de interferência de RNA aprovada para uso clínico (patisiran, para amiloidose hereditária) é um exemplo direto do impacto dessas descobertas. Terapias baseadas em microRNA já estão em testes clínicos, e a descoberta mudou a visão sobre o chamado “DNA lixo”. Ambos os laureados têm histórico de colaboração com outros ganhadores do Nobel, como Robert Horvitz.
&lt;label for=&quot;dna&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;dna&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;DNA (ou ADN = ácido desoxiribonucléico): molécula orgânica
  complexa, o DNA é um polímero, uma cadeia formada da união de moléculas mais simples.
  Ele é formado de 4 tipos de moléculas: adenina, citosina, guanina e timina, as
  quais são &lt;em&gt;nucleotídeos&lt;/em&gt;, os monômeros (partes individuais que compõem, em conjunto,
  um polímero) do DNA. Cada molécula de DNA é formada pela união de duas longas
  fitas de nucleotídeos, que se enrolam em espiral. A posição dos nucleotídeos
  ao longo da fita de DNA não é casual, ela forma um código, chamado de &lt;em&gt;código
  genético&lt;/em&gt;, que armazena as informações necessárias para a produção de todas as
  proteínas de uma célula. Na verdade, o DNA contido em cada célula carrega as
  informações necessárias para reproduzir &lt;em&gt;todo&lt;/em&gt; o organismo.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/de/Victor_Ambros%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine.jpg/250px-Victor_Ambros%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Victor Ambros&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Victor Ambros. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victor_Ambros&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/24/Gary_Ruvkun%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine_3_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Gary_Ruvkun%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine_3_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gary Ruvkun&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Gary Ruvkun. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_Ruvkun&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;o-que-une-os-temas-e-os-laureados&quot;&gt;O que une os temas e os laureados?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foco molecular e genético:&lt;/strong&gt; Todos os prêmios destacam avanços em biologia molecular, genética e mecanismos fundamentais da saúde e doença.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impacto translacional:&lt;/strong&gt; Cada descoberta levou a novos diagnósticos, terapias ou mudanças fundamentais na ciência biomédica.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colaboração internacional:&lt;/strong&gt; Muitos laureados trabalharam em diferentes países e instituições, refletindo a natureza global da ciência atual.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diversidade de trajetórias:&lt;/strong&gt; Há imigrantes e trajetórias multiculturais (ex: Karikó da Hungria, Patapoutian do Líbano).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cientistas ativos:&lt;/strong&gt; Em junho de 2025, todos os laureados estão vivos e a maioria segue ativa na pesquisa ou na academia, exceto Michael Houghton, que se aposentou, mas está vivo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interrelações:&lt;/strong&gt; Vários laureados colaboraram entre si ou com outros ganhadores do Nobel, mostrando a importância das redes científicas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;controvérsias-e-curiosidades&quot;&gt;Controvérsias e Curiosidades&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020:&lt;/strong&gt; Houve debate sobre a exclusão de outros colaboradores na pesquisa da hepatite C, mas os principais descobridores foram reconhecidos.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021:&lt;/strong&gt; Sem grandes controvérsias; as descobertas foram amplamente aceitas e celebradas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2022:&lt;/strong&gt; Discussão sobre o foco em DNA antigo, mas o pioneirismo de Pääbo foi universalmente reconhecido.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2023:&lt;/strong&gt; O desenvolvimento rápido das vacinas de mRNA gerou debates públicos, mas o feito científico foi claro. A longa luta de Karikó por reconhecimento antes do Nobel foi muito comentada.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2024:&lt;/strong&gt; O campo do microRNA é vasto e outros cientistas contribuíram, mas Ambros e Ruvkun fizeram as descobertas fundamentais.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implicações-para-o-presente-e-o-futuro&quot;&gt;Implicações para o Presente e o Futuro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As tecnologias e descobertas premiadas já têm impacto profundo no presente:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hepatite C:&lt;/strong&gt; A doença está próxima de ser erradicada em vários países graças a testes e tratamentos derivados das descobertas de 2020.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/hepatitis-c&quot;&gt;Saiba mais: OMS - Hepatite C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vacinas de mRNA:&lt;/strong&gt; A plataforma de mRNA está sendo adaptada para vacinas contra câncer, HIV, gripe e doenças autoimunes, com ensaios clínicos em andamento. O recorde de velocidade no desenvolvimento da vacina contra COVID-19 mostrou o potencial dessa tecnologia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02483-w&quot;&gt;Nature - mRNA vaccines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MicroRNA e RNAi:&lt;/strong&gt; A primeira terapia de interferência de RNA aprovada para uso clínico foi o patisiran (Onpattro), para amiloidose hereditária por transtirretina, em 2018. Desde então, já existem seis terapias de interferência de RNA aprovadas pelo FDA, ampliando as possibilidades de tratamento para doenças genéticas e crônicas e podendo revolucionar a medicina personalizada.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/drugs/spotlight-cder-science/new-class-drugs-fulfills-promise-rna-based-medicine&quot;&gt;FDA - RNAi therapies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41573-024-00912-9&quot;&gt;Nature Reviews Drug Discovery - RNAi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genética evolutiva:&lt;/strong&gt; Genes herdados de neandertais, como o &lt;em&gt;F5&lt;/em&gt; (coagulação), &lt;em&gt;SCN9A&lt;/em&gt; (sensibilidade à dor) e variantes do cluster &lt;em&gt;OAS&lt;/em&gt; (imunidade antiviral), afetam características humanas atuais. Um gene de denisovanos, &lt;em&gt;EPAS1&lt;/em&gt;, aumenta a resistência à altitude em tibetanos. Esses achados ajudam a entender susceptibilidade a doenças e adaptações humanas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-020-2818-3&quot;&gt;Nature - Neanderthal DNA and COVID-19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/tibetans-inherited-high-altitude-gene-ancient-human&quot;&gt;Science - Denisovan gene and altitude&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Neurociência sensorial:&lt;/strong&gt; Novos analgésicos e tratamentos para dor crônica e doenças neurológicas estão sendo desenvolvidos com base nos receptores descobertos em 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/hot-and-cool-research-wins-nobel-prize-physiology-or-medicine&quot;&gt;Science - Pain research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No futuro, espera-se que essas descobertas continuem a transformar a medicina, tornando diagnósticos mais precisos, tratamentos mais personalizados e ampliando a compreensão dos mecanismos fundamentais da vida. O intercâmbio internacional, a colaboração multidisciplinar e a valorização da ciência básica mostraram ser essenciais para avanços que beneficiam toda a humanidade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusão&quot;&gt;Conclusão&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Os últimos cinco anos do Nobel de Medicina refletem uma era dourada da biologia molecular e genética, com descobertas de impacto imediato na saúde humana e que aprofundam nossa compreensão da vida. A pesquisa científica é fundamental para o bem-estar das pessoas e para o avanço da sociedade. No entanto, o crescimento do negacionismo científico e da desinformação preocupa, pois ameaça conquistas históricas e dificulta o acesso a tratamentos e vacinas. Por isso, é essencial valorizar e divulgar informação de qualidade, baseada em evidências, para que os benefícios da ciência cheguem a todos e para que a sociedade possa tomar decisões informadas sobre saúde e políticas públicas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/10/nobel-medicina-20-24.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/10/nobel-medicina-20-24.html</guid>
        
        <category>Fisiologia ou Medicina</category>
        
        <category>Nobel</category>
        
        <category>História da Ciência</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2024 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine: The Silent Revolution of MicroRNA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2024 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine was awarded to the American scientists &lt;strong&gt;Victor Ambros&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Gary Ruvkun&lt;/strong&gt;, for their discovery of microRNA (miRNA) and its fundamental role in post-transcriptional gene regulation. [1, 2]
  &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pioneering research of Ambros and Ruvkun revealed a new and sophisticated layer of genetic control, demonstrating that small RNA molecules, once considered irrelevant, play a crucial role in how and when genes are activated. [3] This discovery not only rewrote fundamental parts of molecular biology textbooks but also opened vast new avenues for understanding and treating complex diseases, such as cancer and heart disease. [4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all began in the 1980s, when both scientists, then postdoctoral fellows in the laboratory of H. Robert Horvitz (a 2002 Nobel laureate), were studying the development of the nematode worm &lt;em&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/em&gt;. [2] This simple organism, with its precisely mapped cellular development, was the perfect model for investigating the mysteries of gene regulation. [5] Working independently but focused on the same puzzle, they investigated how certain genes governed the worm’s larval stage transitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was in Victor Ambros’s laboratory that the first piece of the puzzle was found. In 1993, his team discovered that the &lt;em&gt;lin-4&lt;/em&gt; gene did not encode a protein, as was expected, but rather a small RNA molecule, approximately 22 nucleotides long. [6] This molecule bound to a specific region of the messenger RNA (mRNA) of another gene, &lt;em&gt;lin-14&lt;/em&gt;, preventing its translation into a protein. [7] This was an entirely new regulatory mechanism, termed post-transcriptional regulation. [1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simultaneously, Gary Ruvkun’s laboratory made a crucial complementary discovery. He confirmed the proposed mechanism of action, showing how the small &lt;em&gt;lin-4&lt;/em&gt; RNA effectively silenced the &lt;em&gt;lin-14&lt;/em&gt; mRNA. [7] Years later, in 2000, Ruvkun’s lab discovered another of these molecules, &lt;em&gt;let-7&lt;/em&gt;, and, surprisingly, demonstrated that it was evolutionarily conserved across numerous species, including humans. [8] This signaled that this was not a quirk of worms but a fundamental biological mechanism. [2, 3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discoveries of Ambros and Ruvkun revealed that portions of the genome once considered “junk” actually contained functional treasures. Today, we know that the human genome encodes over a thousand types of microRNAs. [2] These molecules are essential for development, metabolism, cell differentiation, and immune function. The malfunction of microRNAs is implicated in numerous pathologies, and the development of miRNA-based therapies is one of the most promising areas of modern medicine. [4, 9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2024 Nobel Prize recognizes a truly fundamental discovery that has drastically changed our understanding of how genetic information is orchestrated to create the complexity of life. [1] The work of Victor Ambros and Gary Ruvkun has opened a new universe in biology, the implications of which for human health are still being explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a7/MiRNA.svg/960px-MiRNA.svg.png?20190519102305&quot; alt=&quot;Figure: A schematic showing the formation and function of micro RNA. Credit: Kelvinsong, CC BY 3.0 &amp;lt;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0&amp;gt;, via Wikimedia Commons&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/2024/press-release/&quot;&gt;1 - The Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine 2024 - Press Release (NobelPrize.org)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/2024/advanced-information/&quot;&gt;2 - Scientific Background: Discoveries of microRNA (NobelPrize.org)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2024/oct/07/nobel-prize-in-medicine-awarded-to-scientists-for-work-on-microrna-victor-ambros-gary-ruvkun&quot;&gt;3 - Nobel prize in medicine awarded to scientists for work on microRNA - The Guardian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-03212-9&quot;&gt;4 - Medicine Nobel awarded for gene-regulating ‘microRNAs’ - Nature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statnews.com/2024/10/07/nobel-prize-medicine-ambros-ruvkun-awarded-prize/&quot;&gt;5 - 2024 Nobel prize in medicine: Ruvkun, Ambros win for discovery of microRNA - STAT News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(93)90529-y&quot;&gt;6 - Lee, R., Feinbaum, R. &amp;amp; Ambros, V. (1993). The &lt;em&gt;C. elegans&lt;/em&gt; heterochronic gene &lt;em&gt;lin-4&lt;/em&gt; encodes small RNAs with antisense complementarity to &lt;em&gt;lin-14&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Cell&lt;/em&gt;, 75(5), 843-854.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(93)90530-4&quot;&gt;7 - Wightman, B., Ha, I. &amp;amp; Ruvkun, G. (1993). Posttranscriptional regulation of the heterochronic gene &lt;em&gt;lin-14&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;em&gt;lin-4&lt;/em&gt; mediates temporal pattern formation in &lt;em&gt;C. elegans&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Cell&lt;/em&gt;, 75(5), 855-862.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/35040556&quot;&gt;8 - Pasquinelli, A. E., et al. (2000). Conservation of the sequence and temporal expression of &lt;em&gt;let-7&lt;/em&gt; heterochronic regulatory RNA. &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;, 408(6808), 86-89.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/nrd.2016.246&quot;&gt;9 - Rupaimoole, R., &amp;amp; Slack, F. J. (2017). MicroRNA therapeutics: towards a new era for the management of cancer and other diseases. &lt;em&gt;Nature Reviews Drug Discovery&lt;/em&gt;, 16(3), 203-222.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 20:22:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2024/10/07/nobel-medicine-24.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2024/10/07/nobel-medicine-24.html</guid>
        
        <category>Physiology or Medicine</category>
        
        <category>Nobel Prize</category>
        
        <category>Genetics</category>
        
        <category>microRNA</category>
        
        <category>Gene Regulation</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Prêmio Nobel de Fisiologia ou Medicina 2024: A Revolução Silenciosa do MicroRNA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;O Prêmio Nobel de Fisiologia ou Medicina de 2024 foi concedido aos cientistas americanos &lt;strong&gt;Victor Ambros&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;Gary Ruvkun&lt;/strong&gt;, por sua descoberta do microRNA (miRNA) e seu papel fundamental na regulação gênica pós-transcricional. [1, 2]
  &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As pesquisas pioneiras de Ambros e Ruvkun revelaram uma nova e sofisticada camada de controle genético, demonstrando que pequenas moléculas de RNA, antes consideradas irrelevantes, desempenham um papel crucial em como e quando os genes são ativados. [3] Essa descoberta não apenas reescreveu partes fundamentais dos manuais de biologia molecular, mas também abriu vastos novos caminhos para a compreensão e o tratamento de doenças complexas, como o câncer e as doenças cardíacas. [4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tudo começou na década de 1980, quando ambos os cientistas, então pós-doutorandos no laboratório de Robert Horvitz (laureado com o Nobel em 2002), estudavam o desenvolvimento do verme nematoide &lt;em&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/em&gt;. [2] Esse organismo simples, com seu desenvolvimento celular precisamente mapeado, era o modelo perfeito para investigar os mistérios da regulação genética. [5] Trabalhando de forma independente, mas com foco no mesmo enigma, eles investigavam como certos genes governavam as transições de estágio larval do verme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foi no laboratório de Victor Ambros que a primeira peça do quebra-cabeça foi encontrada. Em 1993, sua equipe descobriu que o gene &lt;em&gt;lin-4&lt;/em&gt; não codificava uma proteína, como se esperava, mas sim uma pequena molécula de RNA, com aproximadamente 22 nucleotídeos. [6] Essa molécula se ligava a uma região específica do RNA mensageiro (mRNA) de outro gene, o &lt;em&gt;lin-14&lt;/em&gt;, impedindo sua tradução em proteína. [7] Era um mecanismo de regulação inteiramente novo, denominado regulação pós-transcricional. [1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simultaneamente, o laboratório de Gary Ruvkun fez uma descoberta complementar crucial. Ele confirmou o mecanismo de ação proposto, mostrando como o pequeno RNA &lt;em&gt;lin-4&lt;/em&gt; efetivamente silenciava o mRNA de &lt;em&gt;lin-14&lt;/em&gt;. [7] Anos mais tarde, em 2000, o laboratório de Ruvkun descobriu outra dessas moléculas, o &lt;em&gt;let-7&lt;/em&gt;, e, de forma surpreendente, demonstrou que ela era conservada evolutivamente em inúmeras espécies, incluindo os seres humanos. [8] Isso sinalizou que não se tratava de uma peculiaridade dos vermes, mas de um mecanismo biológico fundamental. [2, 3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As descobertas de Ambros e Ruvkun revelaram que porções do genoma antes consideradas “lixo” continham, na verdade, tesouros funcionais. Hoje, sabemos que o genoma humano codifica mais de mil tipos de microRNAs. [2] Essas moléculas são essenciais para o desenvolvimento, o metabolismo, a diferenciação celular e a função imunológica. O mau funcionamento dos microRNAs está implicado em diversas patologias, e o desenvolvimento de terapias baseadas em miRNA é uma das áreas mais promissoras da medicina moderna. [4, 9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O Prêmio Nobel de 2024 reconhece uma descoberta verdadeiramente fundamental, que mudou drasticamente nossa compreensão de como a informação genética é orquestrada para criar a complexidade da vida. [1] O trabalho de Victor Ambros e Gary Ruvkun abriu um novo universo na biologia, cujas implicações para a saúde humana ainda estão sendo exploradas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a7/MiRNA.svg/960px-MiRNA.svg.png?20190519102305&quot; alt=&quot;Figure: Diagrama mostrando a formação e função do micro RNA. Credit: Kelvinsong, CC BY 3.0 &amp;lt;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0&amp;gt;, via Wikimedia Commons&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;referências&quot;&gt;Referências&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/2024/press-release/&quot;&gt;1 - The Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine 2024 - Press Release (NobelPrize.org)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/2024/advanced-information/&quot;&gt;2 - Scientific Background: Discoveries of microRNA (NobelPrize.org)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2024/oct/07/nobel-prize-in-medicine-awarded-to-scientists-for-work-on-microrna-victor-ambros-gary-ruvkun&quot;&gt;3 - Nobel prize in medicine awarded to scientists for work on microRNA - The Guardian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-03212-9&quot;&gt;4 - Medicine Nobel awarded for gene-regulating ‘microRNAs’ - Nature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statnews.com/2024/10/07/nobel-prize-medicine-ambros-ruvkun-awarded-prize/&quot;&gt;5 - 2024 Nobel prize in medicine: Ruvkun, Ambros win for discovery of microRNA - STAT News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(93)90529-y&quot;&gt;6 - Lee, R., Feinbaum, R. &amp;amp; Ambros, V. (1993). The &lt;em&gt;C. elegans&lt;/em&gt; heterochronic gene &lt;em&gt;lin-4&lt;/em&gt; encodes small RNAs with antisense complementarity to &lt;em&gt;lin-14&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Cell&lt;/em&gt;, 75(5), 843-854.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(93)90530-4&quot;&gt;7 - Wightman, B., Ha, I. &amp;amp; Ruvkun, G. (1993). Posttranscriptional regulation of the heterochronic gene &lt;em&gt;lin-14&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;em&gt;lin-4&lt;/em&gt; mediates temporal pattern formation in &lt;em&gt;C. elegans&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Cell&lt;/em&gt;, 75(5), 855-862.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/35040556&quot;&gt;8 - Pasquinelli, A. E., et al. (2000). Conservation of the sequence and temporal expression of &lt;em&gt;let-7&lt;/em&gt; heterochronic regulatory RNA. &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;, 408(6808), 86-89.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/nrd.2016.246&quot;&gt;9 - Rupaimoole, R., &amp;amp; Slack, F. J. (2017). MicroRNA therapeutics: towards a new era for the management of cancer and other diseases. &lt;em&gt;Nature Reviews Drug Discovery&lt;/em&gt;, 16(3), 203-222.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 20:22:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2024/10/07/nobel-medicina-24.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2024/10/07/nobel-medicina-24.html</guid>
        
        <category>Fisiologia ou Medicina</category>
        
        <category>Nobel</category>
        
        <category>Genética</category>
        
        <category>microRNA</category>
        
        <category>Regulação Gênica</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tempestades Geomagnéticas de Maio de 2024: Auroras Históricas</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Em maio de 2024, a Terra foi atingida por uma série de intensas tempestades geomagnéticas &lt;label for=&quot;geomag-tempestade-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;geomag-tempestade-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Tempestade Geomagnética:&lt;/strong&gt; Uma tempestade geomagnética é um distúrbio temporário no campo magnético da Terra causado por atividade solar, como CMEs ou erupções solares. Essas tempestades podem afetar tecnologias, navegação e gerar auroras longe dos polos.
&lt;/span&gt;
 desencadeadas por poderosas ejeções de massa coronal (CMEs) &lt;label for=&quot;geomag-cme-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;geomag-cme-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Ejeção de Massa Coronal (CME):&lt;/strong&gt; Uma CME é uma grande liberação de vento solar e campos magnéticos da coroa do Sol para o espaço. Quando direcionadas à Terra, as CMEs podem desencadear tempestades geomagnéticas, afetando satélites, redes elétricas e produzindo auroras em latitudes incomuns.
&lt;/span&gt;
 do Sol. Essas tempestades produziram auroras &lt;label for=&quot;geomag-aurora-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;geomag-aurora-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Aurora:&lt;/strong&gt; Aurora é um fenômeno luminoso natural observado no céu, geralmente em regiões de altas latitudes. Auroras são causadas por partículas solares carregadas interagindo com o campo magnético e a atmosfera da Terra, produzindo luzes coloridas.
&lt;/span&gt;
 visíveis em latitudes excepcionalmente baixas, incluindo partes dos Estados Unidos, Brasil, Europa e até &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arabiaweather.com/en/content/due-to-the-solar-storm-and-in-a-historical-precedent-the-northern-lights-were-seen-from-algeria-and-areas-on-the-equator&quot;&gt;Norte da África&lt;/a&gt;.   &lt;!--more--&gt;
O fenômeno foi amplamente documentado por observadores e cientistas, marcando um dos eventos de clima espacial mais significativos do século XXI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/4e/May_2024_Aurora_SC.jpg/960px-May_2024_Aurora_SC.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora em Pawleys Island, EUA, 11 de maio de 2024&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Aurora vista em Pawleys Island, Carolina do Sul, EUA (33°N GLAT, 43°N MLAT), 11 de maio de 2024. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_2024_solar_storms&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/9/99/Aurora_austral.jpg/960px-Aurora_austral.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora em Quillón, Chile, 11 de maio de 2024&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Aurora vista em Quillón, Chile (36°S GLAT, 24°S MLAT), 11 de maio de 2024. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_2024_solar_storms&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e2/Palm_Trees_and_Auroras_In_Mazatlan.jpg/960px-Palm_Trees_and_Auroras_In_Mazatlan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora em Mazatlán, México, 11 de maio de 2024&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Aurora vista em Mazatlán, México (23°N GLAT, 31°N MLAT), 11 de maio de 2024. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_2024_solar_storms&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ciencia-medica/assets/img/aurora-algeria-24.png&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora na Argélia, 11 de maio de 2024&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Aurora vista na Argélia, 11 de maio de 2024. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arabiaweather.com/en/content/due-to-the-solar-storm-and-in-a-historical-precedent-the-northern-lights-were-seen-from-algeria-and-areas-on-the-equator&quot;&gt;ArabiaWeather.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/9/91/Aurora_Australis_From_Melbourne.jpg/330px-Aurora_Australis_From_Melbourne.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora em Melbourne, Austrália, 11 de maio de 2024&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/7/78/Aurora_Borealis_from_Cwmbran%2C_Wales.png/330px-Aurora_Borealis_from_Cwmbran%2C_Wales.png&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora em Cwmbran, País de Gales, Reino Unido, 11 de maio de 2024&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aurora vista em Melbourne, Austrália (38°S GLAT, 48°S MLAT) e em Cwmbran, País de Gales, Reino Unido (51°N GLAT, 47°N MLAT), 11 de maio de 2024. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_2024_solar_storms&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;o-que-são-tempestades-geomagnéticas&quot;&gt;O que são tempestades geomagnéticas?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tempestades geomagnéticas são distúrbios no campo magnético da Terra causados por interações com partículas solares altamente energéticas, especialmente durante CMEs. Elas podem afetar comunicações, redes elétricas, satélites e até causar auroras em latitudes incomuns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparação-com-eventos-históricos&quot;&gt;Comparação com eventos históricos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As tempestades de maio de 2024 foram classificadas como G5 (extrema) pelo NOAA SWPC, com índices Kp &lt;label for=&quot;geomag-kp-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;geomag-kp-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Índice Kp:&lt;/strong&gt; O índice Kp é uma escala de 0 a 9 que mede a intensidade global da atividade geomagnética. Valores altos de Kp indicam tempestades mais fortes e maior chance de auroras em latitudes baixas.
&lt;/span&gt;
 chegando a 9. Para comparação:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evento Carrington (1859):&lt;/strong&gt; A maior tempestade geomagnética já registrada, causando falhas em telégrafos e auroras até o Caribe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tempestade de Quebec (1989):&lt;/strong&gt; Provocou apagão no Canadá e auroras em latitudes médias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tempestades de maio de 2024:&lt;/strong&gt; Auroras vistas até o sul do Brasil e Texas, com relatos de perturbações em redes elétricas e navegação.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Evento&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Ano&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Kp Máx&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Impacto Principal&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Carrington&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1859&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9+&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Falhas em telégrafos, auroras tropicais&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;New York Railroad&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1921&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Incêndios em ferrovias, falhas em comunicações&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Quebec&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1989&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Apagão, auroras em latitudes médias&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tempestades de Halloween&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2003&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Satélites, GPS, aviação afetados&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Maio de 2024&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2024&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Auroras em baixas latitudes, falhas elétricas&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tempestade de março&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1989&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Falhas em redes elétricas, auroras&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tempestade de maio&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1921&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Falhas em comunicações, incêndios&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tempestade de agosto&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1972&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8-9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Satélites, comunicações afetadas&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tempestade de julho&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1958&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Auroras em baixas latitudes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tempestade de setembro&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1941&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Falhas em comunicações, auroras&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;seção-histórica-os-eventos-carrington-e-quebec&quot;&gt;Seção Histórica: Os Eventos Carrington e Quebec&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;o-evento-carrington-1859&quot;&gt;O Evento Carrington (1859)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O Evento Carrington é considerado a tempestade geomagnética mais poderosa já registrada. Em 1º de setembro de 1859, o astrônomo britânico Richard Carrington observou e desenhou um grande grupo de manchas solares, seguido por um clarão brilhante — hoje conhecido como erupção solar &lt;label for=&quot;geomag-erupcao-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;geomag-erupcao-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Erupção Solar:&lt;/strong&gt; Uma erupção solar é um aumento súbito de brilho intenso na superfície do Sol, geralmente próximo a grupos de manchas solares. Erupções liberam grandes quantidades de energia e partículas no espaço, podendo causar tempestades geomagnéticas na Terra.
&lt;/span&gt;
. Foi a primeira vez que uma erupção solar foi diretamente associada a distúrbios geomagnéticos na Terra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/9/92/Carrington_Richard_drawing_of_1859_sunspots.jpeg/330px-Carrington_Richard_drawing_of_1859_sunspots.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Desenho das manchas solares por Carrington, 1º de setembro de 1859&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Desenho das manchas solares por Richard Carrington, 1859. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carrington_Event&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Em apenas 17 horas, uma ejeção de massa coronal (CME) atingiu a Terra, causando auroras visíveis até o Caribe e norte da América do Sul. Sistemas de telégrafo em toda a Europa e América do Norte falharam, com operadores recebendo choques elétricos e papéis pegando fogo. Alguns sistemas continuaram a operar mesmo desconectados da fonte de energia, alimentados por correntes induzidas geomagneticamente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sobre Richard Carrington:&lt;/strong&gt;
Richard Christopher Carrington (1826–1875) foi um astrônomo inglês pioneiro que fez contribuições significativas à física solar. Suas observações em 1859 forneceram a primeira evidência de uma conexão direta entre atividade solar e tempestades geomagnéticas na Terra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-tempestade-de-quebec-março-de-1989&quot;&gt;A Tempestade de Quebec (março de 1989)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tempestade geomagnética de Quebec ocorreu em 13 de março de 1989 e é um dos eventos de clima espacial mais significativos da era moderna. Desencadeada por uma poderosa CME, a tempestade causou um apagão de nove horas na província canadense de Quebec, deixando seis milhões de pessoas sem eletricidade. O evento também afetou satélites, comunicações de rádio e causou auroras até o Texas e a Flórida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/20/ExtremeEvent_19890310-00h_19890315-24h.jpg/960px-ExtremeEvent_19890310-00h_19890315-24h.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Apagão de Quebec, 13 de março de 1989&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;GOES-7 monitorando as condições do clima espacial durante a grande tempestade geomagnética de março de 1989. O monitor de nêutrons de Moscou registrou a passagem de uma CME como uma queda nos níveis conhecida como Forbush decrease. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/March_1989_geomagnetic_storm&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repercussões:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transformadores de redes elétricas foram danificados no Canadá e nos EUA.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Operações de satélites foram afetadas, e alguns saíram de controle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sistemas de rádio e navegação sofreram interrupções.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;O evento levou a grandes investimentos em monitoramento do clima espacial e proteção das redes elétricas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Datas envolvidas:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9 de março de 1989: Flare solar e CME observados.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;13 de março de 1989: Tempestade geomagnética e apagão em Quebec.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;e-se-um-evento-do-nível-carrington-ocorresse-hoje&quot;&gt;E se um evento do nível Carrington ocorresse hoje?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uma tempestade da magnitude de Carrington poderia causar apagões generalizados, danos a transformadores, falhas em satélites, GPS e comunicações, além de prejuízos econômicos trilionários. A sociedade moderna é muito mais dependente de eletricidade e tecnologia do que em 1859, tornando-nos mais vulneráveis a tais eventos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Qual a probabilidade de outro evento Carrington?&lt;/strong&gt;
Estudos estimam que tempestades desse porte tenham probabilidade de 1–2% por década (aproximadamente uma vez a cada 50–100 anos). Embora raros, o risco é suficiente para que governos e concessionárias invistam em monitoramento e estratégias de mitigação.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;monitoramento-do-clima-espacial-e-sua-importância&quot;&gt;Monitoramento do Clima Espacial e Sua Importância&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O monitoramento do clima espacial é crucial para proteger a infraestrutura tecnológica moderna dos efeitos das tempestades geomagnéticas. Diversas agências nacionais e internacionais operam sistemas de monitoramento e alerta:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOAA Space Weather Prediction Center (SWPC, EUA):&lt;/strong&gt; Principal agência dos EUA para previsão, monitoramento e alertas de clima espacial. Fornece dados em tempo real, avisos e recursos educativos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ESA Space Weather Office (Europa):&lt;/strong&gt; A Agência Espacial Europeia coordena o monitoramento e a pesquisa em clima espacial no continente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UK Met Office Space Weather Operations Centre (Reino Unido):&lt;/strong&gt; Fornece previsões e alertas para o Reino Unido e colabora internacionalmente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agência Meteorológica do Japão (JMA):&lt;/strong&gt; Monitora atividade solar e geomagnética no Leste Asiático.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outras agências:&lt;/strong&gt; Canadá, Rússia, China e Austrália também mantêm programas de clima espacial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essas agências compartilham dados e colaboram por meio do International Space Environment Service (ISES), uma rede global para troca de informações sobre clima espacial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;programas-de-alerta-de-clima-espacial&quot;&gt;Programas de Alerta de Clima Espacial&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A maioria das agências opera sistemas públicos de alerta que notificam concessionárias, operadores de satélites, companhias aéreas e o público sobre eventos de clima espacial em andamento ou previstos. Os alertas usam escalas padronizadas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Índice Kp:&lt;/strong&gt; Índice global de atividade geomagnética de 0 (muito calmo) a 9 (extremamente perturbado). Valores de Kp igual ou acima de 5 indicam tempestade geomagnética.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Escala G (NOAA):&lt;/strong&gt; O SWPC dos EUA usa a escala G para classificar tempestades geomagnéticas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Nível G&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Descrição&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Kp&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Efeitos típicos&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Menor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Flutuações fracas na rede elétrica, impacto menor em satélites, auroras em altas latitudes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Moderada&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Possíveis alarmes de tensão, danos em transformadores em altas latitudes, auroras em latitudes médias&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Forte&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Correções de tensão necessárias, alarmes falsos em dispositivos de proteção, auroras até o sul do Brasil/EUA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Severa&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Problemas generalizados de controle de tensão, possíveis danos a transformadores, auroras até o sul do Brasil/Europa&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Extrema&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Problemas generalizados na rede elétrica, possível colapso do sistema, auroras vistas em regiões tropicais&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essas escalas ajudam a comunicar a gravidade e os possíveis impactos das tempestades geomagnéticas para tomadores de decisão e o público.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fontes-e-leituras-adicionais&quot;&gt;Fontes e leituras adicionais&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_2024_solar_storms&quot;&gt;Wikipedia: Tempestades geomagnéticas de maio de 2024&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://satlib.cira.colostate.edu/event/extreme-geomagnetic-storm/&quot;&gt;NOAA SWPC - Tempestade geomagnética extrema&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swpc.noaa.gov/noaa-scales-explanation&quot;&gt;NOAA SWPC - Escalas de Clima Espacial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusão&quot;&gt;Conclusão&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As tempestades geomagnéticas de maio de 2024 serão lembradas como um dos maiores espetáculos naturais do século, ressaltando a importância do monitoramento do clima espacial e da preparação para seus impactos em nossa sociedade tecnológica.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2024/05/15/tempestades-geomagneticas-2024.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2024/05/15/tempestades-geomagneticas-2024.html</guid>
        
        <category>Geomagnetismo</category>
        
        <category>Aurora</category>
        
        <category>Espaço</category>
        
        <category>História da Ciência</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>May 2024 Geomagnetic Storms: Historic Auroras</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In May 2024, Earth was struck by a series of intense geomagnetic storms &lt;label for=&quot;geomag-storm&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;geomag-storm&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Geomagnetic Storm:&lt;/strong&gt; A geomagnetic storm is a temporary disturbance of Earth’s magnetic field caused by solar activity, such as CMEs or solar flares. These storms can disrupt technology, navigation, and create auroras far from the poles.
&lt;/span&gt;
 triggered by powerful coronal mass ejections (CMEs) &lt;label for=&quot;geomag-cme&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;geomag-cme&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Coronal Mass Ejection (CME):&lt;/strong&gt; A CME is a massive burst of solar wind and magnetic fields released from the Sun’s corona into space. When directed toward Earth, CMEs can trigger geomagnetic storms, affecting satellites, power grids, and producing auroras at unusual latitudes.
&lt;/span&gt;
 from the Sun. These storms produced auroras &lt;label for=&quot;geomag-aurora&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;geomag-aurora&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Aurora:&lt;/strong&gt; An aurora is a natural light display in Earth’s sky, usually seen in high-latitude regions. Auroras are caused by charged solar particles interacting with Earth’s magnetic field and atmosphere, producing colorful lights.
&lt;/span&gt;
 visible at exceptionally low latitudes, including parts of the United States, Brazil, Europe, and even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arabiaweather.com/en/content/due-to-the-solar-storm-and-in-a-historical-precedent-the-northern-lights-were-seen-from-algeria-and-areas-on-the-equator&quot;&gt;North Africa&lt;/a&gt;.   &lt;!--more--&gt;
The phenomenon was widely documented by observers and scientists, marking one of the most significant space weather events of the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/4e/May_2024_Aurora_SC.jpg/960px-May_2024_Aurora_SC.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora in Pawleys Island, USA, May 11, 2024&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Aurora seen in Pawleys Island, South Carolina, U.S. (33°N GLAT, 43°N MLAT) May 11, 2024. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_2024_solar_storms&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/9/99/Aurora_austral.jpg/960px-Aurora_austral.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora in Quillon, Chile, May 11, 2024&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Aurora seen in Quillón, Chile (36°S GLAT, 24°S MLAT), May 11, 2024. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_2024_solar_storms&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e2/Palm_Trees_and_Auroras_In_Mazatlan.jpg/960px-Palm_Trees_and_Auroras_In_Mazatlan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora in Mazatlán, Mexico, May 11, 2024&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Aurora seen in Mazatlán, Mexico (23°N GLAT, 31°N MLAT), May 11, 2024. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_2024_solar_storms&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ciencia-medica/assets/img/aurora-algeria-24.png&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora in Algeria, May 11, 2024&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Aurora seen in Algeria, May 11, 2024. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arabiaweather.com/en/content/due-to-the-solar-storm-and-in-a-historical-precedent-the-northern-lights-were-seen-from-algeria-and-areas-on-the-equator&quot;&gt;ArabiaWeather.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/9/91/Aurora_Australis_From_Melbourne.jpg/330px-Aurora_Australis_From_Melbourne.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora in Melbourne, Australia, May 11, 2024&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/7/78/Aurora_Borealis_from_Cwmbran%2C_Wales.png/330px-Aurora_Borealis_from_Cwmbran%2C_Wales.png&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora in Cwmbran, Wales, U.K., May 11, 2024&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aurora seen Melbourne, Australia (38°S GLAT, 48°S MLAT), and in Cwmbran, Wales, U.K. (51°N GLAT, 47°N MLAT), May 11, 2024. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_2024_solar_storms&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-geomagnetic-storms&quot;&gt;What are geomagnetic storms?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geomagnetic storms are disturbances in Earth’s magnetic field caused by interactions with highly energetic solar particles, especially during CMEs. They can disrupt communications, power grids, satellites, and even cause auroras at unusual latitudes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparison-with-historic-events&quot;&gt;Comparison with historic events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The May 2024 storms were classified as G5 (extreme) by NOAA SWPC, with Kp &lt;label for=&quot;geomag-kp&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;geomag-kp&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Kp Index:&lt;/strong&gt; The Kp index is a scale from 0 to 9 that measures the global intensity of geomagnetic activity. Higher Kp values mean stronger geomagnetic storms and a greater chance of seeing auroras at lower latitudes.
&lt;/span&gt;
 indices reaching 9. For comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Carrington Event (1859):&lt;/strong&gt; The largest geomagnetic storm ever recorded, causing telegraph failures and auroras as far south as the Caribbean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quebec Storm (1989):&lt;/strong&gt; Caused a blackout in Canada and auroras at mid-latitudes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 2024 Storms:&lt;/strong&gt; Auroras seen as far south as southern Brazil and Texas, with reports of power grid and navigation disruptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Event&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Max Kp&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Main Impact&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Carrington&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1859&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9+&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Telegraph failures, tropical auroras&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;New York Railroad&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1921&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Railroad fires, telegraph/telephone outages&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Quebec&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1989&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Blackout, mid-latitude auroras&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Halloween Storms&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2003&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Satellite, GPS, aviation disruptions&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;May 2024&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2024&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Low-latitude auroras, power disruptions&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;March Storm&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1989&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Power grid failures, auroras&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;May Storm&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1921&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Telegraph/telephone outages, fires&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;August Storm&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1972&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8-9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Satellite, communication disruptions&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;July Storm&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1958&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Auroras at low latitudes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;September Storm&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1941&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Telegraph/telephone outages, auroras&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;historical-section-the-carrington-and-quebec-events&quot;&gt;Historical Section: The Carrington and Quebec Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-carrington-event-1859&quot;&gt;The Carrington Event (1859)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Carrington Event is considered the most powerful geomagnetic storm ever recorded. On September 1, 1859, British astronomer Richard Carrington observed and drew a massive group of sunspots, followed by a sudden bright flash—now known as a solar flare &lt;label for=&quot;geomag-flare&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;geomag-flare&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Solar Flare:&lt;/strong&gt; A solar flare is a sudden flash of increased brightness on the Sun, usually near sunspot groups. Flares release large amounts of energy and particles into space, sometimes leading to geomagnetic storms on Earth.
&lt;/span&gt;
. This was the first time a solar flare was directly linked to geomagnetic disturbances on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/9/92/Carrington_Richard_drawing_of_1859_sunspots.jpeg/330px-Carrington_Richard_drawing_of_1859_sunspots.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Carrington&apos;s sunspot drawing, September 1, 1859&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Richard Carrington’s drawing of the sunspots, 1859. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carrington_Event&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within 17 hours, a coronal mass ejection (CME) reached Earth, causing auroras visible as far south as the Caribbean and northern South America. Telegraph systems across Europe and North America failed, with some operators receiving electric shocks and telegraph paper catching fire. Some systems continued to operate even when disconnected from their power supplies, powered by geomagnetically induced currents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Richard Carrington:&lt;/strong&gt;
Richard Christopher Carrington (1826–1875) was a pioneering English astronomer who made significant contributions to solar physics. His observations in 1859 provided the first evidence of a direct connection between solar activity and geomagnetic storms on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-quebec-storm-march-1989&quot;&gt;The Quebec Storm (March 1989)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Quebec geomagnetic storm occurred on March 13, 1989, and is one of the most significant space weather events of the modern era. Triggered by a powerful CME, the storm caused a nine-hour blackout in the Canadian province of Quebec, leaving six million people without electricity. The event also disrupted satellites, radio communications, and caused auroras as far south as Texas and Florida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/20/ExtremeEvent_19890310-00h_19890315-24h.jpg/960px-ExtremeEvent_19890310-00h_19890315-24h.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Quebec blackout, March 13, 1989&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;GOES-7 monitors the space weather conditions during the Great Geomagnetic storm of March 1989, the Moscow neutron monitor recorded the passage of a CME as a drop in levels known as a Forbush decrease. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/March_1989_geomagnetic_storm&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repercussions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Power grid transformers were damaged in Canada and the US.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Satellite operations were disrupted, and some satellites tumbled out of control.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shortwave radio and navigation systems experienced outages.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The event led to major investments in space weather monitoring and grid protection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dates involved:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;March 9, 1989: Solar flare and CME observed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;March 13, 1989: Geomagnetic storm and blackout in Quebec.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-if-a-carrington-level-event-happened-today&quot;&gt;What if a Carrington-level event happened today?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A storm of Carrington magnitude could cause widespread blackouts, damage to transformers, satellite failures, GPS and communication disruptions, and economic losses in the trillions of dollars. Modern society is far more dependent on electricity and technology than in 1859, making us more vulnerable to such events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How likely is another Carrington event?&lt;/strong&gt;
Studies estimate that Carrington-class storms have a probability of about 1–2% per decade (roughly once every 50–100 years). While rare, the risk is significant enough that governments and utilities are investing in monitoring and mitigation strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;space-weather-monitoring-and-its-importance&quot;&gt;Space Weather Monitoring and Its Importance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Space weather monitoring is crucial for protecting modern technological infrastructure from the effects of geomagnetic storms. Several national and international agencies operate space weather monitoring and alert systems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOAA Space Weather Prediction Center (SWPC, USA):&lt;/strong&gt; The leading U.S. agency for space weather forecasting, monitoring, and alerts. Provides real-time data, warnings, and educational resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ESA Space Weather Office (Europe):&lt;/strong&gt; The European Space Agency coordinates space weather monitoring and research across Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UK Met Office Space Weather Operations Centre (UK):&lt;/strong&gt; Provides forecasts and alerts for the UK and collaborates internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Japan Meteorological Agency (JMA):&lt;/strong&gt; Monitors solar and geomagnetic activity in East Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other agencies:&lt;/strong&gt; Canada, Russia, China, and Australia also maintain space weather programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These agencies share data and collaborate through the International Space Environment Service (ISES), a global network for space weather information exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;space-weather-alert-programs&quot;&gt;Space Weather Alert Programs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most agencies operate public alert systems that notify utilities, satellite operators, airlines, and the public about ongoing or expected space weather events. Alerts are issued using standardized scales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kp Index:&lt;/strong&gt; A global geomagnetic activity index ranging from 0 (very quiet) to 9 (extremely disturbed). Kp values of 5 or higher indicate geomagnetic storm conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;G Scale (NOAA):&lt;/strong&gt; The NOAA SWPC uses the G scale to classify geomagnetic storms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;G Level&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Kp Index&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Typical Effects&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Minor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Weak power grid fluctuations, minor satellite impact, auroras at high latitudes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Moderate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Possible voltage alarms, transformer damage at high latitudes, auroras at mid-latitudes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Strong&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Voltage corrections required, false alarms on some protection devices, auroras as far south as Illinois/Oregon (US)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Severe&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Widespread voltage control problems, possible transformer damage, auroras as far south as Alabama (US)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Extreme&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Widespread power system problems, grid collapse possible, auroras seen in Texas/Florida (US)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These scales help communicate the severity and potential impacts of geomagnetic storms to decision-makers and the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources-and-further-reading&quot;&gt;Sources and further reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_2024_solar_storms&quot;&gt;Wikipedia: May 2024 geomagnetic storms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://satlib.cira.colostate.edu/event/extreme-geomagnetic-storm/&quot;&gt;NOAA SWPC - Extreme geomagnetic storm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swpc.noaa.gov/noaa-scales-explanation&quot;&gt;NOAA SWPC - Space Weather Scales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The geomagnetic storms of May 2024 will be remembered as one of the greatest natural spectacles of the century, highlighting the importance of space weather monitoring and preparedness for its impacts on our technological society.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2024/05/15/geomagnetic-storms-2024.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2024/05/15/geomagnetic-storms-2024.html</guid>
        
        <category>Geomagnetism</category>
        
        <category>Aurora</category>
        
        <category>Space</category>
        
        <category>Science History</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2023 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine: The mRNA Revolution with Karikó and Weissman</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2023 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine was awarded to &lt;strong&gt;Katalin Karikó&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Drew Weissman&lt;/strong&gt;, for their groundbreaking discoveries that led to the development of mRNA vaccines against COVID-19.
  &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karikó and Weissman, working independently but with a common goal, dedicated their careers to unraveling the potential of messenger RNA (mRNA) as a tool for human health. mRNA, the molecule that carries the genetic instructions for protein production, was seen as a promising pathway for developing new therapies, but it faced significant obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main challenge was the inflammatory response of the immune system to mRNA, which prevented its clinical application. Karikó, in her work at the University of Pennsylvania, spent years researching to understand and overcome this barrier. She discovered that a specific chemical modification to mRNA, replacing uridine with pseudouridine, could reduce the inflammatory response and increase the molecule’s stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Drew Weissman, also at the University of Pennsylvania, was conducting research on the role of TLR7, an immune receptor that recognizes mRNA and triggers the inflammatory response. His studies revealed that the chemical modification discovered by Karikó did, in fact, reduce TLR7 activation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collaboration between Karikó and Weissman proved crucial in validating and developing this discovery, paving the way for the creation of safe and effective mRNA vaccines. This technology proved fundamental in the fight against the COVID-19 pandemic, with mRNA vaccines being developed in record time and saving millions of lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karikó and Weissman’s discoveries are not limited to the pandemic. mRNA technology has become one of the most promising areas of medical research, with the potential to treat a variety of diseases, including cancer, rare diseases, and infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2023 Nobel Prize recognizes the profound influence of Karikó and Weissman’s work, which has transformed modern medicine and opened doors to a future of innovation and hope in the field of health.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 20:22:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2023/10/03/nobel-medicine-23.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2023/10/03/nobel-medicine-23.html</guid>
        
        <category>Physiology or Medicine</category>
        
        <category>Nobel Prize</category>
        
        <category>mRNA Vaccine</category>
        
        <category>COVID-19</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
