<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ciência médica</title>
    <description>Blog sobre ciência médica, pesquisa científica, oncologia pediátrica, farmacologia e outras ciências da saúde afins. Continuação do blog publicado em https://pharmakon.blogspot.com
</description>
    <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 21:00:51 -0300</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 21:00:51 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title></title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-problem-with-p-values-how-significant-are-they-really&quot;&gt;The problem with p values: how significant are they, really?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/profiles/geoff-cumming-4100&quot;&gt;Geoff Cumming&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;La Trobe University&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For researchers there’s a lot that turns on the &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value, the number used to determine whether a result is statistically significant. The current consensus is that if &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is less than .05, a study has reached the holy grail of being statistically significant, and therefore likely to be published. Over .05 and it’s usually back to the drawing board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But today, Texas A&amp;amp;M University professor &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stat.tamu.edu/directory-details.php?directoryid=321&quot;&gt;Valen Johnson&lt;/a&gt;, writing in the prestigious journal Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.1313476110&quot;&gt;argues&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; less than .05 is far too weak a standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using .05 is, he contends, a key reason why false claims are published and many published results fail to replicate. He advocates requiring .005 or even .001 as the criterion for statistical significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-p-value-anyway&quot;&gt;What is a &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value anyway?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value is at the heart of the most common approach to data analysis – null hypothesis significance testing (NHST). Think of NHST as a waltz with three steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;State a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.null-hypothesis.co.uk/science/item/what_is_a_null_hypothesis/&quot;&gt;null hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;: that is, there is no effect.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Calculate the &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value, which is the probability of getting results like ours – &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; the null hypothesis is true.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is sufficiently small, reject the null hypothesis and sound the trumpets: our effect is not zero, it’s statistically significant!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British statistician and geneticist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronald_Fisher&quot;&gt;Sir Ronald Fisher&lt;/a&gt; introduced &lt;a href=&quot;https://psychclassics.yorku.ca/Fisher/Methods/index.htm&quot;&gt;the &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value&lt;/a&gt; in 1925. He adopted .05 as a reference point for rejecting a null hypothesis. For him it was not a sharp cutoff: a thoughtful researcher should consider the context, and other results as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHST has, however, become deeply entrenched in medicine and numerous other disciplines. The precise value .05 has become a bar to wriggle under to achieve publication in top journals. Generations of students have been inducted into the rituals of .05 meaning “significant”, and .01 “highly significant”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sounds-good-whats-the-problem&quot;&gt;Sounds good. What’s the problem?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble is there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apastyle.org/manual/related/kline-2004.pdf&quot;&gt;numerous deep flaws&lt;/a&gt; in NHST.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://tiny.cc/nhstohdear&quot;&gt;evidence&lt;/a&gt; that students, researchers and even many teachers of statistics don’t understand NHST properly. More worryingly, there’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/neuro/journal/v14/n9/full/nn.2886.html&quot;&gt;evidence&lt;/a&gt; it’s widely misused, even in top journals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most researchers don’t appreciate that &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is highly unreliable. Repeat your experiment and you’ll get a &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value that could be extremely different. Even more surprisingly, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is highly unreliable even for &lt;a href=&quot;https://tiny.cc/pintervals&quot;&gt;very large samples&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHST may be a waltz, but the dance of &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is highly frenetic. Here’s a demonstration of why we simply shouldn’t trust any &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5OL1RqHrZQ8&quot;&gt;YouTube: Why p-values are unreliable&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all those problems, NHST persists, perhaps because we yearn for certainty. Declaring a result “significant” suggests certainty, even though our results almost always contain considerable uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;should-we-require-stronger-evidence&quot;&gt;Should we require stronger evidence?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Johnson makes a cogent argument that .05 provides only weak evidence against the null hypothesis: perhaps only odds of 3 or 4 to 1 against reasonable alternative hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He suggests we should require more persuasive odds, say 50 to 1 or even 200 to 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, we need to adopt .005 or .001 as our &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; value criterion for statistical significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He recognises there’s a price to pay for demanding stronger evidence. In typical cases, we’d need to roughly double our sample sizes to still have a reasonable chance of finding true effects. Using larger samples would indeed be highly desirable, but sometimes that’s simply not possible. And are research grants about to double?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Johnson is correct that .05 corresponds to weak evidence, and .005 or .001 to evidence that’s usefully stronger. Adopting his stricter criterion would, however, mean that the majority of all published research analysed using NHST would fail the new test, and suddenly be statistically non-significant!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c479107.ssl.cf2.rackcdn.com/files/34853/width237/kzzxq98g-1384132459.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;shutupyourface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More fundamentally, merely shifting the criterion does not overcome the unreliability of &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, or most of the other deep flaws of NHST. The core problem is that NHST panders to our yearning for certainty by presenting the world as black or white — an effect is statistically significant or not; it exists or it doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact our world is many shades of grey — I won’t pretend to know how many. We need something more nuanced than NHST, and fortunately there are good alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-better-way-estimation-and-meta-analysis&quot;&gt;A better way: estimation and meta-analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiana.edu/~kruschke/DoingBayesianDataAnalysis/&quot;&gt;Bayesian techniques&lt;/a&gt; are highly promising and becoming widely used. Most readily available and already widely used is estimation based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://tiny.cc/GeoffConversation&quot;&gt;confidence intervals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A confidence interval gives us the best estimate of the true effect, and also indicates the extent of uncertainty in our results. Confidence intervals are also what we need to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://tiny.cc/GeoffConversation&quot;&gt;meta-analysis&lt;/a&gt;, which allows us to integrate results from a number of experiments that investigate the same issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often need to make clear decisions — whether or not to licence the new drug, for example — but NHST provides a poor basis for such decisions. It’s far better to use the integration of all available evidence to guide decisions, and estimation and meta-analysis provides that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merely shifting the NHST goal posts simply won’t do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Further reading:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/give-p-a-chance-significance-testing-is-misunderstood-20207&quot;&gt;Give p a chance: significance testing is misunderstood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Geoff Cumming has received funding from the Australian Research Council.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article was originally published at &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com&quot;&gt;The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;. Read the &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/the-problem-with-p-values-how-significant-are-they-really-20029&quot;&gt;original article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postagem original em Pharmakon &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;aqui&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 21:00:51 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/21/2013-11-19-the-problem-with-p-values-how.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/21/2013-11-19-the-problem-with-p-values-how.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Merchant, the Portal, and Time Loops: Science and Fiction in Ted Chiang</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In his award-winning short story “The Merchant and the Alchemist’s Gate,” Ted Chiang weaves a fascinating narrative around a real scientific concept: closed timelike curves.&lt;label for=&quot;closed-timelike-curve&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;closed-timelike-curve&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Closed timelike curve:&lt;/strong&gt; A trajectory in spacetime that returns to the same point, theoretically allowing time travel without violating general relativity.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Inspired by a lecture from physicist Kip Thorne, Chiang explores the idea of trajectories in spacetime that return to the same point—meaning, mathematically possible time travel.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/e/e3/The_Merchant_and_the_Alchemist%27s_Gate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cover of the original edition of &amp;quot;The Merchant and the Alchemist&apos;s Gate&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cover of the original edition of “The Merchant and the Alchemist’s Gate”. Image by Subterranean Press, published on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:The_Merchant_and_the_Alchemist%27s_Gate.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; under Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported license.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we get lost in paradoxes and portals, it’s worth asking: what is time, after all? Long before time became a theme in Western philosophy, Hindus wrote in the Vedas about cycles of creation and destruction lasting more than 4 million years each. The Egyptian Ptahotep said that wasting time was an abomination (perhaps already anticipating Novikov? - see below). The Incas saw space and time as one: pacha. And probably the ancient speakers of Proto-Semitic already had the concept of remote time and an origin of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Aristotle, time was not an independent entity, but the measure of change—time exists only because things change. Newton, on the other hand, saw time (and space) as absolutes, a fixed stage where everything happens, regardless of what exists or changes. Then Einstein brought the big surprise: time can “stretch” or “shrink” depending on speed and gravity, becoming relative to the observer.&lt;label for=&quot;relativity&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;relativity&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Relativity:&lt;/strong&gt; The physical theory developed by Einstein that revolutionized our understanding of space, time, and gravity, showing they are relative to the observer.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Other philosophers also gave their interpretations, but none changed our understanding as much as modern physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what are these curves, after all? Technically, they are “closed worldlines of a Lorentzian manifold in spacetime.”&lt;label for=&quot;closed-timelike-curve&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;closed-timelike-curve&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Closed timelike curve:&lt;/strong&gt; A trajectory in spacetime that returns to the same point, theoretically allowing time travel without violating general relativity.
&lt;/span&gt;
 In simpler terms: they are trajectories that allow an object to return to the same point in space and time. The first mathematical solution for this concept was found by Willem Jacob van Stockum in 1937, and later confirmed by Kurt Gödel in 1949, both using Einstein’s field equations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before time travel was seriously considered, Karl Schwarzschild—adventurer, mountaineer, and physicist—found the first exact solution to Einstein’s equations during World War I.&lt;label for=&quot;wormhole-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;wormhole-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Wormhole:&lt;/strong&gt; A theoretical solution to Einstein’s equations connecting two distinct points in spacetime, acting as a cosmic shortcut.
&lt;/span&gt;
 His work paved the way for the concept of wormholes, which would later be considered possible mechanisms for closed timelike curves. If anyone had to be a time traveler, it would be him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the concepts that most fascinated Chiang was Novikov’s self-consistency principle. But who was Novikov? Igor Dmitriyevich Novikov is a Russian astrophysicist and cosmologist, known for his contributions to black hole physics, cosmology, and especially to the study of time travel.&lt;label for=&quot;novikov-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;novikov-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Novikov self-consistency principle:&lt;/strong&gt; States that events causing time paradoxes have zero probability of occurring, making the universe “self-consistent”.
&lt;/span&gt;
 He formulated the self-consistency principle, which states that the probability of worldlines causing time paradoxes is zero. In other words, the universe “adjusts itself” to prevent paradoxes, making them impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1990s, Thorne and other physicists found mathematical solutions suggesting the existence of infinite closed timelike curves that avoid paradoxes.&lt;label for=&quot;time-paradox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;time-paradox&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time paradox:&lt;/strong&gt; A hypothetical situation in which an action in the past changes the future in a contradictory way, such as preventing one’s own birth.
&lt;/span&gt;
 This could be used in traversable wormholes—true “windows” to the past or future, but always in worldlines where paradoxes cannot occur. The result would be similar to Chiang’s description in his story, something quite different from the wormhole in Carl Sagan’s book Contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chiang is a master at building stories around singular scientific concepts, always in a romanticized fantasy setting. “The Merchant and the Alchemist’s Gate” won the Nebula and Hugo awards in 2008, showing how great science fiction can arise from mathematically possible ideas that remain mysterious to most of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ted Chiang is an American science fiction writer, known for his stories that explore deep scientific and philosophical concepts. His most popular work is the short story “Story of Your Life,” which was adapted into the acclaimed film “Arrival” (2016), directed by Denis Villeneuve. Chiang has received several major awards in speculative fiction, including the Nebula, Hugo, and Locus awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.: The concepts discussed in this post also apply to other works of fiction in different media, such as the Netflix series “Dark” and the anime “Steins;Gate”—each of which deserves its own dedicated post in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/20/chiang-merchant-portal-en.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/20/chiang-merchant-portal-en.html</guid>
        
        <category>Science fiction</category>
        
        <category>Time travel</category>
        
        <category>Relativity</category>
        
        <category>Wormhole</category>
        
        <category>Ted Chiang</category>
        
        <category>Kip Thorne</category>
        
        <category>Gödel</category>
        
        <category>Novikov</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>O mercador, o portal e as curvas do tempo: ciência e ficção em Ted Chiang</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ted Chiang, em seu premiado conto “O Mercador e o Portal do Alquimista”, constrói uma narrativa fascinante ao redor de um conceito científico real: as curvas fechadas do tipo tempo.&lt;label for=&quot;curva-fechada-tempo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;curva-fechada-tempo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Curva fechada do tipo tempo:&lt;/strong&gt; Trajetória no espaço-tempo que retorna ao mesmo ponto, permitindo, em teoria, viagens no tempo sem violar as equações da relatividade geral.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Inspirado por uma palestra do físico Kip Thorne, Chiang explora a ideia de trajetórias no espaço-tempo que retornam ao mesmo ponto — ou seja, viagens no tempo matematicamente possíveis.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/e/e3/The_Merchant_and_the_Alchemist%27s_Gate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Capa da edição original de &amp;quot;The Merchant and the Alchemist&apos;s Gate&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Capa da edição original de “The Merchant and the Alchemist’s Gate”. Imagem de Subterranean Press, publicada na &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:The_Merchant_and_the_Alchemist%27s_Gate.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; sob licença Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antes de nos perdermos nos paradoxos e portais, vale perguntar: afinal, o que é o tempo? Muito antes de o tempo ser tema da filosofia ocidental, os hindus já escreviam nos Vedas sobre ciclos de criação e destruição que duravam mais de 4 milhões de anos cada. O egípcio Ptahotep dizia que a perda de tempo era uma abominação (talvez já antecipando Novikov? - veja adiante). Os Incas viam espaço e tempo como uma coisa só: &lt;em&gt;pacha&lt;/em&gt;. E, provavelmente, os antigos falantes do proto-semítico já tinham o conceito de tempo remoto e de uma origem do tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para Aristóteles, o tempo não era uma entidade independente, mas a medida da mudança — só existe tempo porque as coisas mudam. Newton, por outro lado, via o tempo (e o espaço) como absolutos, um palco fixo onde tudo acontece, independentemente do que existe ou muda. Já Einstein trouxe a grande surpresa: o tempo pode “esticar” ou “encolher” dependendo da velocidade e da gravidade, tornando-se relativo ao observador.&lt;label for=&quot;relatividade&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;relatividade&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Relatividade:&lt;/strong&gt; Teoria física desenvolvida por Einstein que revolucionou a compreensão do espaço, tempo e gravidade, mostrando que são relativos ao observador.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Outros filósofos também deram suas interpretações, mas nenhuma delas mudou tanto nossa compreensão quanto a física moderna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mas afinal o que são as tais curvas? Em termos técnicos, são “linhas do universo fechadas de um distribuidor Lorentziano no espaço-tempo”.&lt;label for=&quot;curva-fechada-tempo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;curva-fechada-tempo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Curva fechada do tipo tempo:&lt;/strong&gt; Trajetória no espaço-tempo que retorna ao mesmo ponto, permitindo, em teoria, viagens no tempo sem violar as equações da relatividade geral.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Traduzindo: são trajetórias que permitem a um objeto voltar ao mesmo ponto no espaço e no tempo. A primeira solução matemática para esse conceito foi encontrada por Willem Jacob van Stockum em 1937, e depois confirmada por Kurt Gödel em 1949, ambos usando as equações de campo de Einstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antes mesmo de se falar em viagens no tempo, Karl Schwarzschild — aventureiro, alpinista e físico — encontrou a primeira solução exata das equações de Einstein durante a Primeira Guerra Mundial.&lt;label for=&quot;wormhole&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;wormhole&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Buraco de minhoca:&lt;/strong&gt; Solução teórica das equações de Einstein que conecta dois pontos distintos do espaço-tempo, funcionando como um atalho cósmico.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Sua solução abriu caminho para o conceito de buracos de minhoca, que mais tarde seriam considerados possíveis mecanismos para curvas fechadas do tempo. Se alguém tivesse que ser um viajante do tempo, seria ele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Um dos conceitos que mais fascinaram Chiang foi o princípio de autoconsistência de Novikov (um astrofísico e cosmólogo russo, conhecido por suas contribuições à física dos buracos negros, à cosmologia e, especialmente, ao estudo das viagens no tempo).&lt;label for=&quot;novikov&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;novikov&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Princípio de autoconsistência de Novikov:&lt;/strong&gt; Postula que eventos que causariam paradoxos temporais têm probabilidade zero de ocorrer, tornando o universo “autoconsistente”.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Esse princípio postula que a probabilidade de linhas do universo que causam paradoxos temporais é zero. Ou seja, o universo “se ajusta” para impedir paradoxos, tornando-os impossíveis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nos anos 90, Thorne e outros físicos encontraram soluções matemáticas que sugerem a existência de infinitas curvas fechadas do tempo que evitam paradoxos.&lt;label for=&quot;paradoxo-temporal&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;paradoxo-temporal&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Paradoxo temporal:&lt;/strong&gt; Situação hipotética em que uma ação no passado altera o futuro de forma contraditória, como impedir o próprio nascimento.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Isso poderia ser usado em buracos de minhoca atravessáveis — verdadeiras “janelas” para o passado ou futuro, mas sempre em linhas do universo onde paradoxos não podem ocorrer. O resultado seria semelhante à descrição de Chiang em seu conto, algo bem diferente do buraco de minhoca do livro Contato, de Carl Sagan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chiang é mestre em criar contos ao redor de conceitos científicos singulares, sempre em cenários de fantasia romanceada. “O Mercador e o Portal do Alquimista” ganhou os prêmios Nebula e Hugo em 2008, mostrando como a boa ficção científica pode nascer de ideias matematicamente possíveis, mas ainda misteriosas para a maioria de nós.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ted Chiang é um escritor norte-americano de ficção científica, conhecido por suas histórias que exploram conceitos científicos e filosóficos profundos. Sua obra mais popular é o conto “Story of Your Life” (“A História da Sua Vida”), que foi adaptado para o cinema no premiado filme “A Chegada” (“Arrival”, 2016), dirigido por Denis Villeneuve. Chiang já recebeu diversos prêmios importantes da literatura fantástica, incluindo o Nebula, o Hugo e o Locus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.: Os conceitos discutidos nesta postagem também se aplicam a outras obras de ficção em diferentes mídias, como a série da Netflix “Dark” e o anime “Steins;Gate” — cada uma delas merece, no futuro, uma postagem própria.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/20/chiang-mercador-portal-pt.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/20/chiang-mercador-portal-pt.html</guid>
        
        <category>Ficção científica</category>
        
        <category>Viagem no tempo</category>
        
        <category>Relatividade</category>
        
        <category>Buraco de minhoca</category>
        
        <category>Ted Chiang</category>
        
        <category>Kip Thorne</category>
        
        <category>Gödel</category>
        
        <category>Novikov</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>O lobo terrível não voltou: o que realmente significa o anúncio da &quot;desextinção&quot; e por que o futuro é mais importante que o passado</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Em abril de 2025, manchetes ao redor do mundo anunciaram a suposta “desextinção” do lobo terrível (dire wolf), espécie extinta há milhares de anos, após divulgação de um preprint e comunicado da empresa Colossal Biosciences.&lt;label for=&quot;desextincao&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;desextincao&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Desextinção:&lt;/strong&gt; Conceito que se refere à tentativa de recriar ou restaurar espécies extintas por meio de técnicas biotecnológicas, como clonagem, edição genética ou cruzamentos seletivos. Até hoje, nenhum caso de desextinção plena foi comprovado cientificamente.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Mas, afinal, o que realmente aconteceu? A resposta é mais complexa e interessante do que o sensacionalismo sugere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/92/Canis_dirus_Sergiodlarosa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reconstrução artística do lobo terrível (Canis dirus)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Reconstrução artística do lobo terrível (Canis dirus). Ilustração de Sergiodlarosa, publicada sob licença Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Canis_dirus_Sergiodlarosa.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;label for=&quot;lobo-terrivel&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;lobo-terrivel&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Lobo terrível (Canis dirus):&lt;/strong&gt; Espécie de lobo pré-histórico que viveu nas Américas durante o Pleistoceno e se extinguiu há cerca de 10 mil anos. Era maior e mais robusto que os lobos modernos.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;o-que-foi-feito-e-o-que-não-foi&quot;&gt;O que foi feito (e o que não foi)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Colossal Biosciences utilizou material genético de lobos cinzentos modernos, não de cães. Um dos  grandes avanços metodológicos nesse caso foi o uso de clonagem a partir de células progenitoras endoteliais, que normalmente existem em quantidade diminuta no revestimento interno dos vasos sanguíneos. Diferente das técnicas tradicionais de clonagem, que dependem de amostras de tecido obtidas por biópsia (e podem ser contaminadas por células diferenciadas), essa abordagem requer apenas uma amostra de sangue e a separação específica dessas células progenitoras — algo que até pouco tempo parecia ficção científica, como no filme ‘O Sexto Dia’. &lt;label for=&quot;clonagem&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;clonagem&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Clonagem:&lt;/strong&gt; Técnica de reprodução assexuada que gera um organismo geneticamente idêntico ao original. Pode ser feita por transferência nuclear, como no caso da ovelha Dolly, ou por outros métodos laboratoriais.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O DNA dos lobos cinzentos foi então editado geneticamente usando uma técnica com a enzima CRISPR-Cas9, permitindo a modificação de 20 posições de nucleotídeos do material genético original. Essas 20 alterações foram suficientes para dar aos animais gerados a aparência do lobo terrível. No entanto, os lobos terríveis originais tinham milhões de pares de bases diferentes dos lobos cinzentos modernos — ou seja, a modificação é superficial e limitada. &lt;label for=&quot;crispr&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;crispr&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;CRISPR:&lt;/strong&gt; Ferramenta de edição genética baseada em um sistema natural de defesa bacteriana, que permite modificar o DNA de organismos de forma precisa, rápida e relativamente barata. Revolucionou a biotecnologia e a medicina.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Após a edição genética, o núcleo dessas células modificadas foi transferido para óvulos de lobo cujo núcleo havia sido removido, etapa semelhante à técnica clássica de clonagem utilizada no caso da famosa ovelha Dolly. Assim, os embriões resultantes continham o material genético editado e puderam ser implantados para o desenvolvimento dos filhotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Os embriões de lobo cinzento geneticamente modificados foram implantados em cadelas, que gestaram e deram à luz três filhotes. Portanto, não são lobos terríveis, mas sim lobos cinzentos modificados para parecerem lobos terríveis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A polêmica aumentou em maio de 2025, quando a própria cientista-chefe da Colossal admitiu publicamente que os animais criados não são lobos terríveis e que nunca houve, de fato, uma desextinção. Essa admissão, amplamente repercutida na mídia, reforçou o caráter midiático do anúncio e evidenciou a importância de uma comunicação científica precisa e transparente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cientistas e veículos como a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/dire-wolf-back-dead-not-exactly&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; e a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/portuguese/articles/c62973qwx4do&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt; foram claros: não existe desextinção real, nem evidências de que lobos terríveis estejam de volta. O anúncio foi, em grande parte, um golpe de mídia, como apontou também a &lt;a href=&quot;https://jornal.usp.br/radio-usp/nao-existem-evidencias-cientificas-da-recuperacao-dos-lobos-terriveis-extintos-ha-milhares-de-anos/&quot;&gt;Universidade de São Paulo - USP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;o-verdadeiro-marco-crispr-e-o-futuro&quot;&gt;O verdadeiro marco: CRISPR e o futuro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apesar do exagero midiático, o trabalho representa um avanço notável na aplicação da edição genética em mamíferos, especialmente usando CRISPR para inserir modificações genéticas semelhantes aquelas de espécies extintas em genomas modernos. Isso abre portas para pesquisas em biotecnologia, saúde animal e humana, e até para a conservação de espécies ameaçadas — mas não para “ressuscitar” o passado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O impacto prático imediato para a ecologia ou proteção de espécies é nulo. Não há benefícios para o meio ambiente, nem para a biodiversidade, neste momento. O que há, de fato, é um salto tecnológico que pode, no futuro, revolucionar a medicina, tornando possível criar animais (e talvez humanos) resistentes a doenças, ou com características otimizadas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;o-debate-ético-e-o-futuro-disruptivo&quot;&gt;O debate ético e o futuro disruptivo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O aspecto mais relevante — e pouco discutido — é o potencial da edição genética para criar seres vivos com características inéditas. O “lobo terrível” é só um símbolo: o verdadeiro dilema está em como a sociedade lidará com a possibilidade de modificar profundamente seres humanos e animais. A tecnologia CRISPR pode, em médio e longo prazo, transformar a saúde, mas também traz desafios éticos enormes. &lt;label for=&quot;bioetica&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;bioetica&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Bioética:&lt;/strong&gt; Campo interdisciplinar que discute os limites éticos, sociais e legais das intervenções biomédicas, como clonagem, edição genética e desextinção. Fundamental para orientar decisões responsáveis na ciência.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusão&quot;&gt;Conclusão&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A notícia da “desextinção” do lobo terrível é, na verdade, um marco para o futuro, não para o passado. O mais importante não é o que foi recuperado, mas o que poderá ser criado. O debate sobre os limites e usos da edição genética está só começando.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fontes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.04.09.647074v1.full.pdf&quot;&gt;Preprint científico&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/dire-wolf-back-dead-not-exactly&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/portuguese/articles/c62973qwx4do&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jornal.usp.br/radio-usp/nao-existem-evidencias-cientificas-da-recuperacao-dos-lobos-terriveis-extintos-ha-milhares-de-anos/&quot;&gt;Universidade de São Paulo - USP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://colossal.com/direwolf/&quot;&gt;Colossal Biosciences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://colossal.com/direwolf/science/&quot;&gt;Colossal - Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/7274542/colossal-dire-wolf/&quot;&gt;Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/18/direwolf-2025.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/18/direwolf-2025.html</guid>
        
        <category>Desextinção</category>
        
        <category>CRISPR</category>
        
        <category>Edição genética</category>
        
        <category>Lobo terrível</category>
        
        <category>Bioética</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The dire wolf is not back: what the &quot;de-extinction&quot; announcement really means and why the future matters more than the past</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In April 2025, headlines around the world announced the supposed “de-extinction” of the dire wolf, a species extinct for thousands of years, following the release of a preprint and a statement from Colossal Biosciences.&lt;label for=&quot;deextinction&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;deextinction&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;De-extinction:&lt;/strong&gt; The concept of attempting to recreate or restore extinct species using biotechnological techniques such as cloning, genetic editing, or selective breeding. To date, no full de-extinction has been scientifically achieved.
&lt;/span&gt;
 But what really happened? The answer is more complex and interesting than the hype suggests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/92/Canis_dirus_Sergiodlarosa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Artistic reconstruction of the dire wolf (Canis dirus)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Artistic reconstruction of the dire wolf (Canis dirus). Illustration by Sergiodlarosa, published under Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported license. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Canis_dirus_Sergiodlarosa.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;label for=&quot;dire-wolf&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;dire-wolf&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Dire wolf (Canis dirus):&lt;/strong&gt; A prehistoric wolf species that lived in the Americas during the Pleistocene and went extinct about 10,000 years ago. It was larger and more robust than modern wolves.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-was-and-wasnt-done&quot;&gt;What was (and wasn’t) done&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colossal Biosciences used genetic material from modern gray wolves, not dogs. One of the major methodological advances was the use of cloning from endothelial progenitor cells, which are normally found in very small quantities in the inner lining of blood vessels. Unlike traditional cloning techniques, which rely on tissue samples obtained by biopsy (and can be contaminated by differentiated cells), this approach requires only a blood sample and the specific separation of these progenitor cells—something that until recently seemed like science fiction, as in the movie ‘The 6th Day.’ &lt;label for=&quot;cloning&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;cloning&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cloning:&lt;/strong&gt; An asexual reproduction technique that generates a genetically identical organism to the original. It can be done by nuclear transfer, as in the case of Dolly the sheep, or by other laboratory methods.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DNA of the gray wolves was then genetically edited using a CRISPR-Cas9 based technique, allowing for the modification of 20 DNA nucleotide positions in the original genetic material. These 20 changes were enough to give the resulting animals the appearance of a dire wolf. However, the original dire wolves had millions of base pairs different from modern gray wolves—so the modification is superficial and limited. &lt;label for=&quot;crispr-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;crispr-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;CRISPR:&lt;/strong&gt; A genetic editing tool based on a natural bacterial defense system, allowing precise, fast, and relatively inexpensive modification of DNA in organisms. It has revolutionized biotechnology and medicine.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the genetic editing, the nuclei of these modified cells were transferred into gray wolf eggs whose nuclei had been removed, a step similar to the classic cloning technique used in the famous Dolly the sheep. The resulting embryos, containing the edited genetic material, could then be implanted for development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genetically modified gray wolf embryos were implanted into domestic dogs, which gestated and gave birth to three pups. Therefore, these are not dire wolves, but gray wolves modified to look like dire wolves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The controversy increased in May 2025, when Colossal’s chief scientist publicly admitted that the animals created are not dire wolves and that there was, in fact, no de-extinction. This admission, widely reported in the media, reinforced the media-driven nature of the announcement and highlighted the importance of precise and transparent scientific communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists and outlets such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/dire-wolf-back-dead-not-exactly&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/portuguese/articles/c62973qwx4do&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt; were clear: there is no real de-extinction, nor evidence that dire wolves are back. The announcement was, for the most part, a media stunt, as also pointed out by &lt;a href=&quot;https://jornal.usp.br/radio-usp/nao-existem-evidencias-cientificas-da-recuperacao-dos-lobos-terriveis-extintos-ha-milhares-de-anos/&quot;&gt;Universidade de São Paulo - USP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-real-milestone-crispr-and-the-future&quot;&gt;The real milestone: CRISPR and the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the media exaggeration, the work represents a remarkable advance in the application of genetic editing in mammals, especially using CRISPR to insert genetic modifications similar to extinct species into modern genomes. This opens doors for research in biotechnology, animal and human health, and even for the conservation of endangered species—but not for “resurrecting” the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The immediate practical impact for ecology or species protection is zero. There are no benefits for the environment or biodiversity at this time. What we do have is a technological leap that could, in the future, revolutionize medicine, making it possible to create animals (and perhaps humans) resistant to diseases or with optimized traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-ethical-debate-and-a-disruptive-future&quot;&gt;The ethical debate and a disruptive future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most relevant—and underdiscussed—aspect is the potential of genetic editing to create living beings with unprecedented characteristics. The “dire wolf” is just a symbol: the real dilemma is how society will deal with the possibility of profoundly modifying humans and animals. CRISPR technology could, in the medium and long term, transform health, but it also brings enormous ethical challenges. &lt;label for=&quot;bioethics&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;bioethics&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Bioethics:&lt;/strong&gt; An interdisciplinary field that discusses the ethical, social, and legal boundaries of biomedical interventions such as cloning, genetic editing, and de-extinction. Essential for guiding responsible decisions in science.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The news of the dire wolf’s “de-extinction” is, in fact, a milestone for the future, not the past. The most important thing is not what was recovered, but what could be created. The debate about the limits and uses of genetic editing is just beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.04.09.647074v1.full.pdf&quot;&gt;Scientific preprint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/dire-wolf-back-dead-not-exactly&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/portuguese/articles/c62973qwx4do&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jornal.usp.br/radio-usp/nao-existem-evidencias-cientificas-da-recuperacao-dos-lobos-terriveis-extintos-ha-milhares-de-anos/&quot;&gt;Universidade de São Paulo - USP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://colossal.com/direwolf/&quot;&gt;Colossal Biosciences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://colossal.com/direwolf/science/&quot;&gt;Colossal - Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/7274542/colossal-dire-wolf/&quot;&gt;Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/18/direwolf-2025-en.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/18/direwolf-2025-en.html</guid>
        
        <category>De-extinction</category>
        
        <category>CRISPR</category>
        
        <category>Genetic editing</category>
        
        <category>Dire wolf</category>
        
        <category>Bioethics</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fibromyalgia, chronic pain and the role of the gut microbiome: new findings from 2025</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A study published in &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032&quot;&gt;Neuron&lt;/a&gt; in 2025 and discussed on the TWIM (This Week in Microbiology) podcast on May 27th brought new evidence about the relationship between the gut microbiome and chronic pain in fibromyalgia. The work shows that changes in gut bacteria may not only be associated with, but also directly contribute to, pain and other symptoms of the disease.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction-what-is-fibromyalgia-and-why-does-the-microbiome-matter&quot;&gt;Introduction: What is fibromyalgia and why does the microbiome matter?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fibromyalgia is a common syndrome, marked by widespread pain, fatigue, sleep disturbances, and cognitive difficulties, mainly affecting women. It is estimated that fibromyalgia affects about 2% to 4% of the world population, being more prevalent in women between 30 and 60 years old. In Brazil, this represents millions of people living with chronic pain and a significant impact on quality of life, productivity, and healthcare costs. &lt;label for=&quot;fibromyalgia-epid-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;fibromyalgia-epid-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Fibromyalgia epidemiology:&lt;/strong&gt; Fibromyalgia affects about 2% to 4% of the world population, being more common in women. In Brazil, millions of people are estimated to live with the syndrome, which is one of the main causes of chronic pain and disability.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Despite its high prevalence, the causes of fibromyalgia are still poorly understood and available treatments are often unsatisfactory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does the microbiome matter for health?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gut microbiome is the set of trillions of microorganisms (mainly bacteria) that live in our digestive tract. It acts as a true “biochemical factory,” helping digest food, produce vitamins, regulate the immune system, and protect against infectious agents. In addition, the microbiome communicates with the brain through chemical substances and the enteric nervous system, influencing mood, metabolism, and even pain perception. Changes in the balance of these bacteria (dysbiosis) have been associated with several diseases, including metabolic, autoimmune, psychiatric disorders, and chronic pain conditions such as fibromyalgia. &lt;label for=&quot;microbiome-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;microbiome-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Gut microbiome:&lt;/strong&gt; The gut microbiome is the set of trillions of microorganisms that inhabit the human gastrointestinal tract. The microbiome influences digestion, immunity, metabolism, and even the functioning of the nervous system.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent studies suggest that the gut microbiome can influence the functioning of the nervous and immune systems, even affecting pain perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;methods-how-was-the-study-conducted&quot;&gt;Methods: How was the study conducted?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The researchers transplanted the microbiome (gut bacteria) from women with fibromyalgia into germ-free mice, comparing with transplants from healthy individuals. They also conducted a small open clinical study, in which women with fibromyalgia received microbiota transplants from healthy donors after antibiotic and bowel preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;main-results&quot;&gt;Main results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In mice:&lt;/strong&gt; Transplanting microbiota from fibromyalgia patients induced persistent pain, immune system changes, metabolic alterations, and reduced skin innervation—all phenomena similar to those observed in human patients. The mice showed increased sensitivity to mechanical, thermal (heat and cold), and spontaneous pain, without motor or cognitive changes. The study also showed that the patients’ microbiota led to changes in immune cells, activation of microglia in the spinal cord (cells involved in chronic pain), and changes in metabolites such as bile acids and neuroactive amino acids. &lt;label for=&quot;microglia-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;microglia-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Microglia:&lt;/strong&gt; Microglia are cells of the central nervous system that act as “defenders” of the brain and spinal cord. When chronically activated, they can contribute to persistent pain and inflammation.
&lt;/span&gt;
 When the mice later received microbiota from healthy people, the pain was reversed and part of the metabolic and immune changes returned to normal, suggesting a causal role of the microbiome in chronic pain in fibromyalgia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reversal:&lt;/strong&gt; When the mice subsequently received healthy microbiota, the pain was relieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.cell.com/cms/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032/asset/c4101b78-70b3-4e9b-84f1-25c59bce8c12/main.assets/gr5_lrg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 5 from the article&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 5 from the article: Graphs show that mice receiving microbiota from fibromyalgia patients had greater sensitivity to pain (mechanical, thermal, and spontaneous), and that subsequent transplantation of healthy microbiota reversed this, normalizing pain thresholds. Source: Cai W et al., Neuron, 2025.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the clinical study:&lt;/strong&gt; Women with severe, treatment-resistant fibromyalgia showed significant pain reduction and improved quality of life after receiving healthy microbiota transplants. The open clinical study involved 14 women, who received capsules of microbiota from healthy donors after bowel preparation. There was an average drop of 2 points on the pain scale (NRS), improvement in global disease impact (FIQ), reduction in anxiety and depression, better sleep, and improved physical quality of life. Sensory tests showed increased cold pain threshold and a trend toward improvement in heat pain. The metabolic profile and microbiome composition also changed, becoming more similar to the donors’. Adverse effects were mild and transient, mainly fatigue and mild gastrointestinal symptoms. &lt;label for=&quot;fmt-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;fmt-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Fecal Microbiota Transplantation (FMT):&lt;/strong&gt; A procedure in which gut bacteria from a healthy donor are transferred to the intestine of a patient, aiming to restore the balance of the microbiome. It is already used to treat &lt;em&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/em&gt; infections and is under study for other conditions.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.cell.com/cms/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032/asset/86701a65-abed-49f6-9c26-9a92e9d705fc/main.assets/gr6_lrg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 6 from the article&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 6 from the article: Graphs show that after healthy microbiota transplantation, women with fibromyalgia had significant reduction in pain intensity, improvement in global disease impact, anxiety, depression, sleep quality, and physical quality of life. The graphs also show changes in cold and heat pain thresholds. Source: Cai W et al., Neuron, 2025.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;significance-for-the-field-and-for-patients&quot;&gt;Significance for the field and for patients&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study provides evidence that the gut microbiome is not just a “bystander” in fibromyalgia, but may be one of the factors causing or perpetuating chronic pain. This opens the way for new therapeutic approaches, such as microbiota transplantation or the use of specific probiotics, and reinforces the importance of research on the relationship between the gut, immune system, and brain. &lt;label for=&quot;probiotic-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;probiotic-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Probiotics:&lt;/strong&gt; These are live microorganisms that, when administered in adequate amounts, confer health benefits. They can modulate the gut microbiome and are being studied as a complementary therapy in chronic diseases.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the promising results, it is important to remember that the clinical study was small and open-label (without a control group), and more research is needed before microbiota transplantation can be routinely recommended. Still, the work represents an important advance in understanding fibromyalgia and may inspire new strategies to treat chronic pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is TWiM?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TWiM (This Week in Microbiology) is a podcast created by virologist Vincent Racaniello, from Columbia University (USA), in 2010. The program discusses weekly advances and curiosities in microbiology, focusing on recent scientific articles and topics relevant to health and science. The regular members include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vincent Racaniello (Columbia University, USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Petra Levin (Washington University in St. Louis, USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michele Swanson (University of Michigan, USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Schmidt (Medical University of South Carolina, USA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All are recognized scientists in their fields. TWiM is part of the MicrobeTV network and is available for free at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microbe.tv/twim/&quot;&gt;microbe.tv/twim&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032&quot;&gt;Original article in Neuron&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microbe.tv/twim/twim-332/&quot;&gt;TWIM 332: Fibromyalgia pain and the gut microbiome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/12/fibromyalgia-microbiome-2025.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/12/fibromyalgia-microbiome-2025.html</guid>
        
        <category>Fibromyalgia</category>
        
        <category>Microbiome</category>
        
        <category>Chronic pain</category>
        
        <category>Clinical research</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fibromialgia, dor crônica e o papel do microbioma intestinal: novos achados de 2025</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Um estudo publicado na revista &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032&quot;&gt;Neuron&lt;/a&gt; em 2025 e discutido no podcast TWIM (This Week in Microbiology) de 27 de maio trouxe novas evidências sobre a relação entre o microbioma intestinal e a dor crônica na fibromialgia. O trabalho mostra que alterações nas bactérias intestinais podem não só estar associadas, mas também contribuir diretamente para a dor e outros sintomas da doença.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introdução-o-que-é-fibromialgia-e-por-que-o-microbioma-importa&quot;&gt;Introdução: O que é fibromialgia e por que o microbioma importa?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fibromialgia é uma síndrome comum, marcada por dor generalizada, fadiga, distúrbios do sono e dificuldades cognitivas, afetando principalmente mulheres. Estima-se que a fibromialgia atinja cerca de 2% a 4% da população mundial, sendo mais prevalente em mulheres entre 30 e 60 anos. No Brasil, isso representa milhões de pessoas convivendo com dor crônica e impacto significativo na qualidade de vida, produtividade e custos de saúde. &lt;label for=&quot;fibromialgia-epid&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;fibromialgia-epid&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Epidemiologia da fibromialgia:&lt;/strong&gt; A fibromialgia afeta cerca de 2% a 4% da população mundial, sendo mais comum em mulheres. No Brasil, estima-se que milhões de pessoas convivam com a síndrome, que é uma das principais causas de dor crônica e incapacidade.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Apesar de sua alta prevalência, as causas da fibromialgia ainda são pouco compreendidas e os tratamentos disponíveis costumam ser insatisfatórios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Por que o microbioma importa para a saúde?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O microbioma intestinal é o conjunto de trilhões de microrganismos (principalmente bactérias) que vivem no nosso trato digestivo. Ele atua como uma verdadeira “fábrica bioquímica”, ajudando na digestão de alimentos, produção de vitaminas, regulação do sistema imunológico e proteção contra agentes infecciosos. Além disso, o microbioma se comunica com o cérebro por meio de substâncias químicas e do sistema nervoso entérico, influenciando o humor, o metabolismo e até a percepção da dor. Alterações no equilíbrio dessas bactérias (disbiose) têm sido associadas a diversas doenças, incluindo distúrbios metabólicos, autoimunes, psiquiátricos e condições de dor crônica como a fibromialgia. &lt;label for=&quot;microbioma&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;microbioma&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Microbioma intestinal:&lt;/strong&gt; É o conjunto de trilhões de microrganismos que habitam o trato gastrointestinal humano. O microbioma influencia digestão, imunidade, metabolismo e até o funcionamento do sistema nervoso.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estudos recentes sugerem que o microbioma intestinal pode influenciar o funcionamento do sistema nervoso e do sistema imunológico, afetando inclusive a percepção da dor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;metodologia-como-o-estudo-foi-feito&quot;&gt;Metodologia: Como o estudo foi feito?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Os pesquisadores transplantaram o microbioma (bactérias intestinais) de mulheres com fibromialgia para camundongos criados em ambiente estéril (germ-free), comparando com transplantes de pessoas saudáveis. Também realizaram um pequeno estudo clínico aberto, em que mulheres com fibromialgia receberam transplante de microbiota de doadoras saudáveis, após preparo com antibióticos e limpeza intestinal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resultados-principais&quot;&gt;Resultados principais&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Em camundongos:&lt;/strong&gt; O transplante de microbiota de pacientes com fibromialgia induziu dor persistente, alterações no sistema imunológico, mudanças no metabolismo e redução da inervação da pele — todos fenômenos semelhantes aos observados em pacientes humanos. Os camundongos apresentaram maior sensibilidade à dor mecânica, térmica (calor e frio) e espontânea, sem alterações motoras ou cognitivas. O estudo também mostrou que a microbiota de pacientes levou a alterações em células do sistema imune, ativação de microglia na medula espinhal (células envolvidas na dor crônica) e mudanças em metabólitos como ácidos biliares e aminoácidos neuroativos. &lt;label for=&quot;microglia&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;microglia&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Microglia:&lt;/strong&gt; São células do sistema nervoso central que atuam como “defensoras” do cérebro e da medula espinhal. Quando ativadas de forma crônica, podem contribuir para a dor persistente e inflamação.
&lt;/span&gt;
 Quando os camundongos receberam, posteriormente, microbiota de pessoas saudáveis, a dor foi revertida e parte das alterações metabólicas e imunes voltou ao normal, sugerindo um papel causal do microbioma na dor crônica da fibromialgia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reversão do quadro:&lt;/strong&gt; Quando os camundongos receberam, posteriormente, microbiota de pessoas saudáveis, a dor foi aliviada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.cell.com/cms/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032/asset/c4101b78-70b3-4e9b-84f1-25c59bce8c12/main.assets/gr5_lrg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figura 5 do artigo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figura 5 do artigo: Gráficos mostram que camundongos que receberam microbiota de pacientes com fibromialgia apresentaram maior sensibilidade à dor (mecânica, térmica e espontânea), e que o transplante subsequente de microbiota saudável reverteu esse quadro, normalizando os limiares de dor. Fonte: Cai W et al., Neuron, 2025.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No estudo clínico:&lt;/strong&gt; Mulheres com fibromialgia grave e resistente a tratamentos apresentaram redução significativa da dor e melhora da qualidade de vida após receberem transplante de microbiota saudável. O estudo clínico aberto envolveu 14 mulheres, que receberam cápsulas de microbiota de doadoras saudáveis após preparo intestinal. Houve queda média de 2 pontos na escala de dor (NRS), melhora do impacto global da doença (FIQ), redução de ansiedade e depressão, melhora do sono e da qualidade de vida física. Testes sensoriais mostraram aumento do limiar de dor ao frio e tendência de melhora ao calor. O perfil metabólico e a composição do microbioma também mudaram, aproximando-se do perfil das doadoras. Os efeitos adversos foram leves e transitórios, principalmente fadiga e sintomas gastrointestinais leves. &lt;label for=&quot;fmt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;fmt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Transplante de Microbiota Fecal (FMT):&lt;/strong&gt; Procedimento em que bactérias intestinais de um doador saudável são transferidas para o intestino de um paciente, visando restaurar o equilíbrio do microbioma. Já é usado para tratar infecções por &lt;em&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/em&gt; e está em estudo para outras condições.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.cell.com/cms/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032/asset/86701a65-abed-49f6-9c26-9a92e9d705fc/main.assets/gr6_lrg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figura 6 do artigo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figura 6 do artigo: Gráficos mostram que, após o transplante de microbiota saudável, mulheres com fibromialgia apresentaram redução significativa da intensidade da dor, melhora do impacto global da doença, ansiedade, depressão, qualidade do sono e qualidade de vida física. Os gráficos também mostram a mudança no limiar de dor ao frio e calor. Fonte: Cai W et al., Neuron, 2025.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;significado-para-o-campo-e-para-os-pacientes&quot;&gt;Significado para o campo e para os pacientes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O estudo fornece evidências de que o microbioma intestinal não é apenas um “espectador” na fibromialgia, mas pode ser um dos fatores que causam ou perpetuam a dor crônica. Isso abre caminho para novas abordagens terapêuticas, como o transplante de microbiota ou o uso de probióticos específicos, além de reforçar a importância de pesquisas sobre a relação entre intestino, sistema imunológico e cérebro. &lt;label for=&quot;probiotico&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;probiotico&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Probióticos:&lt;/strong&gt; São microrganismos vivos que, quando administrados em quantidades adequadas, conferem benefícios à saúde. Podem modular o microbioma intestinal e estão sendo estudados como terapia complementar em doenças crônicas.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apesar dos resultados promissores, é importante lembrar que o estudo clínico foi pequeno e aberto (sem grupo controle), e mais pesquisas são necessárias antes que o transplante de microbiota possa ser recomendado rotineiramente. Ainda assim, o trabalho representa um avanço importante na compreensão da fibromialgia e pode inspirar novas estratégias para tratar a dor crônica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;O que é o TWiM?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O TWiM (This Week in Microbiology) é um podcast criado pelo virologista Vincent Racaniello, da Universidade Columbia (EUA), em 2010. O programa discute semanalmente avanços e curiosidades em microbiologia, com foco em artigos científicos recentes e temas relevantes para a saúde e a ciência. Os integrantes regulares incluem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vincent Racaniello (Universidade Columbia, EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Petra Levin (Universidade Washington em St. Louis, EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michele Swanson (Universidade de Michigan, EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Schmidt (Universidade Médica da Carolina do Sul, EUA).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todos são cientistas reconhecidos em suas áreas. O TWiM faz parte da rede MicrobeTV e está disponível gratuitamente em &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microbe.tv/twim/&quot;&gt;microbe.tv/twim&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Referências:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.03.032&quot;&gt;Artigo original na Neuron&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microbe.tv/twim/twim-332/&quot;&gt;TWIM 332: Fibromyalgia pain and the gut microbiome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/12/fibromialgia-microbioma-2025.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/12/fibromialgia-microbioma-2025.html</guid>
        
        <category>Fibromialgia</category>
        
        <category>Microbioma</category>
        
        <category>Dor crônica</category>
        
        <category>Pesquisa clínica</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine 2020–2024: Five Years of Breakthroughs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last five years, the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine has recognized discoveries that have revolutionized our understanding of genetics, molecular biology, and medicine. Below is a summary table of the laureates, their countries, and the main themes:
  &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Theme&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Laureates&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Country&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2020&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Discovery of Hepatitis C virus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Harvey J. Alter, Michael Houghton, Charles M. Rice&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA, UK, Canada&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2021&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Receptors for temperature and touch&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;David Julius, Ardem Patapoutian&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA, Lebanon/USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2022&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Genomes of extinct hominins and human evolution&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Svante Pääbo&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sweden, Germany&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2023&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;mRNA vaccine technology&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Katalin Karikó, Drew Weissman&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hungary/USA, USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2024&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Discovery of microRNA and gene regulation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Victor Ambros, Gary Ruvkun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;laureates-and-themes&quot;&gt;Laureates and Themes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2020-discovery-of-hepatitis-c-virus&quot;&gt;2020: Discovery of Hepatitis C Virus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureates:&lt;/strong&gt; Harvey J. Alter (USA), Michael Houghton (UK/Canada), Charles M. Rice (USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theme:&lt;/strong&gt; Identification of the hepatitis C virus, enabling blood tests and curative therapies for a major cause of chronic hepatitis and liver cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before these discoveries, millions were infected through contaminated blood transfusions, with no precise diagnosis. The laureates’ work enabled highly sensitive blood tests, eliminating transfusion-related transmission and leading to antivirals that now cure hepatitis C in over 95% of cases. &lt;label for=&quot;antiviral-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;antiviral-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Antiviral: a type of medication used to treat viral infections by inhibiting the development or replication of viruses. Antivirals are distinct from antibiotics, which target bacteria.&lt;/span&gt;
 The global impact is profound, with the World Health Organization targeting hepatitis C elimination as a public health threat.
&lt;label for=&quot;gene-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;gene-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Gene: a segment of DNA that encodes a molecule (usually a protein) with a specific function. Genes are the units of inheritance first hypothesized by Mendel and named by the Danish botanist Wilhelm Johannsen in 1909. Genes make up only a small fraction of a cell’s DNA; most DNA does not code for proteins and is not part of genes. The phrase “one gene, one protein” summarizes the central dogma of biology: genetic information is transferred from DNA to RNA and then to a protein.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;label for=&quot;who-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;who-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;World Health Organization (WHO): a specialized agency of the United Nations responsible for international public health. Founded in 1948, the WHO coordinates global health responses, sets standards, and provides guidance on health issues, disease prevention, and control.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/ba/Dr._Harvey_J._Alter_wins_2020_Nobel_Prize_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Dr._Harvey_J._Alter_wins_2020_Nobel_Prize_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Harvey J. Alter&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Harvey J. Alter. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvey_J._Alter&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e4/Prof_Michael_Houghton.jpg/250px-Prof_Michael_Houghton.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Michael Houghton&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Michael Houghton. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Houghton&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6d/Charles_M._Rice.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Charles M. Rice&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Charles M. Rice. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_M._Rice&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2021-receptors-for-temperature-and-touch&quot;&gt;2021: Receptors for Temperature and Touch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureates:&lt;/strong&gt; David Julius (USA), Ardem Patapoutian (Lebanon/USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theme:&lt;/strong&gt; Discovery of how our bodies sense temperature and mechanical stimuli, through TRP and Piezo receptors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julius used capsaicin (the spicy compound in chili peppers) to identify the TRPV1 receptor, responsible for heat sensation. Patapoutian discovered Piezo1 and Piezo2 receptors, essential for touch and pressure. These findings opened new fields in sensory neuroscience, directly impacting the development of painkillers and treatments for chronic pain, and explaining rare genetic diseases related to proprioception. &lt;label for=&quot;pain-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;pain-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Pain: an unpleasant sensory and emotional experience associated with actual or potential tissue damage. Pain can be acute (short-term) or chronic (long-lasting), and is a major focus of medical research and treatment.&lt;/span&gt;
 Julius and Patapoutian also collaborated and co-published, highlighting the interconnectedness of the scientific community.
&lt;label for=&quot;receptor-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;receptor-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Receptor: a protein molecule, usually found on the surface of a cell, that receives and responds to chemical signals from outside the cell. Receptors are essential for communication between cells and for the body’s response to hormones, neurotransmitters, and other signaling molecules.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/49/Dr_David_Julius_by_christopher_michel_in_2022_04_%28cropped2%29.jpg/250px-Dr_David_Julius_by_christopher_michel_in_2022_04_%28cropped2%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;David Julius&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;David Julius. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Julius&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e6/Ardem_Patapoutian_by_C_Michel_67_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Ardem_Patapoutian_by_C_Michel_67_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ardem Patapoutian&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ardem Patapoutian. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ardem_Patapoutian&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2022-genomes-of-extinct-hominins-and-human-evolution&quot;&gt;2022: Genomes of Extinct Hominins and Human Evolution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureate:&lt;/strong&gt; Svante Pääbo (Sweden/Germany)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theme:&lt;/strong&gt; Sequencing the Neanderthal genome and discovering Denisovans, revealing interbreeding with Homo sapiens and transforming our understanding of human evolution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pääbo founded paleogenomics, overcoming technical challenges to extract and sequence ancient DNA. His team showed that modern humans inherited genes from Neanderthals and Denisovans, influencing immunity, metabolism, and even responses to diseases like COVID-19. &lt;label for=&quot;immune-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;immune-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Immune system: the complex network of cells, tissues, and organs that defends the body against infections and diseases. It recognizes and neutralizes pathogens such as bacteria, viruses, and other foreign substances.&lt;/span&gt;
 For example, Neanderthal gene variants affect blood clotting (&lt;em&gt;F5&lt;/em&gt;), pain sensitivity (&lt;em&gt;SCN9A&lt;/em&gt;), and antiviral immunity (OAS gene cluster), while a Denisovan gene (&lt;em&gt;EPAS1&lt;/em&gt;) increases altitude tolerance in Himalayan populations. Pääbo’s work inspired multidisciplinary collaborations, and his son, Hugo Zeberg, also works in the field, showing family continuity in research.
&lt;label for=&quot;genome-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;genome-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Genome: the complete genetic material of an organism. It includes all genes, non-coding DNA sequences (which are not genes), and also the genetic material in organelles such as mitochondria. For example, the 22,000 human genes make up less than 2% of the human genome.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/26/Professor_Svante_Paabo_ForMemRS_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Professor_Svante_Paabo_ForMemRS_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Svante Pääbo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Svante Pääbo. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Svante_P%C3%A4%C3%A4bo&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2023-mrna-vaccine-technology&quot;&gt;2023: mRNA Vaccine Technology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureates:&lt;/strong&gt; Katalin Karikó (Hungary/USA), Drew Weissman (USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theme:&lt;/strong&gt; Discoveries enabling the development of mRNA vaccines, crucial in the fight against COVID-19 and opening new avenues for vaccines and therapies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karikó and Weissman faced years of skepticism and lack of funding, but their persistence led to the modification of mRNA to avoid inflammatory responses, making clinical use possible. The technology was rapidly applied to COVID-19 vaccines, setting a record for speed and saving millions of lives. Today, mRNA platforms are being tested for cancer, HIV, and autoimmune diseases. Karikó and Weissman collaborated directly, and their stories inspire scientists about the importance of resilience and international collaboration.
&lt;label for=&quot;mrna-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;mrna-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;mRNA (messenger RNA): a type of RNA that carries genetic information from DNA to the cell’s protein-making machinery (ribosomes). mRNA serves as the template for protein synthesis, playing a central role in the expression of genetic information.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/3e/Katalin_Karik%C3%B3_at_the_United_States_Embassy_Sweden%2C_2023_Nobel_Reception_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Katalin_Karik%C3%BÓ_at_the_United_States_Embassy_Sweden%2C_2023_Nobel_Reception_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Katalin Karikó&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Katalin Karikó. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katalin_Karik%C3%B3&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e2/Drew_Weissman%2C_2023_Nobel_Laureate_in_Medicine_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Drew_Weissman%2C_2023_Nobel_Laureate_in_Medicine_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drew Weissman&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Drew Weissman. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drew_Weissman&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2024-discovery-of-microrna-and-gene-regulation&quot;&gt;2024: Discovery of microRNA and Gene Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureates:&lt;/strong&gt; Victor Ambros (USA), Gary Ruvkun (USA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theme:&lt;/strong&gt; Discovery of microRNAs, small RNA molecules that regulate gene expression, with profound implications for development, disease, and therapeutics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambros and Ruvkun, who worked in parallel and also collaborated, showed that small non-coding RNAs control gene expression in animals and humans. The microRNA field exploded, revealing roles in cancer, heart disease, neurodegeneration, and immunity. The first RNA interference therapy approved for clinical use (patisiran, for hereditary amyloidosis) is a direct result of these discoveries. RNA-based therapies are now in clinical trials, and the discovery changed our view of so-called “junk DNA.” Both laureates have collaborated with other Nobel winners, such as Robert Horvitz.
&lt;label for=&quot;dna-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;dna-en&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid): a complex organic molecule, DNA is a polymer—a chain made up of simpler molecules. It is composed of four types of molecules: adenine, cytosine, guanine, and thymine, which are nucleotides, the monomers (individual parts) that make up the DNA polymer. Each DNA molecule consists of two long strands of nucleotides that coil into a double helix. The order of nucleotides along the DNA strand is not random; it forms a code, called the genetic code, which stores the information needed to produce all the proteins in a cell. In fact, the DNA in each cell contains the information necessary to reproduce the entire organism.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/de/Victor_Ambros%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine.jpg/250px-Victor_Ambros%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Victor Ambros&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Victor Ambros. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victor_Ambros&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/24/Gary_Ruvkun%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine_3_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Gary_Ruvkun%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine_3_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gary Ruvkun&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Gary Ruvkun. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_Ruvkun&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-unites-the-themes-and-laureates&quot;&gt;What Unites the Themes and Laureates?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molecular and Genetic Focus:&lt;/strong&gt; All prizes highlight advances in molecular biology, genetics, and the mechanisms underlying health and disease.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Translational Impact:&lt;/strong&gt; Each discovery has led to new diagnostics, therapies, or fundamental shifts in biomedical science.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Collaboration:&lt;/strong&gt; Many laureates have worked across countries and institutions, reflecting the global nature of modern science.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diversity of Backgrounds:&lt;/strong&gt; Laureates include immigrants and those with multicultural backgrounds (e.g., Karikó from Hungary, Patapoutian from Lebanon).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Active Scientists:&lt;/strong&gt; As of June 2025, all laureates are alive and most remain active in research or academia, except Michael Houghton, who retired but is still alive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interrelations:&lt;/strong&gt; Several laureates have collaborated with each other or with other Nobel winners, showing the importance of scientific networks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;controversies-and-curiosities&quot;&gt;Controversies and Curiosities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020:&lt;/strong&gt; Debate over the exclusion of other contributors to hepatitis C research, but the main discoverers were recognized.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021:&lt;/strong&gt; No major controversies; the discoveries were widely accepted and celebrated.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2022:&lt;/strong&gt; Some discussion about the focus on ancient DNA, but Pääbo’s pioneering work was universally acknowledged.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2023:&lt;/strong&gt; The rapid development and deployment of mRNA vaccines during the COVID-19 pandemic sparked public debate, but the scientific achievement was clear. Karikó’s long struggle for recognition before the Nobel was widely discussed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2024:&lt;/strong&gt; The microRNA field is vast, and some researchers contributed to its development, but Ambros and Ruvkun’s foundational discoveries were decisive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications-for-the-present-and-future&quot;&gt;Implications for the Present and Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The awarded technologies and discoveries already have a profound impact today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hepatitis C:&lt;/strong&gt; The disease is close to eradication in several countries thanks to tests and treatments derived from the 2020 discoveries.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/hepatitis-c&quot;&gt;Learn more: WHO - Hepatitis C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mRNA Vaccines:&lt;/strong&gt; The mRNA platform is being adapted for vaccines against cancer, HIV, influenza, and autoimmune diseases, with clinical trials underway. The record speed of COVID-19 vaccine development demonstrated the potential of this technology.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02483-w&quot;&gt;Nature - mRNA vaccines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;microRNA and RNAi:&lt;/strong&gt; The first RNA interference therapy approved for clinical use was patisiran (Onpattro), for hereditary transthyretin amyloidosis, in 2018. Since then, six RNAi therapies have been FDA-approved, expanding treatment options for genetic and chronic diseases and potentially revolutionizing personalized medicine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/drugs/spotlight-cder-science/new-class-drugs-fulfills-promise-rna-based-medicine&quot;&gt;FDA - RNAi therapies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41573-024-00912-9&quot;&gt;Nature Reviews Drug Discovery - RNAi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evolutionary Genetics:&lt;/strong&gt; Genes inherited from Neanderthals, such as &lt;em&gt;F5&lt;/em&gt; (clotting), &lt;em&gt;SCN9A&lt;/em&gt; (pain sensitivity), and variants in the &lt;em&gt;OAS&lt;/em&gt; cluster (antiviral immunity), affect current human traits. A Denisovan gene, &lt;em&gt;EPAS1&lt;/em&gt;, increases altitude tolerance in Tibetans. These findings help explain disease susceptibility and human adaptations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-020-2818-3&quot;&gt;Nature - Neanderthal DNA and COVID-19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/tibetans-inherited-high-altitude-gene-ancient-human&quot;&gt;Science - Denisovan gene and altitude&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sensory Neuroscience:&lt;/strong&gt; New painkillers and treatments for chronic pain and neurological diseases are being developed based on the receptors discovered in 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/hot-and-cool-research-wins-nobel-prize-physiology-or-medicine&quot;&gt;Science - Pain research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, these discoveries are expected to continue transforming medicine, making diagnostics more precise, treatments more personalized, and deepening our understanding of life’s fundamental mechanisms. International exchange, multidisciplinary collaboration, and the value of basic science have proven essential for advances that benefit all humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last five years of Nobel Prizes in Medicine reflect a golden era for molecular biology and genetics, with discoveries that have immediate impact on human health and deepen our understanding of life itself. Scientific research is fundamental to human well-being and societal progress. However, the rise of scientific denialism and misinformation is concerning, as it threatens historic achievements and hinders access to treatments and vaccines. It is therefore essential to value and disseminate quality, evidence-based information, so that the benefits of science reach everyone and society can make informed decisions about health and public policy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/10/nobel-medicine-20-24.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/10/nobel-medicine-20-24.html</guid>
        
        <category>Physiology or Medicine</category>
        
        <category>Nobel Prize</category>
        
        <category>Science History</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Prêmio Nobel de Fisiologia ou Medicina 2020–2024: Cinco Anos de Revoluções</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nos últimos cinco anos, o Prêmio Nobel de Fisiologia ou Medicina reconheceu descobertas que revolucionaram a genética, a biologia molecular e a medicina. Veja abaixo uma tabela-resumo dos laureados, seus países e os principais temas:
  &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Ano&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Tema&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Laureados&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;País(es)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2020&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Descoberta do vírus da Hepatite C&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Harvey J. Alter, Michael Houghton, Charles M. Rice&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;EUA, Reino Unido, Canadá&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2021&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Receptores de temperatura e tato&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;David Julius, Ardem Patapoutian&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;EUA, Líbano/EUA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2022&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Genomas de hominídeos extintos e evolução&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Svante Pääbo&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Suécia, Alemanha&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2023&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tecnologia de vacinas de mRNA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Katalin Karikó, Drew Weissman&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hungria/EUA, EUA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2024&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Descoberta do microRNA e regulação gênica&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Victor Ambros, Gary Ruvkun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;EUA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;laureados-e-temas&quot;&gt;Laureados e Temas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2020-descoberta-do-vírus-da-hepatite-c&quot;&gt;2020: Descoberta do Vírus da Hepatite C&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureados:&lt;/strong&gt; Harvey J. Alter (EUA), Michael Houghton (Reino Unido/Canadá), Charles M. Rice (EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tema:&lt;/strong&gt; Identificação do vírus da hepatite C, permitindo testes sanguíneos e terapias curativas para uma das principais causas de hepatite crônica e câncer de fígado.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antes dessas descobertas, milhões de pessoas eram infectadas por transfusões de sangue contaminado, sem diagnóstico preciso. O trabalho dos laureados permitiu o desenvolvimento de testes altamente sensíveis, tornando possível eliminar a transmissão do vírus por transfusões e levando ao desenvolvimento de antivirais que hoje curam a hepatite C em mais de 95% dos casos. &lt;label for=&quot;antiviral-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;antiviral-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Antiviral: medicamento utilizado para tratar infecções virais, inibindo o desenvolvimento ou a replicação dos vírus. Antivirais são diferentes de antibióticos, que atuam contra bactérias.&lt;/span&gt;
 O impacto é global, com a Organização Mundial da Saúde estabelecendo a meta de erradicação da hepatite C como problema de saúde pública.
&lt;label for=&quot;gene&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;gene&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Gene (&lt;em&gt;gr gonos&lt;/em&gt; = geração, semente): trecho de DNA que
  codifica uma molécula (proteína) com uma função. Correspondem às unidades de herança
  hipotetizadas por Mendel e denominadas de genes pelo botânico dinamarquês
  Johannsen em 1905. Constitui uma minoria do DNA de uma célula. A maior parte do DNA
  não codifica proteínas e, portanto, não faz parte de genes. A expressão “um gene,
  uma proteína” resume o &lt;em&gt;dogma central da biologia&lt;/em&gt;, de que a informação genética
  é transferida (codificada) do DNA para o RNA e deste para uma proteína
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;label for=&quot;oms-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;oms-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Organização Mundial da Saúde (OMS): agência especializada das Nações Unidas responsável pela saúde pública internacional. Fundada em 1948, a OMS coordena respostas globais, define padrões e fornece orientações sobre saúde, prevenção e controle de doenças.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/ba/Dr._Harvey_J._Alter_wins_2020_Nobel_Prize_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Dr._Harvey_J._Alter_wins_2020_Nobel_Prize_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Harvey J. Alter&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Harvey J. Alter. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvey_J._Alter&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e4/Prof_Michael_Houghton.jpg/250px-Prof_Michael_Houghton.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Michael Houghton&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Michael Houghton. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Houghton&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6d/Charles_M._Rice.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Charles M. Rice&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Charles M. Rice. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_M._Rice&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2021-receptores-de-temperatura-e-tato&quot;&gt;2021: Receptores de Temperatura e Tato&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureados:&lt;/strong&gt; David Julius (EUA), Ardem Patapoutian (Líbano/EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tema:&lt;/strong&gt; Descoberta de como o corpo sente temperatura e estímulos mecânicos, através dos receptores TRP e Piezo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julius utilizou a capsaicina (composto da pimenta) para identificar o receptor TRPV1, responsável pela sensação de calor. Patapoutian identificou os receptores Piezo1 e Piezo2, essenciais para a sensação de toque e pressão. Essas descobertas abriram novas áreas na neurociência sensorial, com impacto direto no desenvolvimento de analgésicos e tratamentos para dor crônica, além de explicar doenças genéticas raras ligadas à propriocepção. &lt;label for=&quot;pain-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;pain-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Dor: experiência sensorial e emocional desagradável associada a dano real ou potencial aos tecidos. Pode ser aguda (curta duração) ou crônica (longa duração), sendo um dos principais focos de pesquisa e tratamento em medicina.&lt;/span&gt;
 Julius e Patapoutian também colaboraram e publicaram juntos em alguns momentos, mostrando a interconexão da comunidade científica.
&lt;label for=&quot;receptor-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;receptor-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Receptor: molécula (geralmente uma proteína) presente na superfície ou interior das células, responsável por receber e responder a sinais químicos do ambiente. Receptores são essenciais para a comunicação entre células e para a resposta do organismo a hormônios, neurotransmissores e outros sinais.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/49/Dr_David_Julius_by_christopher_michel_in_2022_04_%28cropped2%29.jpg/250px-Dr_David_Julius_by_christopher_michel_in_2022_04_%28cropped2%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;David Julius&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;David Julius. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Julius&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e6/Ardem_Patapoutian_by_C_Michel_67_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Ardem_Patapoutian_by_C_Michel_67_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ardem Patapoutian&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ardem Patapoutian. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ardem_Patapoutian&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2022-genomas-de-hominídeos-extintos-e-evolução-humana&quot;&gt;2022: Genomas de Hominídeos Extintos e Evolução Humana&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureado:&lt;/strong&gt; Svante Pääbo (Suécia/Alemanha)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tema:&lt;/strong&gt; Sequenciamento do genoma neandertal e descoberta dos denisovanos, revelando cruzamentos com Homo sapiens e transformando a compreensão da evolução humana.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pääbo fundou a paleogenômica, superando desafios técnicos para extrair e sequenciar DNA antigo. Sua equipe mostrou que humanos modernos herdaram genes de neandertais e denisovanos, influenciando imunidade, metabolismo e até resposta a doenças como COVID-19. &lt;label for=&quot;immune-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;immune-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Sistema imunológico: rede complexa de células, tecidos e órgãos que defende o organismo contra infecções e doenças. Reconhece e neutraliza patógenos como bactérias, vírus e outras substâncias estranhas.&lt;/span&gt;
 Por exemplo, variantes de genes neandertais afetam a coagulação do sangue e a sensibilidade à dor, enquanto um gene herdado dos denisovanos aumenta a resistência à altitude em populações do Himalaia. O trabalho de Pääbo inspirou colaborações multidisciplinares entre genética, arqueologia e antropologia, e seu filho, Hugo Zeberg, também atua na área, mostrando continuidade familiar na pesquisa.
&lt;label for=&quot;genoma&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;genoma&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Genoma: material genético de um organismo. Inclui todos os
  genes, as sequências de DNA &lt;em&gt;não codificante&lt;/em&gt; (que não são genes) e também o
  material genético em organelas como as mitocôndrias. Por exemplo, os 22 mil genes
  humanos constituem menos de 2% do genoma humano.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/26/Professor_Svante_Paabo_ForMemRS_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Professor_Svante_Paabo_ForMemRS_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Svante Pääbo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Svante Pääbo. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Svante_P%C3%A4%C3%A4bo&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2023-tecnologia-de-vacinas-de-mrna&quot;&gt;2023: Tecnologia de Vacinas de mRNA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureados:&lt;/strong&gt; Katalin Karikó (Hungria/EUA), Drew Weissman (EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tema:&lt;/strong&gt; Descobertas que permitiram o desenvolvimento das vacinas de mRNA, fundamentais no combate à COVID-19 e abrindo novas possibilidades para vacinas e terapias.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karikó e Weissman enfrentaram anos de descrédito e falta de financiamento, mas sua persistência levou à modificação do mRNA para evitar resposta inflamatória, tornando possível o uso clínico. A tecnologia foi rapidamente aplicada nas vacinas contra COVID-19, batendo recorde de velocidade no desenvolvimento de uma vacina eficaz e salvando milhões de vidas. Hoje, a plataforma de mRNA está sendo testada para vacinas contra câncer, HIV e doenças autoimunes. Karikó e Weissman colaboraram diretamente, e suas trajetórias inspiram cientistas sobre a importância da resiliência e da colaboração internacional.
&lt;label for=&quot;mrna-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;mrna-pt&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;mRNA (RNA mensageiro): tipo de RNA que carrega a informação genética do DNA até a maquinaria celular responsável pela produção de proteínas (ribossomos). O mRNA serve como molde para a síntese de proteínas, desempenhando papel central na expressão gênica.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/3e/Katalin_Karik%C3%B3_at_the_United_States_Embassy_Sweden%2C_2023_Nobel_Reception_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Katalin_Karik%C3%BÓ_at_the_United_States_Embassy_Sweden%2C_2023_Nobel_Reception_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Katalin Karikó&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Katalin Karikó. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katalin_Karik%C3%B3&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e2/Drew_Weissman%2C_2023_Nobel_Laureate_in_Medicine_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Drew_Weissman%2C_2023_Nobel_Laureate_in_Medicine_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drew Weissman&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Drew Weissman. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drew_Weissman&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2024-descoberta-do-microrna-e-regulação-gênica&quot;&gt;2024: Descoberta do microRNA e Regulação Gênica&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laureados:&lt;/strong&gt; Victor Ambros (EUA), Gary Ruvkun (EUA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tema:&lt;/strong&gt; Descoberta dos microRNAs, pequenas moléculas de RNA que regulam a expressão gênica, com impacto profundo no desenvolvimento, doenças e terapias.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambros e Ruvkun, que trabalharam em paralelo e também colaboraram, mostraram que pequenos RNAs não codificantes controlam a expressão de genes em animais e humanos. O campo do microRNA explodiu, revelando seu papel em câncer, doenças cardíacas, neurodegenerativas e imunidade. A primeira terapia de interferência de RNA aprovada para uso clínico (patisiran, para amiloidose hereditária) é um exemplo direto do impacto dessas descobertas. Terapias baseadas em microRNA já estão em testes clínicos, e a descoberta mudou a visão sobre o chamado “DNA lixo”. Ambos os laureados têm histórico de colaboração com outros ganhadores do Nobel, como Robert Horvitz.
&lt;label for=&quot;dna&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;dna&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;DNA (ou ADN = ácido desoxiribonucléico): molécula orgânica
  complexa, o DNA é um polímero, uma cadeia formada da união de moléculas mais simples.
  Ele é formado de 4 tipos de moléculas: adenina, citosina, guanina e timina, as
  quais são &lt;em&gt;nucleotídeos&lt;/em&gt;, os monômeros (partes individuais que compõem, em conjunto,
  um polímero) do DNA. Cada molécula de DNA é formada pela união de duas longas
  fitas de nucleotídeos, que se enrolam em espiral. A posição dos nucleotídeos
  ao longo da fita de DNA não é casual, ela forma um código, chamado de &lt;em&gt;código
  genético&lt;/em&gt;, que armazena as informações necessárias para a produção de todas as
  proteínas de uma célula. Na verdade, o DNA contido em cada célula carrega as
  informações necessárias para reproduzir &lt;em&gt;todo&lt;/em&gt; o organismo.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/de/Victor_Ambros%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine.jpg/250px-Victor_Ambros%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Victor Ambros&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Victor Ambros. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victor_Ambros&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/24/Gary_Ruvkun%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine_3_%28cropped%29.jpg/250px-Gary_Ruvkun%2C_2024_Nobel_Prize_Laureate_in_Medicine_3_%28cropped%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gary Ruvkun&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Gary Ruvkun. Fonte: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_Ruvkun&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;o-que-une-os-temas-e-os-laureados&quot;&gt;O que une os temas e os laureados?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foco molecular e genético:&lt;/strong&gt; Todos os prêmios destacam avanços em biologia molecular, genética e mecanismos fundamentais da saúde e doença.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impacto translacional:&lt;/strong&gt; Cada descoberta levou a novos diagnósticos, terapias ou mudanças fundamentais na ciência biomédica.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colaboração internacional:&lt;/strong&gt; Muitos laureados trabalharam em diferentes países e instituições, refletindo a natureza global da ciência atual.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diversidade de trajetórias:&lt;/strong&gt; Há imigrantes e trajetórias multiculturais (ex: Karikó da Hungria, Patapoutian do Líbano).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cientistas ativos:&lt;/strong&gt; Em junho de 2025, todos os laureados estão vivos e a maioria segue ativa na pesquisa ou na academia, exceto Michael Houghton, que se aposentou, mas está vivo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interrelações:&lt;/strong&gt; Vários laureados colaboraram entre si ou com outros ganhadores do Nobel, mostrando a importância das redes científicas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;controvérsias-e-curiosidades&quot;&gt;Controvérsias e Curiosidades&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020:&lt;/strong&gt; Houve debate sobre a exclusão de outros colaboradores na pesquisa da hepatite C, mas os principais descobridores foram reconhecidos.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021:&lt;/strong&gt; Sem grandes controvérsias; as descobertas foram amplamente aceitas e celebradas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2022:&lt;/strong&gt; Discussão sobre o foco em DNA antigo, mas o pioneirismo de Pääbo foi universalmente reconhecido.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2023:&lt;/strong&gt; O desenvolvimento rápido das vacinas de mRNA gerou debates públicos, mas o feito científico foi claro. A longa luta de Karikó por reconhecimento antes do Nobel foi muito comentada.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2024:&lt;/strong&gt; O campo do microRNA é vasto e outros cientistas contribuíram, mas Ambros e Ruvkun fizeram as descobertas fundamentais.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implicações-para-o-presente-e-o-futuro&quot;&gt;Implicações para o Presente e o Futuro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As tecnologias e descobertas premiadas já têm impacto profundo no presente:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hepatite C:&lt;/strong&gt; A doença está próxima de ser erradicada em vários países graças a testes e tratamentos derivados das descobertas de 2020.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/hepatitis-c&quot;&gt;Saiba mais: OMS - Hepatite C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vacinas de mRNA:&lt;/strong&gt; A plataforma de mRNA está sendo adaptada para vacinas contra câncer, HIV, gripe e doenças autoimunes, com ensaios clínicos em andamento. O recorde de velocidade no desenvolvimento da vacina contra COVID-19 mostrou o potencial dessa tecnologia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02483-w&quot;&gt;Nature - mRNA vaccines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MicroRNA e RNAi:&lt;/strong&gt; A primeira terapia de interferência de RNA aprovada para uso clínico foi o patisiran (Onpattro), para amiloidose hereditária por transtirretina, em 2018. Desde então, já existem seis terapias de interferência de RNA aprovadas pelo FDA, ampliando as possibilidades de tratamento para doenças genéticas e crônicas e podendo revolucionar a medicina personalizada.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/drugs/spotlight-cder-science/new-class-drugs-fulfills-promise-rna-based-medicine&quot;&gt;FDA - RNAi therapies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41573-024-00912-9&quot;&gt;Nature Reviews Drug Discovery - RNAi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genética evolutiva:&lt;/strong&gt; Genes herdados de neandertais, como o &lt;em&gt;F5&lt;/em&gt; (coagulação), &lt;em&gt;SCN9A&lt;/em&gt; (sensibilidade à dor) e variantes do cluster &lt;em&gt;OAS&lt;/em&gt; (imunidade antiviral), afetam características humanas atuais. Um gene de denisovanos, &lt;em&gt;EPAS1&lt;/em&gt;, aumenta a resistência à altitude em tibetanos. Esses achados ajudam a entender susceptibilidade a doenças e adaptações humanas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-020-2818-3&quot;&gt;Nature - Neanderthal DNA and COVID-19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/tibetans-inherited-high-altitude-gene-ancient-human&quot;&gt;Science - Denisovan gene and altitude&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Neurociência sensorial:&lt;/strong&gt; Novos analgésicos e tratamentos para dor crônica e doenças neurológicas estão sendo desenvolvidos com base nos receptores descobertos em 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/hot-and-cool-research-wins-nobel-prize-physiology-or-medicine&quot;&gt;Science - Pain research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No futuro, espera-se que essas descobertas continuem a transformar a medicina, tornando diagnósticos mais precisos, tratamentos mais personalizados e ampliando a compreensão dos mecanismos fundamentais da vida. O intercâmbio internacional, a colaboração multidisciplinar e a valorização da ciência básica mostraram ser essenciais para avanços que beneficiam toda a humanidade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusão&quot;&gt;Conclusão&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Os últimos cinco anos do Nobel de Medicina refletem uma era dourada da biologia molecular e genética, com descobertas de impacto imediato na saúde humana e que aprofundam nossa compreensão da vida. A pesquisa científica é fundamental para o bem-estar das pessoas e para o avanço da sociedade. No entanto, o crescimento do negacionismo científico e da desinformação preocupa, pois ameaça conquistas históricas e dificulta o acesso a tratamentos e vacinas. Por isso, é essencial valorizar e divulgar informação de qualidade, baseada em evidências, para que os benefícios da ciência cheguem a todos e para que a sociedade possa tomar decisões informadas sobre saúde e políticas públicas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/10/nobel-medicina-20-24.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2025/06/10/nobel-medicina-20-24.html</guid>
        
        <category>Fisiologia ou Medicina</category>
        
        <category>Nobel</category>
        
        <category>História da Ciência</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2024 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine: The Silent Revolution of MicroRNA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2024 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine was awarded to the American scientists &lt;strong&gt;Victor Ambros&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Gary Ruvkun&lt;/strong&gt;, for their discovery of microRNA (miRNA) and its fundamental role in post-transcriptional gene regulation. [1, 2]
  &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pioneering research of Ambros and Ruvkun revealed a new and sophisticated layer of genetic control, demonstrating that small RNA molecules, once considered irrelevant, play a crucial role in how and when genes are activated. [3] This discovery not only rewrote fundamental parts of molecular biology textbooks but also opened vast new avenues for understanding and treating complex diseases, such as cancer and heart disease. [4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all began in the 1980s, when both scientists, then postdoctoral fellows in the laboratory of H. Robert Horvitz (a 2002 Nobel laureate), were studying the development of the nematode worm &lt;em&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/em&gt;. [2] This simple organism, with its precisely mapped cellular development, was the perfect model for investigating the mysteries of gene regulation. [5] Working independently but focused on the same puzzle, they investigated how certain genes governed the worm’s larval stage transitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was in Victor Ambros’s laboratory that the first piece of the puzzle was found. In 1993, his team discovered that the &lt;em&gt;lin-4&lt;/em&gt; gene did not encode a protein, as was expected, but rather a small RNA molecule, approximately 22 nucleotides long. [6] This molecule bound to a specific region of the messenger RNA (mRNA) of another gene, &lt;em&gt;lin-14&lt;/em&gt;, preventing its translation into a protein. [7] This was an entirely new regulatory mechanism, termed post-transcriptional regulation. [1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simultaneously, Gary Ruvkun’s laboratory made a crucial complementary discovery. He confirmed the proposed mechanism of action, showing how the small &lt;em&gt;lin-4&lt;/em&gt; RNA effectively silenced the &lt;em&gt;lin-14&lt;/em&gt; mRNA. [7] Years later, in 2000, Ruvkun’s lab discovered another of these molecules, &lt;em&gt;let-7&lt;/em&gt;, and, surprisingly, demonstrated that it was evolutionarily conserved across numerous species, including humans. [8] This signaled that this was not a quirk of worms but a fundamental biological mechanism. [2, 3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discoveries of Ambros and Ruvkun revealed that portions of the genome once considered “junk” actually contained functional treasures. Today, we know that the human genome encodes over a thousand types of microRNAs. [2] These molecules are essential for development, metabolism, cell differentiation, and immune function. The malfunction of microRNAs is implicated in numerous pathologies, and the development of miRNA-based therapies is one of the most promising areas of modern medicine. [4, 9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2024 Nobel Prize recognizes a truly fundamental discovery that has drastically changed our understanding of how genetic information is orchestrated to create the complexity of life. [1] The work of Victor Ambros and Gary Ruvkun has opened a new universe in biology, the implications of which for human health are still being explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a7/MiRNA.svg/960px-MiRNA.svg.png?20190519102305&quot; alt=&quot;Figure: A schematic showing the formation and function of micro RNA. Credit: Kelvinsong, CC BY 3.0 &amp;lt;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0&amp;gt;, via Wikimedia Commons&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/2024/press-release/&quot;&gt;1 - The Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine 2024 - Press Release (NobelPrize.org)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/2024/advanced-information/&quot;&gt;2 - Scientific Background: Discoveries of microRNA (NobelPrize.org)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2024/oct/07/nobel-prize-in-medicine-awarded-to-scientists-for-work-on-microrna-victor-ambros-gary-ruvkun&quot;&gt;3 - Nobel prize in medicine awarded to scientists for work on microRNA - The Guardian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-03212-9&quot;&gt;4 - Medicine Nobel awarded for gene-regulating ‘microRNAs’ - Nature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statnews.com/2024/10/07/nobel-prize-medicine-ambros-ruvkun-awarded-prize/&quot;&gt;5 - 2024 Nobel prize in medicine: Ruvkun, Ambros win for discovery of microRNA - STAT News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(93)90529-y&quot;&gt;6 - Lee, R., Feinbaum, R. &amp;amp; Ambros, V. (1993). The &lt;em&gt;C. elegans&lt;/em&gt; heterochronic gene &lt;em&gt;lin-4&lt;/em&gt; encodes small RNAs with antisense complementarity to &lt;em&gt;lin-14&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Cell&lt;/em&gt;, 75(5), 843-854.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(93)90530-4&quot;&gt;7 - Wightman, B., Ha, I. &amp;amp; Ruvkun, G. (1993). Posttranscriptional regulation of the heterochronic gene &lt;em&gt;lin-14&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;em&gt;lin-4&lt;/em&gt; mediates temporal pattern formation in &lt;em&gt;C. elegans&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Cell&lt;/em&gt;, 75(5), 855-862.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/35040556&quot;&gt;8 - Pasquinelli, A. E., et al. (2000). Conservation of the sequence and temporal expression of &lt;em&gt;let-7&lt;/em&gt; heterochronic regulatory RNA. &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;, 408(6808), 86-89.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/nrd.2016.246&quot;&gt;9 - Rupaimoole, R., &amp;amp; Slack, F. J. (2017). MicroRNA therapeutics: towards a new era for the management of cancer and other diseases. &lt;em&gt;Nature Reviews Drug Discovery&lt;/em&gt;, 16(3), 203-222.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 20:22:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2024/10/07/nobel-medicine-24.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://fhcflx.github.io/ciencia-medica/2024/10/07/nobel-medicine-24.html</guid>
        
        <category>Physiology or Medicine</category>
        
        <category>Nobel Prize</category>
        
        <category>Genetics</category>
        
        <category>microRNA</category>
        
        <category>Gene Regulation</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
